<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
<eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="manosca" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/smitharchives/manosca44.html">manosca44</eadid>

<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Mary Ellen Chase Papers, 1893-1995</titleproper>
<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
<author>Finding aid prepared by Elizabeth Kates.</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Smith College Archives</publisher>
<address>
<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
</address>
<date>© 2007</date>
<p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Deborah A. Richards. 
<date>2007-03-12</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<frontmatter id="front"> 
<titlepage> 
<publisher>Smith College Archives</publisher> 
<titleproper>Mary Ellen Chase Papers, 1893-1995</titleproper>
<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle> 
<num>RG 42</num> 
<author>Elizabeth Kates</author> 
<date>1999, 2001</date> 
<p>© 2007 Smith College. All rights reserved.</p> 
</titlepage> 
</frontmatter> 

<archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<did id="main">
<head>Collection Overview</head>
<origination label="Creator:">
<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Chase, Mary Ellen, 1887-1973</persname>
</origination>
<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Mary Ellen Chase Papers</unittitle> <unitdate label="Dates:">1893-1995</unitdate>

<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="manosca">RG 42 UUID:1693ca76-6fdc-4d17-9785-9a54af9d5ce0</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
<extent encodinganalog="300$a">6 boxes</extent>
<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(9 linear ft.)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>

<repository label="Location:">
<corpname>Smith College Archives</corpname>
<address>
<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
Professor of English and novelist.  Contains biographical material, articles, correspondence, photographs, awards, financial information, reviews, and writings.
</abstract>
</did>



<bioghist id="bioghist">

<p>Mary Ellen Chase was born on February 24, 1887 in Blue Hill, Maine.  Her parents were deeply religious Protestants and Mary Ellen was one of eight children who received a thorough biblical education as well as an academic one.  She began writing at the age of sixteen and by her death on July 28, 1973, had published more than thirty essays, novels, and biographies.</p>
<p>At the age of nineteen, Chase took a leave from the University of Maine, where she was enrolled as an undergraduate, in order to teach in a one-room school in Buck's Harbor, Maine.  Following her graduation, she taught for three years in Wisconsin at a coeducational boarding school and later for two years at a private girls school in Chicago, Illinois.  At that point in time, Chase fell ill and was advised by her doctor that a move to Montana would improve her health.  During her time there, Chase taught public school and wrote two novels.</p>
<p>Upon full recovery, Chase took a teaching position at the University of Minnesota where she also studied and earned her MA in 1918 and later her Ph.D. in 1922.  In 1926 she was hired by Smith College where she taught courses on the English novel and the King James version of the Bible.  During her time at Smith, Chase became respected colleague, teacher, and friend to many.  Her courses, taken by English majors and non-English majors alike, were  some of the most popular on campus.  In addition, Chase's home on Paradise Road became a favorite place for her students to go for good conversation and cookies.</p>
<p>Despite her success as an author, teaching remained her true love throughout her career.  She viewed teaching as the main source of meaning in her life.  An extremely dedicated professor, Chase believed that "the personality of the teacher is more important than her intellectual attainments" and that "if the teacher has no enthusiasm for teaching and for subject matter, her students will learn little."  She was very excited about her field of expertise and hoped to similarly inspire her students.</p>
<p>Mary Ellen Chase has come to be known as one of the great American novelists.  Much of her work was inspired by her childhood in Maine and several of her novels are autobiographical.  <title render="italic">The Goodly Heritage</title> (1932) and <title render="italic">A Goodly Fellowship</title> (1939) are about her childhood and how she became a teacher, respectively.  Chase also wrote several books for children and more than one of her novels became best-sellers.</p>
<p>Chase's popularity and skill at public speaking earned her many invitations to lecture around the country.  She was awarded honorary degrees at the University of Maine, Bowdoin and Colby Colleges, Smith College, and Northeastern University.  Her work was also acknowledged by the Women's National Book Association in 1956 when she was awarded the Constance Lindsay Skinner Award.</p>
<p>After her retirement in 1955 at the age of sixty-eight, Chase continued to live on-campus with her long-time companion, Eleanor Duckett, and her dog, Gregory.  She spent summers in Maine at her home, "Windswept," and journeyed to England where she took Hebrew classes at Cambridge in order to better understand the Old Testament.  She also taught two adult education seminars on the Bible at Radcliffe College.  In 1968, Smith College acknowledged her dedication to the students and the College with a new dormitory, The Mary Ellen Chase House.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">

<p>The Mary Ellen Chase Papers include biographical material including articles, correspondence, photographs, awards, financial information, reviews and writings. The latter part, which comprises the bulk of the collection, includes Chases's books, articles, and lectures in manuscript, typescript, galley and final published form. Among her books are translations of many of her titles into several languages.
</p>
<p>The Smith College Archives houses other letters and photographs of Mary Ellen Chase that are not kept among the Mary Ellen Chase Papers, but with the papers of the other professors or students to whom the letters or pictures belonged. These are not listed in this finding aid, but can be located by consulting the card catalogue of the College Archives. The Mortimer Rare Book Room also holds some Mary Ellen Chase material, and likewise these holdings are not listed here, but can be found by consulting the catalogue of the Mortimer Rare Book Room.
</p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">

<p>This collection is organized into six series:</p>
<list>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser1">Biography</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser2">Photographs</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser3">Personal Correspondence</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser4">Professional Correspondence</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser5">Speeches</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser6">Publications</ref>
</item>
</list>
</arrangement>




<descgrp id="admin">
<head>Information on Use</head>
<descgrp>
<head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
<accessrestrict id="admin-access">
<p>The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict id="admin-use">
<p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish any material from the Mary Ellen Chase collection must be secured from the Smith College Archives as owners of the physical property. Literary copyright must be secured from Mary Ellen Chase's heirs.</p>
</userestrict>
</descgrp>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
<p>Mary Ellen Chase Papers, Box #, Smith College Archives.</p>
</prefercite>
<descgrp>
<head>History of the Collection</head>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
<p>The materials in the Mary Ellen Chase collection were given to the College Archives over a period of years between 1973 and 2001 by several donors, including Victor B. Harrison, Elizabeth Jacobsen, Helen K. Mills, Jenny V. Holtzermann, Deborah Wheeler, Professor Chase herself, and by her estate.</p> 
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
</descgrp>














<descgrp id="addinfo">
<head>Additional Information</head>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
<head>Related Material</head>
<list><item>
<extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/smitharchives/manosca57_main.html">42. Eleanor Shipley Duckett Papers</extref></item>
<item>Mary Ellen Chase Papers, Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College</item>
<item>See card catalogue of the Smith College Archives</item>
</list>
</relatedmaterial>
<bibliography id="add-biblio">
<list><head>Books by Mary Ellen Chase in the Smith College Archives</head>
<item><title render="italic">Abby Aldrich Rockefeller.</title> New York: The Macmillan Company, 1950</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Bible and the Common Reader.</title> New York: The Macmillan Company, 1944 (2 copies)</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Bible and the Common Reader.</title> Revised edition, 1952</item>

<item><title render="italic">Das Buch der Bucher, bie Bibel und der Mensch von Heute</title>. Stuttgart: Hans E. Verlag</item>

<item><title render="italic">Constructive Theme Writing for College Freshman</title>. New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1929</item>

<item><title render="italic">Constructive Theme Writing for College Freshman</title>. Revised edition, 1938</item>

<item><title render="italic">Dawn in Lyonesse</title>. New York: The Macmillan Company, 1938 (3 copies)</item>

<item><title render="italic">Dolly Moses: the Cat and the Clam Chowder.</title> New York: W.W. Norton and Company, 1964</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Edge of Darkness.</title> New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1957</item>

<item><title render="italic">Am Rande der Dunkel-Heit.</title> Munchen: Winkler-Verlag, 1964</item>

<item><title render="italic">Prakash-Reka.</title> Bambay: Kailas Prakashan, 1959 (Marathi language) (also in Iranian, Bengali and another language -- possibly Arabic)</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Girl from the Big Horn Country.</title> New York: A.L. Burt and Company, 1916</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Golden Ass and Other Essays.</title> New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1929 (2 copies)</item>

<item><title render="italic">A Goodly Fellowship.</title> New York: Macmillan and Company, 1939</item>

<item><title render="italic">La Joie d'Enseinger.</title> Paris: Bantam Books, 1959</item>

<item><title render="italic">La Joie d'Enseinger.</title> Bombay: Nav Lekhan Piublishers, 1962 (Marathi language)</item>

<item><title render="italic">La Joie d'Enseinger.</title> Bombay: Ravani Prakashan Griha, n.d. (Gujarati language)</item>

<item><title render="italic">La Joie d'Enseinger.</title> Tokyo: Kaitakusha Publishing Co, Ladder Edit., 1964 (in English with Japanese glosses) (also 2 Bengali editions)</item>

<item><title render="italic">A Goodly Heritage.</title> New York: Henry Holt and Company, 1932</item>

<item><title render="italic">Haseen Miras.</title> Lahore, Pakistan: West-Pak Publishing Company, Urdu-Bazar, n.d.</item>

<item><title render="italic">Haseen Miras.</title> Madras, India: Kubera Printers, Ltd. 1932</item>

<item><title render="italic">A Goodly Heritage.</title> Saigon, 1932</item>

<item><title render="italic">His Birthday.</title> Boston: The Pilgrim Press, 1915</item>

<item><title render="italic">Jonathan Fisher, Maine Pastor.</title> New York: The Macmillan Company, 1948 (2 copies)</item>

<item><title render="italic">A Journey to Boston.</title> New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1965</item>

<item><title render="italic">A Journey to Boston.</title> Delhi: Shahazad Book House, 1967 (Urdu languge)</item>

<item><title render="italic">Life and Language in the Old Testament.</title> New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc.1955</item>

<item><title render="italic">Life and Language in the Old Testament.</title> New York: Gramercy Publishing Company, c.1955</item>

<item><title render="italic">Leben und Sprache in Alten Testament.</title> Munchen: Winkler-Verlag, 1957</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Lovely Ambition.</title> New York: W.W. Norton and Compnay, Inc. 1960</item>

<item><title render="italic">Ambiçao de Amor.</title> Rio de Janiero: Lidador [1960]</item>

<item><title render="italic">Ambiçao de Amor.</title> New Delhi: S.R. Suneja Publications, 1967 (Hindi language)</item>

<item><title render="italic">Mary Christmas.</title> Boston: Little, Brown and Company, 1926</item>

<item><title render="italic">Mary Peters.</title> New York: Macmillan Company, 1934 (2 copies)</item>

<item><title render="italic">Mary Peters.</title> Wein im Phoenix Verlag, c.1946</item>

<item><title render="italic">Mary Peters.</title> Bombay: Narayan Puranik, Kailas Prakashan, 1958 (Marathi language)</item>

<item><title render="italic">Mary Peters.</title> Augsburg: Manu Verlag, 1947</item>

<item><title render="italic">Mary Peters.</title> Allahabad: Desh Sewa Press, 1958 (Hindi language)</item>

<item><title render="italic">Look at America: New England.</title> Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1947</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Plum Tree.</title> New York: Macmillan Company, 1949</item>

<item><title render="italic">Der Plaumenbaum/Eine Fahrt Nach Boston.</title> Munchen: Winkler-Verlag, c.1949</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Prophets for the Common Reader.</title> New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1963</item>

<item><title render="italic">Readings from the Bible.</title> New York: Macmillan Company, 1952</item>

<item><title render="italic">Richard Mansfield: Prince of Donkeys.</title> New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1964</item>

<item><title render="italic">Sailing the Seven Seas.</title> New York: Dell, 1967</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Story of Lighthouses.</title> New York: W.W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1965</item>

<item><title render="italic">Silas Crockett.</title> New York: Macmillan Company, 1935</item>

<item><title render="italic">Thomas Hardy from Serial to Novel.</title> New York: Russell and Russell, 1964</item>

<item><title render="italic">Thomas Hardy from Serial to Novel.</title> University of Minnesota Press, 1927</item>

<item><title render="italic">This England.</title> New York: Macmillan Company, 1936 (2 copies and a foreign language edition, possibly Urdu)</item>

<item><title render="italic">Victoria: a Pig in a Pram.</title> New York: W.W. Norton, 1963</item>

<item><title render="italic">Virginia of Elk Creek Valley.</title> New York: A. L. Burt Company, 1917</item>

<item><title render="italic">Uplands.</title> Boston: Little Brown and Company, 1927</item>

<item><title render="italic">A Walk on an Iceberg.</title> New York: W. W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1966</item>

<item><title render="italic">The White Gate.</title> New York: W. W. Norton and Company, Inc. 1954</item>

<item><title render="italic">The White Gate.</title> Maradana, Colombo: Messrs. Gunaratine and Company, n.d. (Sinhalese)</item>

<item><title render="italic">Windswept.</title> New York: Macmillan Company, 1941</item>

<item><title render="italic">Stormhalen.</title> Uppsala: J.A. Lindblads Forlag, 1943</item>

<item><title render="italic">Stormhalen.</title> Armed services edition. Council on Books in Wartime. c. 1941</item>

<item><title render="italic">The Woman and the Sea.</title> Tokyo: Kaitakusha, 1965 (in English with Japanese glosses)</item>

</list>

<list>
<head>Books About Mary Ellen Chase</head>

<item>Squire, Elienne. <title render="italic">A Lantern in the Wind.</title> Santa Barbara: Fithian Press, 1995</item>

<item>Chase, Evelyn Hyman.  <title render="italic">Feminist Convert: A Portrait of Mary Ellen Chase.</title> Santa Barbara, CA: J. Daniel, 1988.</item>

</list>

<list>
<head>Articles About Mary Ellen Chase</head>

<item>Chase, Evelyn Hyman. "Mary Ellen Chase and the Incipient Feminist Movement," <title render="italic">Smith Alumnae Quarterly</title> (Summer 1987).</item>

<item>Hall, Virginia Smith, <title render="italic">Down East Today</title> (1938)</item>

<item>Kingman, Lee. "Pamela's Socks and the Roman Emperors," <title render="italic">Vogue</title> essay contest (date?)</item>

<item>Squire, Elienne. "A Famous Author and Teacher," <title render="italic">Smith Alumnae Quarterly</title> (Summer 1987).</item>

</list>

<list>
<head>Mary Ellen Chase Material at other Repositories</head>

<item>Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Women's National Book Association Records, 1917-1989. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence. There is also correspondence in the Amy Loveman collection.</item>

<item>Harvard Divinity School. Andover-Harvard Theological Library. Robert Henry Pfeiffer Papers, 1911-1958. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.</item>

<item>Iowa State University, Library, Special Collections. Frederick William Lorch papers, 1857-1966. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.</item>

<item>Syracuse University, George Arents Research Library for Special Collections. Robert Silliman  Hillyer papers, 1902-1963. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.</item>

<item>University of Iowa Libraries. Special Collections Department. Letter to Prof. Grover. Northampton, MA, declining an invitation because of a trip (Nov. 30, 19??).</item>

<item>University of Maine. Special Collections. Approximately one inch of "Letters written by Miss Chase to Dr. Hugh Stalker, writings, notebooks, portrait, and clippings" dating from 1940-69. Given by Chase in two accessions, while alive then again from her estate.</item>

<item>University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Bentley Historical Library. Frank Addison Manny papers, 1890-1955. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.</item>

<item>University of Minnesota. Manuscripts Division. Prophets for the Common Reader, manuscript, 1962.</item>

<item>University of New England. Maine Women Writers Project. Approximately 3 linear feet of "Correspondence, documents, and clippings relating to Miss Chase's publications (1909-1964)". There is also correspondence in the Coatsworth Collection.</item>

<item>University of Rochester, Rush Rhees Library, Department of Rare Books, Manuscripts and Archives. Manuscripts Collection  Ch - Cl, 1731-1980. Includes M.E. Chase correspondence.</item>

<item>Yale University. Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Wallace Notestein papers, 1899-1969, and Kathryn Hulme papers, 1846-1981. Both include M.E. Chase correspondence.</item>

</list>
</bibliography>
</descgrp>







<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
<c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series I. BIOGRAPHY</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>General
<unitdate>1930-1957, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Newsclippings
<unitdate>1926-1973, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>"The Diamond Jubille of Mary Ellen Chase," <title render="italic">Colby Library Quarterly</title>
<unitdate>March 1962</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Obituaries and other Posthumous Accounts
<unitdate>1973-1995, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Memorabilia
<unitdate>1944-1973, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Check Registers
<unitdate>1950-1964</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Press Releases
<unitdate>1929-1967, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series II. PHOTOGRAPHS</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Portraits
<unitdate>1920-1957, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Portraits-Stahlberg Portraits
<unitdate>1933, 1941, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Portraits-Dining Room Photos
<unitdate>ca. 1960s</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Chase and Eleanor Duckett
<unitdate>1949, 1961, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Events
<unitdate>1933-1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Family and Friends
<unitdate>1893, 1951, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Houses
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series III. PERSONAL CORRESPONDENCE</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>Jane Brooks
<unitdate>1961</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">15</container>
<unittitle>Virginia Callahan
<unitdate>1965-1971, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">16</container>
<unittitle>Newton K. Chase
<unitdate>1971</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">17</container>
<unittitle>Virginia Gildersleeve
<unitdate>1962</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">18</container>
<unittitle>Margaret Grierson
<unitdate>1966</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">19</container>
<unittitle>J.D. Holtzermann
<unitdate>1922-1936, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">20</container>
<unittitle>Edward Kessler
<unitdate>1960</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Marine Leland
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Ann and Robert MacMurphy
<unitdate>1927, 1929</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Elizabeth "Betty" Pence McKibben
<unitdate>1938-1963</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Thomas Corwin Mendenhall
<unitdate>1966</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Virginia Chase Perkins
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Florence Perry
<unitdate>1942</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Deborah Wheeler
<unitdate>1952-1968, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous
<unitdate>1945-1972, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series IV. PROFESSIONAL CORRESPONDENCE</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>George C. Connor, re: Windswept
<unitdate>1945</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>re Rabbi Abraham Feldman/<title render="italic">Bible and Common Reader</title>
<unitdate>1948</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Mrs. Noels
<unitdate>1934</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Florence Snow
<unitdate>1930-1949</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Katharine Starrett Whitton and Helen Starrett Dinwiddle
<unitdate>1940</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>Fan Mail
<unitdate>1941-1974</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">15</container>
<unittitle>Miscellaneous
<unitdate>1940-1979</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 id="list-ser5" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series V. SPEECHES</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">16</container>
<unittitle>Chapel talks
<unitdate>1937,1941, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">17</container>
<unittitle>Smith College Alumnae Council
<unitdate>Feb 8, 1952</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">18</container>
<unittitle>Postscript to the Writing of a Novel Friends of the Library, Smith College
<unitdate>April 20, 1957</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">19</container>
<unittitle>First Things First, "Fight for Freedom," Meeting of the Hampshire County Committee
<unitdate>Nov. 27, 1941</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 id="list-ser6" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>Series VI PUBLICATIONS</unittitle>
</did>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">20</container>
<unittitle>General
<unitdate>1941-1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">21</container>
<unittitle>"Abby Aldrich Rockefeller" <title render="italic">Good Housekeeping</title>
<unitdate>June 1950</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">22</container>
<unittitle>The Abundant Life in Books
<unitdate>Sept. 1936</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">23</container>
<unittitle>Alice M. Holden obituary
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">24</container>
<unittitle>"Are We Afraid of Being Alone?" <title render="italic">Woman's Day</title>
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">25</container>
<unittitle>"The Author and His Reader"
<unitdate>1935</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">26</container>
<unittitle>Dolly Moses
<unitdate>1964</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">27</container>
<unittitle>"Elizabeth Cutter Morrow"
<unitdate>Feb. 1955</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">28</container>
<unittitle>in memory of Victoria Schrager
<unitdate>Oct. 27, 1943</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">29</container>
<unittitle>Inaugural Date
<unitdate>Oct. 15, [1957]</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">30</container>
<unittitle>Jonathan Fisher
<unitdate>1946</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">31</container>
<unittitle>"A Kitchen Parnassus," <title render="italic">Atlantic Monthly</title>
<unitdate>Aug, 1926</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">32-34</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Life and Language in the Old Testament</title>: manuscript notebooks
<unitdate>Apr. 24, 1955</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Life and Language in the Old Testament</title>: manuscript notebooks 
<unitdate>Apr. 24, 1955</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>"Life in Books," Smith
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>"Old Time Christmases in Maine" <title render="italic">Ladies Home Journal</title>
<unitdate>Dec. 1937</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>"Our Educational Heritage" <title render="italic">Journal of the AAUW</title>
<unitdate>Jan. 1940</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>The Needs of Smith College
<unitdate>1939</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">A Pig in a Pram</title> (original manuscript)
<unitdate>ca. 1963</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">A Pig in a Pram</title> (corrected typescripts)
<unitdate>ca. 1963</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">A Pig in a Pram</title> (marked galley)
<unitdate>Apr. 2, 1963</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">The Plum Tree</title> (revised manuscript)
<unitdate>1949</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Recipe for a Magic Childhood pamphlet and article
<unitdate>1951 and 1952</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Richard Mansfield</title> (marked typescript)
<unitdate>ca. 1963</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Richard Mansfield</title> (marked galley)
<unitdate>Oct. 21, 1963</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Sarah Orne Jewett</title> (typescript)
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>"She Misses Some Goals, " <title render="italic">Life</title>
<unitdate>Dec, 1956</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Smith College - A Definition</title> (book and typescript)
<unitdate>1968</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">15</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">The Story of Lighthouses</title> (typescript)
<unitdate>Jan. 7, 1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">16</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">The Story of Lighthouses</title> (marked galley)
<unitdate>ca. 1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>"Taxi Driver 63," <title render="italic">Delineator</title>
<unitdate>Feb. 1939</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">A Walk on an Iceberg</title> (marked typescript)
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>"When You Go Home," <title render="italic">Coronet</title>
<unitdate>Dec. 1952</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">The White Gate</title> (manuscript notebooks)
<unitdate>1954</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Windswept </title>(drawings, photographs and letters)
<unitdate>c.1941-1946</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>"You Become Someone - Alone" <title render="italic">Readers' Digest</title>
<unitdate>Mar. 1962</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Reviews of publications by M.E.C.
<unitdate>c.1929-1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Reviews, by M.E.C, of publications
<unitdate>c.1928-1966</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Edge of Darkness</title>-general
<unitdate>1957</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Edge of Darkness</title>-original manuscripts, I and II
<unitdate>Jan.12-Mar.5, 1957</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Edge of Darkness</title>-original manuscripts, III and IV
<unitdate>1957</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Edge of Darkness</title>-revised manuscripts, I-IV
<unitdate>Jan.12- Mar.10, 1957</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Edge of Darkness</title>-three manuscript books containing final revisions 
<unitdate>Mar.18-31, 1957</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">The Lovely Ambition:</title> corrected author's galley I
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">The Lovely Ambition:</title> corrected author's galley II
<unitdate>Dec. 31, 1959</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">The Lovely Ambition:</title> galleys: title page
<unitdate>ca. 1960</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">The Lovely Ambition:</title> marked and corrected typescript
<unitdate>Dec. 2, 1959</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Prophets for the Common Reader:</title> manuscript (incomplete)
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Prophets for the Common Reader:</title> first typescript
<unitdate>ca. 1963</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02 level="file">
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Prophets for the Common Reader:</title> second manuscript (complete)
<unitdate>ca. 1963</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>







</archdesc>
</ead>
