<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="manoscmr" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/mortimer/manoscmr15.html">manoscmr15</eadid>

	<filedesc>
		<titlestmt>
			<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Anne Walker Artists' Book Collection, 1974-2006</titleproper>
			<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
			<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Melvin Carlson, Jr.</author>
		</titlestmt>
		<publicationstmt>
			<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Mortimer Rare Book Room, William Allan Neilson Library, Smith College</publisher>
			<address>
				<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
			</address>
			<date encodinganalog="260$c"> 2006</date>
			<p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
		</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
	<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Jennifer Smar. 
		<date>2006-06-21</date>
	</creation>
	<langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

  <frontmatter id="front"> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Smith College William Allan Neilson Library Mortimer Rare Book Room</publisher> 
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Anne Walker artists' book collection, 1974-2006</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle> 
		<num>MS 114</num> 
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Melvin Carlson Jr.</author> 
		<date>2006</date> 
		 
		 
		<p>© 2006 Smith College. All rights reserved.</p> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 

<archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
		<origination label="Creator:">
			<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Walker, Anne, 1933-</persname>
		</origination>
		<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Anne Walker artists' book collection</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1974-2006</unitdate>

		<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="manoscmr">114</unitid>
		
		<physdesc label="Quantity:">
			<extent encodinganalog="300$a">7 boxes</extent>
			<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(3 linear ft.)</extent>
		</physdesc>
		<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">English, French</langmaterial>

	          <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Mortimer Rare Book Room</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
		<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		The collection contains 34 books executed primarily in gouache and pastel by Walker with poetry or lines from various authors living or dead. Poets and writers include Michel Butor, Peter Davison, Emily Dickinson, Edward Kessler, Kenneth Koch, Ron Padgett and Henry David Thoreau. Also included in the collection is correspondence related to the books, exhibition materials, and general publicity on Walker.		
		</abstract>
</did>

<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->

<bioghist id="bioghist">

<p>Anne Walker is a printmaker and painter; she lives in Paris. Walker was born in 1933 in Boston, Massachusetts, and graduated in 1955 from Smith College; she spent her junior year in Paris, working at the Académie de la Grande Chaumière in Montparnasse. In 1956 she returned to Paris to study with Johnny Friedlaender at his atelier; her first etchings were done there. She has continued to make prints, created etchings, and a number of fine-press books. Walker's graphic work has been exhibited worldwide since 1956 and is in public and private collections in Europe and the United States. Her husband, Bertrand Dorny, is also an artist.</p>

<p>In 1986 she took up painting, using gouache combined with pastel, a technique that has predominated in her work since then. With these materials she began exploring the format of the artist's book, which has allowed her to collaborate with poets and writers whom she admires-Michel Butor, Kenneth Koch and Peter Davison, to name a few. Much of her book work is concerned with the language of color and is characterized by a lyricism-sometimes playful, sometimes elegiac-that pairs well with literature.</p>   	

<p>Anne Walker has written the following about her artists' books:</p> 

<p>“I believe the desire to create images originates in an early passion for pictures and paintings. Some of my fondest memories are of my illustrated childhood books, read over and over again, as much for the pictures as for the words. My dream then was to be an illustrator of children's books. Growing up in the Newton suburbs outside of Boston, where I was born, I was close to the Museum of Fine Arts, where I was enrolled in a Saturday morning art class by parents who always encouraged my interest in drawing, but I soon stopped attending in order to roam the more interesting museum. It was a wonderful introduction to seeing: having little knowledge of art history, I was free to admire or dislike as I wandered. The Oriental art rooms particularly impressed me.”</p>

<p>“Attending Smith College as a studio art major and taking my junior year abroad in Paris, where I was first exposed directly to the many forms of contemporary art, were essential in forming my vision as an artist. My first experiments were with printing techniques. I studied woodcutting at Smith with Seong Moy and etching with Johnny Friedlaender in Paris. Having taken up residence in Paris permanently, I could avail myself of the fine presses and printing studios to make numerous etchings and, most important, my first artist's books. These were made in collaboration with my poet friend Edward Kessler. Later, when I turned to using gouache and pastel, I began the series of 'painted books' which I continue to this day.”</p>

<p>“When conceiving a book, I work in harmony with writers whom I know personally, both French and American. Also, words of certain departed poets who speak to me across time can stimulate the visual pattern behind a composition. It is a question of words evoking images or, in direct collaboration with a poet, images evoking words. Because creatively I'm devoted to inventing landscape equivalences, the accordion form of 'folded paintings' suits my concept of an overall, amost unending piece that becomes a book when folded and can be read page by page, but that can also be viewed as a long picture, like a scroll. In my books I seek to illuminate rather than to illustrate the text, which the author inscribes after I've made the painting. If the poet is no longer living, I print the text myself in simple block letters. The words in the books are placed over and within the painting becoming inseparable from it, a form of intermingling that I try to render among the elements in the accompanying image.”</p>

</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">

<p>The Anne Walker Collection consists of a collection of her artists' books, letters and related items relative to the artistry of Ms. Walker. The majority of the artists' books were given to the Mortimer Rare Book Room as a gift from Walker in 2005 in celebration of her graduation from Smith College in 1956, with some of the others coming from other sources. The letters of Michel Butor were also donated by Walker. The other items in the collection are from various sources. </p>
</scopecontent>

<arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	
	<p>This collection is organized into three series:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">SERIES I: ARTISTS' BOOKS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">SERIES II: GENERAL MATERIALS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-serOV">SERIES III: OVERSIZE</ref>
		</item>
	</list>
</arrangement>

<!-- End collection level metadata -->

<!-- Enter administrative information -->


<descgrp id="admin">
	<head>Information on Use</head>
	<descgrp>
		<head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
		<userestrict id="admin-use">
			<p>The Anne Walker Artists' Book Collection is the physical property of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors of the works or their legal representatives.  </p>
		</userestrict>
	</descgrp>
 	<prefercite id="admin-cite">
		<head>Preferred Citation</head>
		<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
		<p>Anne Walker Artists' Book Collection, Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College.</p>
	</prefercite>
	<descgrp>
		<head>History of the Collection</head>
		<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
			<p/> 
		</acqinfo>
		<processinfo id="admin-process">
			<p>Processed by Melvin Carlson, Jr., 2006</p> 
		</processinfo>
	</descgrp>
</descgrp>


<!-- End administrative information -->

<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->



<controlaccess id="subj">
<head>Search Terms</head>

			<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Walker, Anne.</persname>
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Dorny, Bertrand.</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Butor, Michel, 1926-</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Davison, Peter, 1928-2004</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Kessler, Edward, 1927-</persname> 
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Artists' books.</subject> 
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Artists' books-France.</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Art, American-France-Paris</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Expatriate artists-France.</subject>

<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Butor, Michel, 1926</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Davison, Peter, 1928-2004</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886.</persname>  
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Kessler, Edward, 1927-</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Koch, Kenneth, 1925-2002</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Padgett, Ron, 1942-</persname> 
<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Thoreau, Henry David, 1817-1886</persname> 
			
</controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->

<!-- Begin series descriptions -->
<dsc type="analyticover">
  <c01 level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. ARTISTS' BOOKS
<unitdate>(1989-2005)</unitdate>, </unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>2 linear ft.</extent></physdesc>
 </did>
 <arrangement><p>The collection of artists' books includes 34 books executed by Walker and inscribed with poetry or lines from various authors living or dead. Most of the texts by living writers are inscribed by them directly on the paintings by Walker. The artists' books are arranged by the author whose work is being illuminated by Walker.
 </p>
 </arrangement>
  </c01>
  <c01 level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. GENERAL MATERIALS
<unitdate>(1974-2006)</unitdate>, </unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.5 linear ft.</extent></physdesc> </did>
 <arrangement><p>This section contains letters to Walker, publicity materials and other items related to Walker's artistic endeavors.
 </p>
 </arrangement>
  </c01>
</dsc>
<!-- End series descriptions -->

<!-- Begin container list -->
<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List</head>
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. ARTISTS' BOOKS
<unitdate>(1989-2005)</unitdate>, </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Bachman, Ingebord. Im Gewitter der Rosen: In the Storm of Roses,<unitdate> 1990. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. Translation by Mark Anderson. (10 leaves; 16 x 13 cm., in slipcase) No. 3 of 3.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Basho. Book of Seasons: Haiku,<unitdate> 1995. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (34 leaves; 15 x 15 cm., in slipcase) No. 1 of 3.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Butor, Michel. L'Arrière automne, <unitdate>2003.</unitdate> Text inscribed by Butor; signed by Butor and Walker. (14 leaves; 19.5 x 14.4 cm., in portfolio) No. 3 of 7.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Davison, Peter. Fogged in, <unitdate>2002.</unitdate> Text inscribed by Davison; signed by Davison and Walker. (10 leaves; 10.5 x 11 cm., in slipcase) No. 3 of 3.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Davison, Peter. Thatch,<unitdate> 1994. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Davison; signed by Davison and Walker. (8 leaves; 15.5 x 12.5 cm., in slipcase) No. 2 of 3.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Deguy, Michel. Plafond sombre tire,<unitdate> 1996. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Deguy; signed by Deguy and Walker. (7 leaves; 14 x 9.5 cm., in slipcase) No. 3 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Dickinson, Emily. The Day grew small,<unitdate> 1992. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (8 leaves; 12 x 14 cm., in slipcase) [No. 1 of 1].</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Dickinson, Emily. February Hour,<unitdate> 1992. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (8 leaves; 12 x 14 cm., in slipcase) [No. 1 of 1].</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Dickinson, Emily. I Cannot Meet the Spring Unmoved,<unitdate> 1997. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (10 leaves; 18.5 x 10.5 cm., in portfolio) No. 1 of 1.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Dickinson, Emily. A Little Madness in the <unitdate>Spring, 1997. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (10 leaves; 18.5 x 10.5 cm., in portfolio) No. 1 of 1.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Dickinson, Emily. Of Bronze - and Blaze, <unitdate>2002.</unitdate> Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (6 leaves; 14.5 x 10 cm., in portfolio) No. 1 of 1.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Kessler, Edward. After Holy Night, <unitdate>2002.</unitdate> Text inscribed by Kessler; signed by Kessler and Walker. (8 leaves; 19.5 x 13.5 cm., in portfolio) No. 2 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Kessler, Edward. Cypresses,<unitdate> 1996. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Kessler; signed by Kessler and Walker. (7 leaves; 14 x 9.5 cm., in slipcase) No. 2 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>Kessler, Edward. A Desert,<unitdate> 1997. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Kessler; signed by Kessler and Walker. (6 leaves; 19 x 14 cm., in slipcase) No. 3 of 4.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Kessler, Edward. The Elephant's Graveyard,<unitdate> 1994. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (10 leaves; 11.5 x 15.5 cm., in slipcase) No. 1 of 3.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>Kessler, Edward. Gypsies,<unitdate> 1993. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Kessler; signed by Kessler and Walker. (5 leaves; 16 x 13 cm., in portfolio) No. 3 of 4.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">17</container>
 <unittitle>Kessler, Edward. Words from a House,<unitdate> 1992. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Walker; signed by Kessler and Walker. (8 leaves; 16 x 13 cm., in portfolio) No. 2 of 3.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">18</container>
 <unittitle>Koch, Kenneth. Endymion, <unitdate>2000.</unitdate> Text inscribed by Koch; signed by Koch and Walker. (8 leaves; 18.5 x 11 cm., in portfolio) No. 1 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">19</container>
 <unittitle>Koch, Kenneth. Nine Skies: A Likeable First Name,<unitdate> 1993. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Koch; signed by Koch and Walker. (6 leaves; 20.5 x 21 cm., in portfolio) No. 1 of 9. Collection "A mano" <unitdate>1994</unitdate>, Andre Biren, Paris. The poem inscribed is the first poem of Nine Skies; typescript of the poems Nine Skies laid in, and signed by Koch.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">20</container>
 <unittitle>Koch, Kenneth. Poem, <unitdate>[1995]. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Koch; signed by Koch and Walker. (7 leaves; 14.5 x 10 cm., in slipcase) No. 2 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">21</container>
 <unittitle>Koch, Kenneth. Present but not Here,<unitdate> 1997. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Koch; signed by Koch and Walker. (8 leaves; 19 x 14 cm., in portfolio) No. 3 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">22</container>
 <unittitle>Noël, Bernard. Le Reste du voyage,<unitdate> 1997. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Noël; signed by Noël and Walker. (7 leaves; 14.5 x 9.5 cm., in slipcase) No. 2 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">23</container>
 <unittitle>Padgett, Ron. Solo for Piano,<unitdate> 1996. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Padgett; signed by Padgett and Walker. (7 leaves; 14 x 10 cm., in slipcase) No. 3 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">24</container>
 <unittitle>Padgett, Ron. Thinking about the Moon, <unitdate>2005.</unitdate> Text inscribed by Padgett; signed by Padgett and Walker. (8 leaves; 18.5 x 11 cm., in portfolio) No. 3 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">25</container>
 <unittitle>Padgett, Ron. Two Haiku, <unitdate>2001.</unitdate> Text inscribed by Padgett; signed by Padgett and Walker. (6 leaves; 14.5 x 10 cm., in portfolio) No. 3 of 5.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">26</container>
 <unittitle>Padgett, Ron. Why,<unitdate> 1992. </unitdate>Text inscribed by Padgett; signed by Padgett and Walker. (8 leaves; 16 x 13 cm., in portfolio) No. 2 of 3.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">27</container>
 <unittitle>Peyré, Yves. Pincées d'or ou d'écume, <unitdate>2004.</unitdate> Text inscribed by Peyré; signed by Peyré and Walker. (9 leaves; 14 x 19 cm., in portfolio) No. 2 [of 7].</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <unittitle>Shelley, Percy Bysshe. Ode to the West Wind,<unitdate> 1994. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker.</unittitle>
 <note>
 <p>
 <ref target="list-serOV">[See: Oversize]</ref></p>
 </note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">28</container>
 <unittitle>Thoreau, Henry David. Intangible,<unitdate> 1989. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (6 double-sided leaves; 16 x 13 cm., in portfolio) [No. 1 of 1]. Title from spine of the portfolio.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">29</container>
 <unittitle>Thoreau, Henry David. Night,<unitdate> 1989. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (6 double-sided leaves; 16 x 13 cm., in portfolio) [No. 1 of 1]. Title from spine of the portfolio.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">30</container>
 <unittitle>Thoreau, Henry David. October 3, 1858, <unitdate>1991. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (8 double-sided leaves; 15.5 x 12.5 cm., in slipcase) No. 1 of 1. Title from spine of the slipcase.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">31</container>
 <unittitle>Thoreau, Henry David. Seasons,<unitdate> 1989.</unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (6 double-sided leaves; 16 x 13 cm., in portfolio) [No. 1 of 1]. Title from spine of the portfolio.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">32</container>
 <unittitle>Thoreau, Henry David. Smile,<unitdate> 1989. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (6 double-sided leaves; 16 x 13 cm., in portfolio) [No. 1 of 1]. Title from spine of the portfolio.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">33</container>
 <unittitle>Wilhelm, Evelyne. Mine de riens, <unitdate>2004.</unitdate> Text inscribed by Wilhelm; signed by Wilhelm and Walker. (10 leaves; 13 x 16.5 cm., in portfolio) No. 2 of 7.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>


 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. GENERAL MATERIALS
<unitdate>(1974-2006)</unitdate>, </unittitle>
</did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">34</container>
 <unittitle>Letters from Michel Butor to Anne Walker, <unitdate>1994-2003.</unitdate> Written in French with English translation (1992 Jul 20, 1999 Aug 24, 2000 Feb 29, 2003 Jan 19). The letters are on large format postcards or other printed papers. Butor made additions to the design of the postcards and papers creating collages upon which he sometimes writes additional lines. Also includes a letter from Walker to Martin Antonetti (2005 Sep 10) explaining references in Butor's letters.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">35</container>
 <unittitle>Exhibition of Anne Walker's "Painted Books" at Neilson Library, Smith College,<unitdate> 1994 Oct 10-Nov 30. </unitdate>The file contains correspondence related to the exhibition, publicity materials and photographs. Also includes correspondence between Edward Kessler and Karen Kukil on the exhibition. An exhibition was held at the Mount Holyoke College Art Museum of Bertrand Dorny's artists' books at the same time.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">36</container>
 <unittitle>Exhibition of Anne Walker's artists' books at the Librairie Nicaise, Paris,<unitdate> 1999 Jun 3-30. </unitdate>The file contains publicity materials on this exhibition.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">37</container>
 <unittitle>Exhibition of Anne Walker's artists' books at Smith College, Neilson Library, <unitdate>2005 Nov 8-2006 Feb 28.</unitdate> The file contains publicity materials and correspondence on this exhibition.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">38</container>
 <unittitle>Publicity materials,<unitdate> 1974-1993. </unitdate>The file contains publicity materials from various exhibits of Anne Walker's works.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">39</container>
 <unittitle>Reproductions of Anne Walker's artists' books,<unitdate> 1998.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-serOV" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. OVERSIZE
<unitdate>(1994)</unitdate>, </unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.5 linear ft.</extent></physdesc>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>Shelley, Percy Bysshe. Ode to the West Wind,<unitdate> 1994. </unitdate>Text inscribed and signed by Walker. (14 x 303 cm. forming a circle and folded; laid in wood case with Plexiglas cover designed by Sün Evrard) No. 1 of 2.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>
<!-- End container list -->

</archdesc>
</ead>
