<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
<eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="manosca" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/smitharchives/manosca142.html">manosca142</eadid>

<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Sylvia Plath Hughes Papers, 1950-2001</titleproper>
<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
<author>Finding aid prepared by Deborah A. Richards.</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Smith College Archives</publisher>
<address>
<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
</address>
<date>© 2006</date>
<p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Deborah A. Richards. 
<date>2006-08-22</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Finding aid written in
<language>English</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

<frontmatter id="front"> 
<titlepage> 
<publisher>Smith College Archives</publisher> 
<titleproper>Sylvia Plath Hughes Papers, 1950-2001</titleproper>
<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle> 
<num>RG 42</num> 
<author>Nanci A. Young</author> 
<date>2006</date> 
<p>© 2006 Smith College. All rights reserved.</p> 
</titlepage> 
</frontmatter> 

<archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<did id="main">
<head>Collection Overview</head>
<origination label="Creator:">
<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Plath, Sylvia</persname>
</origination>
<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Sylvia Plath Hughes Papers</unittitle> <unitdate label="Dates:">1950-2001</unitdate>
<unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1952-1963</unitdate>
<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="manosca">RG 42 UUID:1babfffe-2bfb-4123-8214-b7ea2bcdc9ce</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
<extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(.5 linear inches)</extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>

<repository label="Location:">
<corpname>Smith College Archives</corpname>
<address>
<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
Professor of English at Smith College and poet, novelist, and essayist. Contains biographical information, photographs, press releases, writings by and about Plath.
</abstract>
</did>



<bioghist id="bioghist">

<p>Sylvia Plath was born in Boston Massachusetts to Aurelia and Otto Plath on October 27, 1932.  A talented writer, her first poem was published in the <title render="italic">Boston Sunday Herald</title> when she was eight years old. In 1940 her father, a professor of Biology at Boston University died after a long illness, and Plath never fully recovered from this loss.  Plath lived in Wellesley, and graduated from Bradford Senior High School, and received the Olive Higgins Prouty Scholarship at Smith College, which she attended from 1950-55.</p>   

<p>While at Smith, Plath was very active in many organizations while excelling academically and being named a first group scholar each semester.  She was the <title render="italic">Press Board</title> Correspondent for the D<title render="italic">aily Hampshire Gazette</title> and the <title render="italic">Springfield Daily News</title>, and she was also editor of the <title render="italic">Smith Review</title>, the college literary magazine.  She was also on the editorial board of the <title render="italic">Campus Cat</title>, a college humor magazine, as well as secretary of the honor board, a member of Alpha Phi- Kappa Psi, and Phi Beta Kappa.  Additionally, Plath taught art at the People's Institute in Northampton and served on the sophomore PUSH committee.   In her sophomore year she had several poems published by <title render="italic">Harper's Magazine</title>, won two Smith College Prize Awards for Poetry, and she also had several short stories and poems published in <title render="italic">Seventeen Magazine</title>.  During the summer of 1953, Plath was named one of 20 guest editors of <title render="italic">Mademoiselle Magazine</title>.  However, in August of that year, Plath attempted to kill herself by overdosing on sleeping pills.  She spent the next six months in McLean Hospital.</p>

<p>During the summer of 1954, Plath received a full scholarship to study German at the Harvard Summer School, before returning to Smith that fall for her senior year.  After graduating Summa Cum Laude from Smith in June of 1955, she received a Fulbright Fellowship to study in Cambridge.  While she was there, she met Ted Hughes.  They were married on December 7, 1956, in London.  From 1957-58, Plath returned to the United States to be an instructor in English Language and Literature at Smith College, however, although she enjoyed teaching, she found no time to spend on her writing, and so she gave up teaching and settled permanently in England in 1959.  In 1960, Plath published her first book of poetry, <title render="italic">The Colossus</title>, and in April of that year, bore her first child, Frieda.  Two years later, in 1962, her son Nicholas was born.  However, Plath's marriage was falling apart, and Hughes eventually left her for another woman.  In January of 1963, she published a novel, <title render="italic">The Bell Jar</title>, under the pen name, Victoria Lucas.  (Although published in England in 1963, it was not published in America until 1971.)  A month later, on February 11, 1963 Plath committed suicide.  She was 30 years old.   A second book of poetry, <title render="italic">Ariel</title>, written in the last few months of her life, was published after her death.</p>  

</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">

<p>The Sylvia Plath Hughes Papers contain biographical information, photographs, press releases, writings by and about Plath.  There is a small amount of correspondence relating to Plath. Most of the items in the collection are published materials.  The collection is contained in one box that is 5 linear inches.</p>
</scopecontent>




<descgrp id="admin">
<head>Information on Use</head>
<descgrp>
<head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
<userestrict id="admin-use">
<p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish or quote from the documents must be obtained from the Smith College Archives.</p>
</userestrict>
</descgrp>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
<p>Sylvia Plath Hughes Papers, Box #, Smith College Archives.</p>
</prefercite>
<descgrp>
<head>History of the Collection</head>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
<p>The materials in the Sylvia Plath Hughes papers, which are part of 42. Faculty Biographical files, came to the College Archives from a number of sources.</p> 
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
</descgrp>

















<descgrp id="addinfo">
<head>Additional Information</head>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>Additional information about Plath's Smith College experience may be found in the Class of 1955 records, the English Department records, student publications of the time, and a subject file on Plath which is available in the College Archives Reading Room.  The primary source for Plath material at Smith College is the Mortimer Rare Book Room.</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>








<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Biographical Material
<unitdate>1957-</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Biographical Material-clippings
<unitdate>1953-2000</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Sylvia Plath Day in Northampton
<unitdate>2001</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence
<unitdate>1950, 1953, 1960</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
<unitdate>1953, 1955</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Writings: Articles and Short Stories, Bibliography, and Newspaper clippings
<unitdate>1952-1955, 1966, 1970, n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Writings-Criticism: "Stings" with an essay by Susan Van Dyne
<unitdate>1982</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>   "The Poetry of Sylvia Plath:A Study of the Themes" by Ingrid Melander
<unitdate>1971</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Writings-Poetry
<unitdate>1954-1966</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Academy of American Poets
<unitdate>1955</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle><title render="italic">Ariel</title>
<unitdate>1965</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Press Releases for <title render="italic">Smith College Press Board</title>
<unitdate>1952, 1953</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
<c01>
<did>
<container type="box">872</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Published Volumes: <title render="italic">The Colossus and other Poems,</title>  <title render="italic">Ariel:</title> Poems by Sylvia Plath
<unitdate>1961, 1962</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c01>
</dsc>







</archdesc>
</ead>
