<ead>
<eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924" audience="internal" id="head" relatedencoding="MARC21">

<eadid publicid="-//us::manosca//TEXT us::manosca::manosca16.xml//EN" countrycode="us" mainagencycode="manosca">manosca16</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Ginling College (Nanjing, Jiangsu Sheng, China) Records, 1920-1993
</titleproper>
<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
<author>Finding aid prepared by Alissa Chadburn and Katrina Cokeng .</author>
<sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Smith College Archives</publisher>
<address>
<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
</address>
<date>&#x00A9; 2003 </date>
<p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded using Perl scripts and edited in XMetal 2.0. Encoded by Brook Hopkins.
<date>2003-06-03</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Finding aid written in
<language>English.</language>
</langusage>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc>
<change>
<date normal="2005-09-23">2005-09-23</date>
<item>manosca16 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02-5c.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
</change>
</revisiondesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter id="front">
<titlepage>
<publisher>Smith College Archives</publisher>
<titleproper>Ginling College (Nanjing, Jiangsu Sheng, China) Records, 1920-1993
</titleproper>
<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
<num>RG 70</num>
<author>Alissa Chadburn and Katrina Cokeng
</author>
<date>2000
</date>
<sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
<p>&#x00A9; 2003  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc relatedencoding="MARC21" level="recordgrp">
<did id="main">
<head>Collection Overview</head>
<origination label="Creator:">
<persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Ginling College (Nanjing, Jiangsu Sheng, China).</persname>
</origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Ginling College (Nanjing, Jiangsu Sheng, China) Records</unittitle><unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1920-1993</unitdate>
<unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1920-1950</unitdate>
<unitid label="Collection Number:" encodinganalog="099" repositorycode="manosca" countrycode="us">RG 70</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
<extent encodinganalog="300$a">9 boxes</extent>
<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(3.92 linear ft.)</extent>
</physdesc>
<repository label="Location:">
<corpname>Smith College Archives</corpname>
<address>
<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">Foreign Sister College to Smith College.  Contains notes, letters, reports, photographs, articles, and bulletins from Alumnae Committee members, Ginling College students and faculty, and others involved with Ginling.
</abstract>
<langmaterial label="Language of Material:">
<language langcode="eng">English.</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Ginling College opened in 1915 with six faculty and eleven students, the product of the imagination of a group of American women educators stranded in Shanghai in 1911, all refugees from the revolutionary turmoil in central China. One was Matilda Thurston, who became the first president of the College. She graduated from Mount Holyoke in 1896, and went to China in 1913 to find a location for Ginling, hire faculty, and recruit students. It was only in 1907 that the Chinese emperor issued an edict favoring education for women in China. The Revolution of 1911 marked a new beginning, and Ginling College was ultimately founded by five mission boards -- Northern Baptists, Disciples of Christ, Northern and Southern Methodists, and Northern Presbyterians. Each board pledged US$10,000 for buildings and equipment, the support of a representative on the teaching staff, and a contribution of US$600 toward current expenses.
</p>
<p>Ginling graduated its first class in 1919; thus Wu Yi-fang, who would later become President of the College in 1928, and four other women became the first women in China to receive fully accredited Bachelor of Arts degrees. All subjects were taught in English except for the Chinese classics.
</p>
<p>Smith's relationship with Ginling began in 1916. Through the enthusiasm of Delia Leavens '01 and Frederica Mead '11, both of whom had spent considerable time in China, the Smith College Association for Christian Work adopted Ginling as its foreign project. Their first campus contribution in 1916 amounted to $1,000 and was made annually until 1921, when it was raised to $2,500, due to increasing interest in Ginling. It was also in 1921 that Smith officially recognized Ginling as its little sister in the Orient. During the difficult period of war, the contribution reached $4,000 a year. The Smith Alumnae Committee for Ginling was started in 1923, and Smith alumnae donated $50,000 for the construction of a recreation building in Ginling. Also, annual contributions to the current expenses of the College gradually increased until it reached a maximum of $5,500 a year.
</p>
<p>Throughout the increasing turmoil in China, the relationship between Smith and Ginling flourished. The Sino-Japanese War began in 1937, and in 1938 Ginling College decided to go into exile in West China Union University in Chengtu. Smith raised almost $2,500 as a gift to Ginling to celebrate its twenty-fifth birthday in 1940, and this money was used for repairs after the war. The Smith College Alumnae Committee for Ginling was expanded in 1941 to include students and faculty. By 1942, fifteen Smith alumnae had taught at Ginling.
</p>
<p>In 1943, Dr. Wu Yi-fang visited Smith to receive an honorary LLD. She brought the gift of a satin scarf bearing the signatures of all the Ginling seniors and an accompanying letter from them to Smith's 1943 graduating class, expressing their gratitude for their concern and help. After the new People's government was established on October 1, 1949, Dr. Wu was recognized as a leader in China and was asked to serve on various committees for education, women's rights, and community service. She began working to change the curriculum and the administration of Ginling so it would be acceptable to the new government.
</p>
<p>The new government pushed for self-support and Chinese leadership in all its institutions, especially those connected with overseas schools and religious groups. In 1950, the U.S. and China cut off all financial transactions with each other. In 1951, Ginling was combined with the University of Nanking to become National Ginling University under government control. Smith was greatly troubled by these changes, and many Smith students and faculty wanted to transfer the Ginling support to Tunghai University in Taiwan, to which a number of Ginling College supporters had gone. Smith was frustrated by the confusion of the situation, so alumnae groups were notified not to collect funds for Ginling and by March 1954 most local Ginling committees had disbanded.
</p>
<p>Ginling College re-opened in 1987 with sixteen students in a two-year course in Applied English in Nanking Normal University. In order for the government to permit it to re-open, Ginling had to provide courses that were unique, different from the others offered in Nanjing Normal University. In 1995, Ginling had 300 students in three programs -- Applied English, Nutrition and Food Sciences, and International Accounting. Ginling is also developing a year-long training program for around 100 women teaching in rural middle schools. The College is funded mainly by the government, although it does receive some private donations from Ginling alumnae and the Wu Yi-fang Memorial Foundation.
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
<head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
<p>The Ginling College Records cover a period from 1920 to 1993. However, the majority of the materials span the time when interaction between Smith and Ginling was at its peak, from 1920 to 1950. A large quantity of the material is composed of letters, reports, photographs, and publications. Other types of material represented in the collection include articles, published works, and other memorabilia.</p>
<p>The collection includes many letters from alumnae committees regarding the development of Ginling College, as well as minutes from meetings. Insight into the political turmoil rampant in China during the period can be gained from the reports of Ginling administrators and faculty. The Ginling College budgets are also included, with the breakdown of spending on various areas.
</p>
<p>There are also a few papers on the history of Ginling College, most notably a book by Mrs. Lawrence Thurston, the first president of the College. Faculty files, such as that of Dr. Wu Yi-fang, detail what it was like to live and teach at Ginling at that particular period. Letters, notes, and bulletins of various organizations associated with Ginling also give one a sense of the early history of the college. There are records from the Association of Christian Colleges in China, the Board of Directors, the Board of Founders, and the United Board of Christian Colleges in China.
</p>
<p>Photographs of buildings, students, and faculty in various time periods, accompanied by descriptions, also give one a feel for campus life. There are many newsletters on events and developments at Ginling, as well as brochures and course bulletins. Publications of student organizations and the President's reports also prove a good source of information on life at Ginling.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
<head>Organization of the Collection</head>
<p>This collection is organized into five series:</p>
<list>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser1"> I. Alumnae Committee for Ginling College</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser2">II. Ginling College: General</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser3">III. Organizations</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser4">IV. Photographs</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser5">V. Publications</ref>
</item>
</list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp type="admininfo" id="admin">
<head>Information on Use</head>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
<p>The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
<p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes. Permission to publish materials from the Ginling College Records must be requested from the Smith College Archives. Official Smith correspondence and documents is copyrighted by the Smith College Archives. Provenance and copyright ownership is unknown and researchers are responsible for determining any question of copyright.
</p>
</userestrict>
</descgrp>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
<p>Ginling College (Nanjing, Jiangsu Sheng, China) Records, Box #, Smith College Archives.</p>
</prefercite>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>History of the Collection</head>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
<p>The Ginling College Records were processed by Alissa Chadburn 1998 and Katrina Cokeng 2002, Friends of the Smith College Libraries Archival Interns.</p>
</processinfo>
</descgrp>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess id="subj">
<head>Search Terms</head>

<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Ginling College (Nanjing, Jiangsu Sheng, China).</corpname>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's colleges--China.</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Universities and colleges--China.</subject>
</controlaccess>
<dsc type="combined" id="contlist">
<c01 level="series" id="list-ser1">
<did>
<unittitle>SERIES I. ALUMNAE COMMITTEE FOR GINLING
 COLLEGE</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.98 linear feet</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series includes letters from various members of
 the Alumnae Committees, reports from Ginling College
 faculty and administrators, minutes from meetings of
 committees, and lists of Ginling alumnae and supporters.
 The letters, spanning a period from 1920 to the 1950's,
 give great insight into the progress of Ginling, from its
 tentative early stages to the eventual parting of Smith
 and Ginling due to China's tense political situation. The
 folders are arranged chronologically, and contain a mixed
 of typed and handwritten letters, notes, and reports.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1920-1935</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1936-1937</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1938-1940</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1941-1943</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1944-1945</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1946-1947</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1948</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1949</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1950</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1951</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1952-1953</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1954</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1955</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1956-1957</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Committee for Ginling College
<unitdate>1958-present</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Association Ginling College Record
   Book
<unitdate>June 1975</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Association
<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series" id="list-ser2">
<did>
<unittitle>SERIES II. GINLING COLLEGE:
 GENERAL</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.49 linear feet</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains not only a comprehensive history
 of Ginling College, but also articles from Smith Alumnae
 Quarterly, records and letters from Ginling alumnae, and
 files of faculty members Wu Yi-fang and Frederica Mead
 Hiltner. Letters, articles, pamphlets, reports, and
 booklets comprise the history of Ginling. In particular,
 there is a report entitled "Remembering Our Sisters in
 China" by Patricia N. Page (1945) and a book "Ginling
 College" by Mrs. Lawrence Thurston and Ruth M. Chester.
 Page's report looks back on Ginling's early history,
 focusing particularly on President Wu Yi-fang and Smith's
 relationship with the college. Thurston and Chester's
 book is a broader look at Ginling, from its inception as
 a pioneer women's college to its alliance with the
 University of Nanking in the 1950's.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Quarterly Articles
<unitdate>Feb. 1950 - May 1951</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Reunion
<unitdate>1983</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Anniversary - "Smith Around the World"
<unitdate>1925</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Anniversary - 1940
<unitdate>1940</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae in U.S.- Ginling Association in
   America
<unitdate>1939-1966</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Faculty - Hiltner, Frederica Mead
<unitdate>1967-1977</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Faculty - Wu, Yi-Fang</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Gifts from Ginling
<unitdate>1925-1950</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>History of Ginling
<unitdate>1921-1940</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>History
<unitdate>1941-1981, n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>History: Ginling College
<unitdate>1945-1955</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>History: Far East Conference Minutes
<unitdate>1950</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series" id="list-ser3">
<did>
<unittitle>SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.49 linear feet</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series is composed mostly of letters and
 bulletins from the Associated Board of Christian Colleges
 in China, whose name was later changed to the United
 Board of Christian Colleges in China in 1948. Meetings
 address what actions to take with Ginling, what policies
 to implement, and how to go about doing this. The notes,
 letters, and minutes span a period from 1931 to the
 1950's, and are arranged chronologically.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Associated Boards of Christian Colleges in
   China
<unitdate>1931-1941</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Associated Boards of Christian Colleges in
   China</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Associated Boards of Christian Colleges in
   China
<unitdate>1946-1947</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Board of Directors: Minutes
<unitdate>1932</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Board of Founders
<unitdate>1937-1945</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>United Board of Christian Colleges in China
<unitdate>1948-1949</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>United Board of Christian Colleges in China
<unitdate>1950</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>United Board of Christian Colleges in China
<unitdate>1951</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>United Board of Christian Colleges in China
<unitdate>1952-1954</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>United Board of Christian Colleges in China
<unitdate>1956-1993</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">4</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>United Board of Christian Colleges in China:
   Publications
<unitdate>1934-1954</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">5</container>
<unittitle>Photograph Album</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series" id="list-ser4">
<did>
<unittitle>SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent>0.735 linear feet</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains photographs of Ginling. The
 folders are divided chronologically. There is an album
 that contains pictures of the campus, faculty, and
 students. Most of the photographs, both candid and posed,
 are accompanied by descriptions. There are photos of
 Ginling's original campus as well as Ginling in Chengtu.
 In addition, there are little scrapbooks made by various
 Ginling students.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
<unitdate>pre 1920</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Buildings
<unitdate>1920</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
<unitdate>1920-1925</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
<unitdate>1939-1938</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
<unitdate>1939-1940</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
<unitdate>1940-1941</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
<unitdate>1942-1990</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Association 25th Anniversary
<unitdate>1940</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Association 40th Anniversary
<unitdate>1955</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae Association Exhibit
<unitdate>1949</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Faculty
<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Jenshow - Ginling's Rural Project
<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Ginling in Chengtu, Szechuan
<unitdate>1939</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">6</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>General photographs
<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 level="series" id="list-ser5">
<did>
<unittitle>SERIES V. PUBLICATIONS</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent>1.225 linear feet</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series is divided up into brochures, bulletins,
 newsletters, magazines, and student activities. The
 newsletters make up a large part of the series, and are
 arranged chronologically. These document the events at
 Ginling, as well as developments in its history. The
 course bulletins allow one to see the direction Ginling
 has taken academically. There are also copies of the
 Ginling College Magazine, and the news articles and
 editorials they contain reflect student opinion. The
 President's reports and publications of student
 organizations are also included in this series.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">7</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Brochures
<unitdate>1915-1934</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">7</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Brochures
<unitdate>1935-1950</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">7</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Bulletins
<unitdate>1915-1931</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">7</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Bullentins
<unitdate>1961</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">7</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Calendars
<unitdate>1924-1952</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>Newsletters</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>1922-June 1937</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>Sept. 1937-Mar. 1938</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>Apr. 1938 -1939</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>1940-1944</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>1945-1946</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>1947-1948</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>1949-1950</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>1951-1957</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>1940-1950</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>News from Schwen Hwa Cheng
<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>President's Reports
<unitdate>1915-1920</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">8</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>Recipe Book
<unitdate>1940</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>Student Activities</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">9</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>Ginling College Magazine
     <unitdate>1924-1928</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">9</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>General
     <unitdate>1943</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">9</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>General</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
