<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
<eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

<eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="manosca" publicid="-//us::manosca//TEXT us::manosca::manosca31.xml//EN">manosca31</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Student Strike of 1970 Files, 1968-1971
</titleproper>
<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
<author>Finding aid prepared by manosca.</author>
<sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt>
<publisher>Smith College Archives</publisher>
<address>
<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
</address>
<date>© 2003 </date>
<p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded using Perl scripts and edited in XMetal 2.0. Encoded by Brook Hopkins.
<date>2003-06-13</date>
</creation>
<langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc>
<change>
<date normal="2005-09-23">2005-09-23</date>
<item>manosca31 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02-5c.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
</change>
</revisiondesc>
</eadheader>
<frontmatter id="front">
<titlepage>
<publisher>Smith College Archives
 

</publisher>
<titleproper>Student Strike of 1970 Files, 1968-1971
</titleproper>
<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
<num>RG 80
</num>
<date>1998
</date>

<sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
<p>© 2003  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
</titlepage>
</frontmatter>
<archdesc level="recordgrp" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<did id="main">
<head>Collection Overview</head>

<origination label="Creator:">
<corpname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Smith College.</corpname>
</origination>
<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Student Strike of 1970 Files</unittitle><unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1968-1971</unitdate>
<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="manosca">RG 80 UUID:1c192289-70f7-4a75-aac0-c9185b6585c8</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
<extent encodinganalog="300$a">3 boxes </extent>
<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1 linear ft.)</extent>
</physdesc>
<repository label="Location:">
<corpname>Smith College Archives</corpname>
<address>
<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Student anti-war demonstration.  Contains correspondence, diaries, notes, speeches, notices, posters, memoranda, photographs, petitions, newsletters, packets, press releases and newspaper clippings
</abstract>
<langmaterial label="Language of Material:">
<language langcode="eng">English.</language>
</langmaterial>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">

<p>The idea of a nationally coordinated student strike
developed over a period of at least two years of growing
tension between the federal administration and minority and
student groups who expressed dissatisfaction with the
undeclared war in Vietnam, the military draft, and economic
consequences of the war. Coordinated by the National
Moratorium Committee (organized in June 1969), Moratorium
Days held on October 15, 1969 and November 15, 1969 included
the suspension of classes, neighborhood canvassing, protest
marches and petitions. The third week in March 1970 was
proclaimed National Anti-Draft Week. Planned demonstrations
were held at local draft board offices, and "we won't go"
petitions were circulated. In 1970, the Fast for Peace was
held on April 13, 14, and 15, as an expression of moral
concern about the war. In early May, student opposition
intensified with the knowledge of the expansion of the
conflict into Cambodia, President Nixon's April 3
announcement of his decision to resume bombing in North
Vietnam, and the treatment of dissenters in the United
States. On May 4, the day of the killings on the Kent State
University campus, "leaders of the National Student
Association and the former Vietnam Moratorium Committee
officially called for a nationwide strike of indefinite
duration" (Facts on File 1970, p.299).</p>
<p>At Smith, the Moratorium Days were occasions for student
involvement in the local community. Smith students staffed
the Green Street Moratorium office, canvassed residents, and
coordinated marches down Main Street with the cooperation of
local businesses. The first Moratorium Day was October 15,
1969 and was called Work for Peace Day at Smith. Smith's
Chaplain the Rev. Richard P. Unsworth participated in a
memorial service for Hampshire County veterans held at the
Unitarian Church. On the second Moratorium Day, November 15,
1969, a contingent of 250 Smith students and 10 Smith
professors attended the march in Washington, D. C to protest
the Vietnam War. In Northampton, the weekend of November 15
included a teach-in at Wright Hall, a silent march from Helen
Hills Hills Chapel to the center of Northampton and back, and
well-attended coffee klatches held in a number of Northampton
homes.</p>
<p>A timeline of activities at Smith during the May, 1970
Strike is provided below. During and after the strike,
alumnae and friends of the college became involved. On May
30, President Mendenhall announced that his office was
receiving 10 letters a day expressing opinions about the
strike (tape recording of last Chapel,../../70). Many
seminars were repeated during Commencement Weekend for the
benefit of alumnae and parents, and a video tape of many of
the strike activities was shown. The following organizations
formed at Smith due to the strike: the Strike Committee, the
Education Committee, the Community Action Committee, Union
for National Draft Opposition, Committee on Justice and
Repression at Home, Unofficial Committee of Concerned
Citizens, Committee on Governance, and the People's Lobby.
The activities of the People's Lobby continued beyond the
academic year, with students working in Northampton, in
Washington D. C., and in their hometown to spread information
and coordinate lobbying efforts. Several existing Smith
organizations took part in Strike activities; these include:
the Student Government Association, the Committee on
Educational Policy, the Faculty - Student Committee, and the
Young Republican Club.</p>
<chronlist>
<chronitem>
<date>May 4, 5 p.m.</date>
<event>At regularly scheduled all-college meetings, a few
 students and a professor speak about strike issues, and
 there is a discussion of race/foreign policy
 distinction.</event>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 4, 8 p.m.</date>
<event>About 30 people opposed to the strike gather in
 front of Neilson Library. Meanwhile at Paradise pond,
 Professor Donald Robinson offers a plan for lobbying
 Congress.</event>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 5</date>
<eventgrp>
<event>About 300 students rally at Davis to hear
   speeches against U. S. action in Cambodia and in
   support of Bobby Seale.</event>
<event>Smith students vote to strike, 1547 to 437 (12
   abstentions).</event>
<event>Smith faculty vote to suspend all normal college
   activities from May 6 to May 10.</event>
</eventgrp>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 5,ca. 11 p.m.</date>
<event>In response to a controversy over whether
 President Mendenhall had announced the results of the
 student strike vote at the faculty meeting, students and
 professors stand outside the President's house in the
 rain until it is announced that there was a failure of
 communication and that a faculty meeting will be held the
 next day.</event>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 6</date>
<event>At an all-college meeting, the Sid Waller '70
 speech and the BSA speech, both contained in this
 collection, are delivered.</event>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 7, 4 p.m.</date>
<event>The Government Department sponsors a lecture at
 the J. M. Greene Hall on President Nixon's policy in
 Cambodia.</event>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 7,5 p.m.</date>
<event>A student statement of purpose is read to 15 area
 clergy and 40 Smith students at a meeting in the Helen
 Hills Hills Chapel lounge led by the Rev. Richard P.
 Unsworth and Rabbi Yechiael Lander.</event>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 8, 9 a.m.</date>
<event>A memorial service is held in the Helen Hills
 Hills Chapel for the Kent State dead.</event>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 9</date>
<event>Smith students attend a protest march in
 Washington, D.C.</event>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 10</date>
<eventgrp>
<event>Students from Smith and other area colleges
   canvass local residents.</event>
<event>Black Panther Doug Miranda lectures in the Quad
   to a group of about 300 people.</event>
</eventgrp>
</chronitem>
<chronitem>
<date>May 31</date>
<event>Commencement exercises bring the Student Strike at
 Smith College to a close; however, many organizations and
 students remained active throughout the summer.</event>
</chronitem>
</chronlist>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">

<p>The approximately one linear foot of files relating to the Student Strike of 1970 consist of a variety of materials including correspondence, diaries, notes, speeches, notices, posters, memoranda, photographs, petitions, newsletters, packets, press releases and newspaper clippings. </p>
<p>Although the collection spans March 11, 1968 - March 19, 1971, most of the material dates from mid April to early June, 1970. This collection provides material from a wide variety of sources representing different view points concerning the Student Strike of 1970. The material specific to Smith College includes first person accounts, such as notes, diaries, and correspondence in addition to newsletters, packets, and statements.
</p>
<p>Of particular interest are the correspondence of Sien-Nyat Chin '73; the diaries of Lucy Bodine '72, and Sarah Gordon '72 and student speeches. Also of interest are the material from faculty and staff, such as the  correspondence and notes of Michele Aldrich, an exam of Charles Melvin, memoranda from President Mendenhall, and a petition drafted by Cecilia Marie Kenyon.  Organizations mentioned in the SMITH - General series include the Unofficial Committee of Concerned Citizens, the Committee on Governance, the Student Government Association, the Committee on Educational Policy, the Faculty - Student Committee, and the Young Republican Club.
</p>
<p>The collection also shows how the Student Strike of 1970 at Smith was organized and structured to include educational programs, lobbying, economic boycotts, and community action programs. The effort was to make an impact on both local and national levels.
</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">

<p>This collection is organized into three series:</p>
<list>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser1">I. Smith</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser2">II. Other Colleges</ref>
</item>
<item>
<ref target="list-ser3">III. Newsclippings</ref>
</item>
</list>
</arrangement>
<descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
<head>Information on Use</head>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
<accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
<p>This collection documenting the Strike of 1970 is open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
</p>
</accessrestrict>
<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
<p>All rights are owned by Smith College insofar as the donors had the right to transfer to the college.  Permission is required for publication in excess of "fair use."
   Copyright is held by Sarah Gordon and Lucy Bodine or their heirs for their diaries.  Permission is required from Sarah Gordon or her heirs to publish quotations from her diary.
</p>
</userestrict>
</descgrp>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
<head>Preferred Citation</head>
<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
<p>Student Strike of 1970 Files, Box #, Smith College Archives.</p>
</prefercite>
<descgrp type="admininfo">
<head>History of the Collection</head>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
<p>In the Spring 1985, the College Archives received a collection of files relating to the strike of 1970.  The material had been collected by Sarah Gordon '72 and David Allmendinger, Assistant Professor of History.  The papers themselves describe the process of collecting examples of notices circulating during the strike (see Sarah Gordon's diary), and include evidence that Prof. Allmendinger solicited further contributions after the strike was over.  This collection was merged with a few College Archives files from the strike of 1970.  Many of the newsclippings may have been collected by the Smith News Office.
</p>
</acqinfo>
</descgrp>
</descgrp>
<controlaccess id="subj">
<head>Search Terms</head>

<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Smith College--Strike, 1970.</corpname>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Student strikes--Massachusetts--Northampton.</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Protest movements--Massachusetts--Northampton.</subject>
<corpname encodinganalog="710" source="lcnaf">Smith College.</corpname>
</controlaccess>
<descgrp id="addinfo" type="add">
<head>Additional Information</head>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>Other sources of information related to the strike of 1970 include the  Sophian, beginning with November 1968 and including April 13 - April 20, 1978; the Smith Alumnae Quarterly, especially August 1970;  The Report of the President 1969-70;  and a tape of Last Chapel, May 29, 1970, with remarks by President Mendenhall.  The Smith Centennial Study oral History project (12. Anniversaries) includes interviews with a few alumnae who were students during the strike. The Class of 1970 commencement folder (80. Class 1970) may be of use as well.
</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
<dsc id="contlist" type="combined">
<c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>SERIES I. SMITH
<unitdate>March 11, 1968 - March 1971, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent>.5 linear feet</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>The first and largest subseries, SMITH - General,
 contains material originating from individuals and
 administrative offices, as well as material of unknown
 origin.</p>
<p>The hierarchy of Smith College is ignored, and this
 series is divided into nine of the special committees
 that were active during the strike. The subseries
 include: General, Canvass Committee; Economic Boycott
 Committee; Education Committee; People's Lobby; Committee
 on Political Repression at Home; Strike Committee; Union
 for National Draft Opposition; and William Allan Neilson
 Library.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>General</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">1</container>
<unittitle>General
<unitdate>May 11 - Jun 6, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">2</container>
<unittitle>Aldrich, Michele
<unitdate>May 4 - 20, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">3</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae
<unitdate>Mar 11, 1968 - May 20, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">4</container>
<unittitle>United States Congress
<unitdate>May 7 - Jul 7, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
<c05>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">5</container>
<unittitle>Enclosures
<unitdate>Oct 31, 1969 - Jun 5, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c05>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Diaries</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">6</container>
<unittitle>Bodine, Lucy '72
<unitdate>May 8 - 16, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">7</container>
<unittitle>Gordon, Sarah '72
<unitdate>May 3 - 10, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">8</container>
<unittitle>Directories
     <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">9</container>
<unittitle>Exams
     <unitdate>May 30, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">10</container>
<unittitle>Fact sheets
     <unitdate>c. May 9, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">11</container>
<unittitle>Memorabilia
     <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Memoranda</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">12</container>
<unittitle>General
<unitdate>May 12, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">13</container>
<unittitle>Faculty and staff
<unitdate>Apr 17 - Jun 1, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">14</container>
<unittitle>President Mendenhall
<unitdate>May 14 - 19, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">15</container>
<unittitle>Registrar, Office of
<unitdate>May 7 - 11, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">16</container>
<unittitle>Treasurer, Office of
<unitdate>May 11, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">17</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>May 4 - 5, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Notes of meetings</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">18</container>
<unittitle>General
<unitdate>May 5, 9, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">19</container>
<unittitle>Aldrich, Michele
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">20</container>
<unittitle>Notices, posters
     <unitdate>Feb 20 - Jun 1, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">21</container>
<unittitle>Petitions
     <unitdate>May, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">22</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
     <unitdate>Spring 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">23</container>
<unittitle>Press releases and letters to editor
     <unitdate>May, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">24</container>
<unittitle>Reports
     <unitdate>May 12, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">25</container>
<unittitle>Speeches
     <unitdate>May 4 - 31, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Statements</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">26</container>
<unittitle>Faculty and staff
<unitdate>May 5 - 12, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">27</container>
<unittitle>Students
<unitdate>May 10, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">28</container>
<unittitle>Strike votes, ballots
     <unitdate>May 5, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Subjects</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">29</container>
<unittitle>Memorial Service
<unitdate>May 8, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">1</container>
<container type="folder">30</container>
<unittitle>Questionnaires
     <unitdate>May 15, 1970, Mar 19, 1971, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>Canvass Committee</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">31</container>
<unittitle>Canvasser's packet
     <unitdate>May 10, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>Economic Boycott Committee</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">32</container>
<unittitle>Notices, statements, report
     <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>Education Committee</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">33</container>
<unittitle>Memoranda
     <unitdate>c. May 8, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">34</container>
<unittitle>Schedules
     <unitdate>May 12 - 18, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Seminars</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<unittitle>General</unittitle>
</did>
<c05>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">35</container>
<unittitle>- notes
<unitdate>May 8, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c05>
<c05>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">36</container>
<unittitle>-notices, schedules, reading lists
<unitdate>May 7 - 18, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c05>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">37</container>
<unittitle>Guidelines for Community Action
<unitdate>May, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">38</container>
<unittitle>The Role of Science in American
 Democracy
<unitdate>c. May 8 - 20, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">39</container>
<unittitle>The Smith Strike as History
<unitdate>May 9, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>People's Lobby</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">40</container>
<unittitle>Correspondence
     <unitdate>May 7 - 29, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">41</container>
<unittitle>Directory
     <unitdate>c. May 13, 1970, May 8, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Information</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">42</container>
<unittitle>about correspondence with Congress
<unitdate>May 6 - 8, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">43</container>
<unittitle>general, statements of purpose
<unitdate>c. May 6, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">44</container>
<unittitle>Newsletter
     <unitdate>Jun 16 - Sept 8, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>Packets</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">45</container>
<unittitle>Introductory packet and policy statement
<unitdate>May 9 - 13, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">46</container>
<unittitle>Alumnae packet
<unitdate>early May, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">47</container>
<unittitle>Legislative research information sheets
<unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">48</container>
<unittitle>Packet sent to other schools
<unitdate>May 12, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">49</container>
<unittitle>Washington packet lobbying
<unitdate>May 11 - 13, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">50</container>
<unittitle>First packet to state captains
<unitdate>late May, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">51</container>
<unittitle>June 1 packet
<unitdate>Jun 1, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">52</container>
<unittitle>June 17 packet
<unitdate>Jun 17, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">53</container>
<unittitle>July 3 packet
<unitdate>Jul 3, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">54</container>
<unittitle>August 21 packet
<unitdate>Aug 21, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">55</container>
<unittitle>Photographs
     <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">56</container>
<unittitle>Press releases and letters to editors
     <unitdate>May 9, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>Political Repression at Home, Committee
   on</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">57</container>
<unittitle>Fact sheet
     <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>Strike Committee</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">58</container>
<unittitle>Directory
     <unitdate>c. May 7, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">59</container>
<unittitle>Memoranda
     <unitdate>May 3 - 8, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">60</container>
<unittitle>Office messages
     <unitdate>May 9, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">61</container>
<unittitle>Newsletters
     <unitdate>May 4 - 31, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">2</container>
<container type="folder">62</container>
<unittitle>Schedules
     <unitdate>May 5 - 31, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">63</container>
<unittitle>Union for National Draft Opposition
<unitdate>c. May 8 - 13, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>William Allan Neilson Library</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">64</container>
<unittitle>Bibliographies
     <unitdate>May 7, 8, 21, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>SERIES II. OTHER COLLEGES
<unitdate>February - June 19, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent>.25 linear feet</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series is divided into Local and National
 subseries.</p>
<p>The Local subseries consists of material from Amherst
 College, Hampshire College, Mt. Holyoke College, and
 University of Massachusetts. This subseries also includes
 material from organizations affiliated with the five
 colleges and other local organizations.</p>
<p>The National subseries includes material from
 Dartmouth College and Yale University, as well as from
 various other colleges in the U. S. In addition, it
 includes a letter from the American Council on Education
 regarding tax exemption and political activities at
 colleges.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>Local</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<unittitle>5-College Communications
     Center</unittitle>
</did>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">65</container>
<unittitle>Newsletter
<unitdate>May 8 - 10, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">66</container>
<unittitle>Memorandum, petition, report
<unitdate>May 13 - 15, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
<c04>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">67</container>
<unittitle>Schedules
<unitdate>May 7 - 16, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c04>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">68</container>
<unittitle>Amherst College
     <unitdate>May 4 - 8, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">69</container>
<unittitle>Hampshire College
     <unitdate>May 7 - 13, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">70</container>
<unittitle>Mt. Holyoke College
     <unitdate>May 7 - 25, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">71</container>
<unittitle>University of Massachusetts
     <unitdate>Mar 3 - May 17, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">72</container>
<unittitle>Valley Peace Center newsletter
     <unitdate>May 9 - 14, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">73</container>
<unittitle>Other organizations
     <unitdate>c. May 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
<c02>
<did>
<unittitle>National</unittitle>
</did>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">74</container>
<unittitle>American Council on Education
     <unitdate>Jun 19, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">75</container>
<unittitle>Dartmouth College
     <unitdate>May 6 - 27, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">76</container>
<unittitle>Yale University
     <unitdate>Apr 19 - May 18, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
<c03>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">77</container>
<unittitle>Other institutions
     <unitdate>Febr - Jun 13, 1970, undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c03>
</c02>
</c01>
<c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
<did>
<unittitle>SERIES III. NEWSCLIPPINGS
<unitdate>May 6 - September 29, 1970. undated</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<physdesc>
<extent>1 folder</extent>
</physdesc>
</did>
<scopecontent>
<p>This series contains newsclippings pertaining to Smith
 College and the other area colleges. There are also
 national newclippings relating to the nationwide Student
 Strike of 1970.</p>
</scopecontent>
<c02>
<did>
<container type="box">3</container>
<container type="folder">78</container>
<unittitle>Various
<unitdate>May 6 - Sept 29, 1970</unitdate>
</unittitle>
</did>
</c02>
</c01>
</dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
