<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="manoscmr" publicid="-//us::manoscmr//TEXT us::manoscmr::manoscmr24.xml//EN">manoscmr24</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">William Canton's Letters to Miss L., 1913-1916</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Melvin Carlson, Jr. .</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Mortimer Rare Book Room</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Margaret Jessup. 
		<date normal="2008-07-01">2008-07-01</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Canton, William, 1845-1926</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">William Canton's letters to Miss L</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1913-1916</unitdate>
	
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="manoscmr">285</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(3 linear inches)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Mortimer Rare Book Room</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		William Canton wrote letters to Miss L (Alice Lachmund) between 1913-1916 in response to her letters; there are also letters from Annie (Canton's wife) and Guy Desmond (their son). Also included with these letters are photographs of William Canton and his family and of Miss L. and her sister D.   
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	
		<p>William Canton was an English poet and journalist born October 17, 1825, on the island of Chushan, China where his father was in the British colonial civil service. His parents were Thomas Canton and Mary Thomas. After his father's death in Jamaica William was educated in France and briefly studied for the Catholic priesthood at the Benedictine College in Douai; his family were Catholics. Subsequent to the studies at the Benedictine College he left the Catholic Church and became a Protestant. </p>

	<p>Settling in London in 1867 Canton taught and worked as a journalist. In 1874 he married Emma Moore. Their daughter, who died in 1877, was commemorated in a prose work <title render="italic">The Invisible Playmate</title> (1894) and was the first prose work to bring him recognition. Emma died in 1880. </p>

	<p>Canton moved to Glasgow in 1876 and worked as an editor in various capacities. He married Annie Elizabeth Taylor in 1882. A daughter, Winifred Vida, was born in 1890 and a son, Guy Desmond, in 1896. In 1891 Canton returned to London as the general manager to the publishers Isbister &amp; Co. and over time became editors of various magazines. </p>

	<p>In 1901 Winifred died. That same year he began the writing of the <title render="italic">History of the British and Foreign Bible Society</title>, a work that took him nine years. He also wrote many popular books for the Bible Society as well as published poems and stories in various publications. He died May 2, 1926 at Hendon, London, where he has lived since 1912.</p>

	<p>Miss L (Alice Lachmund) had initiated a correspondence with William Canton apparently in response to his writings. The letters she received from William Canton, as well as a letter from Mrs. Canton and Guy, were written between 1913 and 1916. Before giving the letters of William Canton's to Smith College Miss Lachmund had blackened out her name leaving only "Miss L." The letters were given as an anonymous gift. </p>

	<p>Alice Lachmund (February 10, 1877-January 10, 1973) was born in St. Louis, Missouri to Charles and Fanny L. Lachmund. She was initially a member of the Class of 1899 of Smith College however she did not graduate from Smith. She did receive a Ph.B. from the University of Chicago and apparently taught home economics in the St. Louis school system. Lachmund did author an unpublished work entitled, <title render="italic">The Naffz Family History</title> (1960?). </p>

    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="scope">
	
	<p>The William Canton Letters to Miss L consists of the following: </p>

	<p>Series I. William Canton's letters to Miss L: Canton's letters to Miss L were written between 1913 and 1916. </p>

	<p>Series II. Photographs:  There are photographs of William and Annie Canton and of their daughter Winifred. Also included are photographs of Alice Lachmund (Miss L) and her sister, identified only as D. </p>

	<p>Series III. Miscellaneous items:  The miscellaneous items include some postcards, a map of London, and the obituary of William Canton. </p> 
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	
	<p>This collection is organized into three series:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">Series I. William Canton's letters to Miss L</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">Series II. Photographs</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser3">Series III. Miscellaneous items </ref>
		</item>
	</list>
    </arrangement>
<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict id="admin-access">
	<p>The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Mortimer Rare Book Room. </p>
    </accessrestrict>

    <userestrict id="admin-use">
	<p>The William Canton letters to Miss L are the physical property of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors of the works or their legal representatives. 
</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>The William Canton letters to Miss L, Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College, Northampton, Massachusetts.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>The William Canton letters to Miss L were an anonymous gift to Smith College Mortimer Rare Book Room in June 1953. The Miss L of the letters and the gift donor was Alice Lachmund. Prior to the letters coming to Smith College, Lachmund had blacked out her name on the letters and envelopes leaving only "Miss L."</p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Melvin Carlson, Jr., 2007</p> 
    </processinfo>
<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
		<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Canton, William, 1845-1926</persname>

	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Lachmund, Alice, 1877-</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Canton, William, 1845-1926</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Canton, Annie</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Canton, Guy Desmond, 1896-</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Lachmund, Alice, 1877-</persname> 

    </controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->



<!-- Insert container list here:-->
<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. William Canton's letters to Miss L</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 9 Audley Road, Hendon, London N.W. to Miss L in Paris<unitdate> 1913 Jul. 19, 11</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>4 p., map and envelope</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>Canton writes to thanks Miss L for a letter she had written him about his daughter Winifred. He drew a simple map to identify Winifred's grave at Highgate Cemetery, as Miss L apparently wanted to visit the grave</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 119 Audley Rd., Hendon, N.W., from Guy D. Canton with added lines from William Canton to Miss L in St. Louis, Mo. <unitdate> 1914 Apr. 14</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>4 p. and envelope.</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>Guy D., the son of William Canton, writes to thank Miss L for a "charming Easter card." His father then pens additional lines in the letter to Miss L</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 19 Audley Rd., Hendon, N.W., from Annie Canton to Miss L in St. Louis, Mo. <unitdate> 1914 May 81</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>4 p. and envelope</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>Miss L and her sister and a friend had sent flowers to the Cantons on what would have been Winifred's birthday. Mrs. Canton writes to thank Miss L for this and to describe the flowers some of which had been placed on Winifred's grave</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 19 Audley Road, Hendron, London, N.W. from William Canton to Miss L<unitdate> 1914 Jun. 51</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>1 p. and envelope</extent>
	</physdesc>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 19 Audley Road, Hendron, London, N.W. from William Canton to "Right Loyalist." <unitdate> 1915 Jul 21</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>4 p</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>The letter is annotated in pencil by Miss L: "M. had signed her letter to him 'Right loyally." An n additional note on a separate piece of paper in Miss L's hand reads: "The 'Right Loyalist' had already passed on 5 days before this letter was written." Likely this letter is to a sister of Miss L's, as Canton says in the letter: "I have to write now to your dear sister, and I must keep something to say to her." Canton wrote a letter on July 2nd, addressed to Miss L (letter in folder 6)</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 19 Audley Road, Hendron, London, N.W. from William Canton to Miss L.<unitdate> 1915 Jul. 21</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>4 p., envelope</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>picture of Winifred Canton and Mr. Canton and some rosemary from Mr. Canton's garden and a note by Miss L.
Canton sent Miss L a picture of Winifred (Oct. 1900) and of himself (extremely small). He also writes of Peggy. In a note by Miss L she identifies Peggy as a girl who was at the Canton's when Miss L had visited the Canton's in August 1913</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 119 Audley Road, Hendron, London, N.W. from William Canton to Miss L<unitdate> 1916 Jan. 16</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>4 p</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>Canton writes to thank Miss L for her Christmas gifts. He writes that guy is now serving as an officer in France</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 119 Audley Road, Hendron, London, N.W. from William Canton to Miss L<unitdate> 1916 Mar. 20</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>4 p. and envelope</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>With note by Miss L. Canton discusses his work "The Bible Story" and sends his regards to Miss L and her two sisters</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Letter, 9 Audley Road, Hendron, London, N.W. from William Canton to Miss L.<unitdate> 1916 Jun. 1911</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>4 p., envelope</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>Canton writes of Guy's promotion in the Army and tells of "Phyllis' Phyllis" (who is 4 years old) who has just visited. Note by Miss L indicates that the elder Phyllis was a cousin and schoolmate of Winifred's in Kent</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. Photographs</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Winifred Vida Canton.Photograph identified in William Canton's hand on the verso and dated <unitdate>Oct. 1900</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>William Canton, by F. A. SwainePhotograph of Canton in a folder. On the back of the folder Canton has signed and dated it,<unitdate> 1914 Jun. 1</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>William Canton</unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>2 photographs.</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<note><p>One is a small one (4 x 3 cm.) and an enlargement of it according to a note of Miss L's in folder 6. She identifies the small photograph as a "bantam" photograph. These are the same photograph as number 11.</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Annie Canton. <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
<note><p>A photograph of Annie Canton in an outdoor setting. On the verso of the photograph it says she is "on a vacation."</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>D.Photograph of Miss L's sister, dated <unitdate>May 1915</unitdate></unittitle>
<note><p>D is in an outdoor setting in a dance pose</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Miss L. Photograph of Miss L in rather formal attire in an outdoor setting, dated <unitdate>June 1915</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. Miscellaneous items</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>The Bible in the World," by William Canton. Article from an unknown magazine <unitdate>May 1917</unitdate></unittitle>
<note><p>In the article Canton tells relates the death of a child (his daughter) and a father reading to the child from Isaiah 40</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">17</container>
 <unittitle>Map of London and vicinity, <unitdate>undated </unitdate></unittitle>
<note><p>With note by Miss L and underlining as to Hendron (the residence of the Canton's) and Highgate where the grave of Winifred is located</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">18</container>
 <unittitle>Postcards of the Main Entrance to the British Museum and the Mausoleum Room. Also a note in Miss L's hand on a British Museum envelope</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">19</container>
 <unittitle>Postcards from Kensington Gardens: the Round Pond and Kensington Palace</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">20</container>
 <unittitle>Obituary of William Canton. Clipping from <title render="italic">The Times (London)</title>, Monday,<unitdate> 1926 May 3</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
