<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="manoscmr" publicid="-//us::manoscmr//TEXT us::manoscmr::manoscmr23.xml//EN">manoscmr23</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Joshua Morse Papers,  1790-1849</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Melvin Carlson, Jr..</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Mortimer Rare Book Room</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Margaret Jessup. 
		<date normal="2008-06-05">2008-06-05</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	  </langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Morse, Joshua</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Joshua Morse Papers</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1790-1849</unitdate>
	
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="manoscmr">276</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(3 linear inches)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Mortimer Rare Book Room</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		The Joshua Morse papers contain land deeds for property transactions in Newfane and Rockingham, Vermont between 1790 and 1941. There are bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounting records between 1817 and 1849. The guardianship papers (1831-1843) of Samuel W. Phillips and Mary Phillips are also in the papers.
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	<head>Historical Note</head>
		<p>There is little information on Joshua Morse, residing in Newfane, Vermont, who is largely responsible for these papers.  The historic record is complicated by the fact that the name Joshua Morse of Newfane, Vermont, was used by other individuals who were likely related to the Joshua Morse of these papers.</p>

	<p>Joshua Morse was born on November 20, 1777, in Princeton, Worcester, Massachusetts and  died at Newfane, Vermont on September 12, 1859.  He married Sarah (or Sally) Phillips at Easton, Massachusetts on August 12, 1798.  To this union were born another Joshua Morse on September 3, 1801, David (June 18, 1807-1811), and Elijah (January 23, 1823-March 31, 1906).</p>

	<p>Joshua Morse was appointed the legal guardian of Samuel W. Phillips and Mary W. Phillips in May 1831 after the death of their father Samuel Phillips.  Samuel Phillips was born about 1791 and married Mary Phillips about 1822.  Mary Phillips was born about 1801 in Marlboro, Windham County, Vermont.  Samuel Wright Phillips was born July 6, 1821; the date of his death is not established.  Mary Wright Phillips was born about 1823 in Marlboro, Windham County, Vermont.  She married Abel S. Ward in June 1844 and died Feb 16, 1851.  Samuel W. Phillips and Mary W. Phillips are likely Joshua Morse's nephew and niece.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="scope">
	<head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
		<p>The Joshua Morse Papers are arranged in 4 series.  SERIES I.  LAND DEEDS includes deeds for transfer of land titles in Newfane and Rockingham, Vermont between 1790 and 1841.  SERIES II.  BILLS AND RECEIPTS has bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounting records for transactions between 1817 and 1849. Joshua Morse was appointed guardian for Samuel W. Phillips and Mary Phillips (likely his niece and nephew) and the papers in SERIES III (1831-1843) relate to that arrangement. SERIES IV. MISCELLANEOUS includes a holograph poem of a religious nature, an appeal (printed) of William H. Smith from 1859 and some newspaper clippings.</p>


    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	<head>Organization of the Collection</head>
	<p>This collection is organized into four series:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">I.  LAND DEEDS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">II.  BILLS AND RECEIPTS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser3">III. GUARDIANSHIP OF SAMUEL W. PHILLIPS AND MARY PHILLIPS BY JOSUHA MORSE</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser4">IV. MISCELLANEOUS</ref>
		</item>
	</list>
    </arrangement>
<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
		<accessrestrict id="admin-access">
			<p>The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Mortimer Rare Book Room.</p>
		</accessrestrict>

    <userestrict id="admin-use">
	<p>The Joshua Morse Papers are the physical property of the Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College.  Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors of the works or their legal representatives.</p>

    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>The Joshua Morse Papers, Mortimer Rare Book Room, Smith College, Northampton, MA.  </p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>The Joshua Morse papers were a gift of Mrs. Emma Bailey, Brattleboro, Vermont in 1964 and came to the Mortimer Rare Book Room through Nancy Dingman Watson (Smith College Class of 1964) of Putney, Vermont.</p> 
	<p>Mrs. Bailey indicated that Joshua Morse was an ancestor of the Bailey family of Vermont.</p> 
   </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Melvin Carlson, Jr., 2007</p> 
    </processinfo>

<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
		<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Morse, Joshua, 1777-1859</persname>
		<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Phillips, Samuel Wright, 1821-</persname>
		<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Phillips, Mary Wright, d. 1851</persname>
		<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Land titles-Registration and transfer-Vermont-Windham County</subject>

	<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Deeds</genreform> 
	<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Financial records</genreform> 
	<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Legal documents</genreform> 
    </controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Insert container list here:-->
<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. LAND DEEDS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Deed  of Peter Penniman and Jacob White, transferring title of land in Newfane, Vermont to James Morse. <unitdate>1790, 1795</unitdate>
	</unittitle>
 <note><p>The document is damaged and lacks the bottom portion of the page. The deed is endorse on the verso by the justice of peace 1790 Apr. 27 and by the town clerk of Newfane, Vermont, 1795 Jun. 3</p>
	</note>
</did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Deed 1803 Jan. 19 of Jacob Morse to Joshua Morse, transferring title of land in Windham County, Vermont. <unitdate> 1803,  1806</unitdate></unittitle>
 	<note><p>The deed is endorsed on the last page by the justice of peace, 1806 Nov. 23</p>
 	</note>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>1 p.</extent>
	</physdesc></did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Deed  1822 Dec. 16 of John Morse to Joshua Morse, transferring title of land in Newfane, Vermont. <unitdate>1822, 1823 </unitdate></unittitle>
	<note><p>The deed is endorsed on the verso by the town clerk in Newfane, Vermont, 1823 Jan. 2.</p>
	</note>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>1 p.</extent>
	</physdesc>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Deed 1830 Jan. 21 of Henry F. Green to Samuel Guild, transferring title of land in Rockingham, county of Windham, Vermont.<unitdate>1830</unitdate> </unittitle>
	<note><p> The deed is endorsed on the verso by the town clerk in Rockingham, Vermont, 1830 Jan. 29.</p>
	</note>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>1 p.</extent>
		</physdesc></did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Deed  1831 Feb. 22of Henry F. Green to Samuel Guild, transferring title of land in Rockingham, county of Windham, Vermont.<unitdate>1831</unitdate> </unittitle>
	<note><p> The deed is endorsed on the verso by the town clerk in Rockingham, Vermont, 1831 Feb. 22.</p>
	</note>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>1 p.</extent>
	</physdesc></did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Deed of 1841 Jun. 23 Rasom King, executor of the estate of William King Cate to Josuha Morse, transferring title of land in Newfane, Vermont. <unitdate>1841</unitdate></unittitle>
	<note><p>The deed is endorsed on the verso by the town clerk of Newfane, Vermont, 1841 Nov. 9.</p>
	</note>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>1 p. </extent>
	</physdesc></did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. BILLS AND RECEIPTS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Nineteen (19) slips of paper containing financial records including bills, receipts, promissory notes and miscellaneous accounting records,<unitdate> 1817-1849.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. GUARDIANSHIP OF SAMUEL W. PHILLIPS AND MARY PHILLIPS BY JOSHUA MORSE</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Appointment of Joshua Morse as guardian for Samuel W. Phillips and Mary Phillips, heirs of Samuel Phillips, Malborough, Windham County, Vermont,<unitdate> 1831 May 4.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Request of Mary Phillips,<unitdate> 1842 Feb. 8.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Accounting record,<unitdate> 1842.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Complaint against Joshua Morse, Newfane, Vermont in regards to his neglect of his guardianship of Samuel W. Phillips and Mary Phillips in regards to the estate of Samuel Phillips,<unitdate> 1843 Apr. 28. </unitdate></unittitle>
 	<note><p>Lemuel Whitney, register, Probate Court, Windham Country, Vermont.</p>
 	</note></did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES IV. MISCELLANEOUS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Manuscript of a religious poem and prose. The poem begins: When God shall call my soul to go. <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Printed public appeal of Warren H. Smith, Rutland, Vt.,<unitdate> 1858 Jul. 8 </unitdate></unittitle>
	<note><p>dealing with pensions and the Kansas question.</p>
	</note> </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>Two newspaper clippings on the abolitionist John Brown.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Newspaper clipping on David Wilmot (1814-1868).</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>Newspaper clipping on Confederate General James Elwell Brown Stuart (1833-1864), known as "Jeb" Stuart.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
