<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="manosca" publicid="-//us::manosca//TEXT us::manosca::manosca352.xml//EN">manosca352</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">War Service Records, 1905-1992</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Laura Cutter, Maris Schwarz.</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Smith College Archives</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		  <addressline/>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2013">2013</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Jeanne Lowrey. 
		<date normal="2013-12-11">2013-12-11</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">War Service</corpname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">War Service Records</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1905-1992</unitdate>
	
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="manosca">RG 12 UUID:36e91116-3057-4026-9ecb-7a552dfd36c2</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">4 boxes</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1.7 linear ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">English</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Smith College Archives</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		  <addressline/>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		Contains correspondence, reports, news articles, publications, and photographs.
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	
	<p>The War Service Records focus on a small group of relief workers and their respective projects. Many of these volunteers were part of larger Smith units that were overseen by the American Red Cross, which was actively working overseas during, and immediately after, World War I. Most of these Smith groups were small, consisting of only 5-10 members. Their recollections are primarily in the form of extensive correspondence, both to family and the War Service Board. The collection documents not only post-war conditions in Europe and the Middle East, but also the social life of the volunteers. Due to strict censors, many of these letters were edited by the authors, in turn leaving out key information and specific details of their locations and work. In addition to parsing the letters down, many letters home were lost or failed to pass the censors, leaving the correspondence nonlinear and disorganized.</p>

<p>There is little background on the group of Smith relief workers sent to the Near East. Working under the supervision of the 'American Committee for Relief in the Near East,' a Red Cross organization, the volunteers worked in what is now known as the Middle East-specifically Turkey, Syria, Armenia, and Kurdistan. These volunteers were deployed during WWI to repair the damage wrought to these areas by conflict and battle. Many of these women were trained as nurses or experienced in social work; their primary responsibility was to make the local populations self-sufficient.</p>

<p>The Red Cross Relief Unit series contains materials relating to both Smith College and the Red Cross, as well as their combined efforts to create Smith relief units. The material in the collection does not relate to specific relief groups, but rather to the larger organizations. The series also contains commemorative material relating to Smith graduates who worked for the Red Cross, but were not members of one of the major relief units.</p>

<p>The Smith College Refugee Unit was formed at the request of the Smith College Relief Unit (SCRU) director, Hannah Dunlop Andrews. SCRU consisted of five social workers sent to work under the Refugee Bureau of the Red Cross in Orleans, France. Its director was Anne Chapin, Class of 1904, a SCRU member. The series is comprised mainly of volunteer correspondence. The letters express both the satisfaction the volunteers found in their work and the conditions of war-torn France, as well as the dismay they felt when the Red Cross decided to close its refugee camps.</p>

<p>The Serbian Relief Unit was sent to an orphanage near Belgrade, with a specific request for nurses and kindergarten teachers. Supervising the Serbian Relief Unit was the Child Welfare Association, whose purpose was to send aid to those areas not already receiving relief. It was under this unit that Elizabeth Williams, Class of 1891, began an orphanage in Serbia. Included in the collection are descriptive letters by kindergarten teacher Charlotte Wiggin, Class of 1908, and extensive correspondence by Williams herself. The letters relay the hopes of the volunteers, as well as the day-to-day tasks of running the unit.</p>

<p>'Other College Programs' is a small series that includes material from both the Vassar Training Camp for Nurses and the Wellesley Good Will Delegation. Smith graduates participated in both of these programs, though these alumnae were not affiliated with the respective colleges. These programs offered pertinent advice and skills to upcoming volunteers.</p>

<p>In 1918, the head of the Women's Overseas Council of the Y.M.C.A. approached New York Smith alumnae, suggesting that they form a unit of 10 women to serve as canteen workers in France. In June, the Alumnae Association endorsed the Smith College Canteen as a necessary war service activity, and the New York alumnae undertook the task of fundraising for the unit. After receiving permission from President William A. Neilson to form the unit, 10 Smith alumnae set sail in late spring, under the supervision of the Y.M.C.A. Harriet Ford Bliss, Class of 1899 and a SCRU relief worker, was asked to represent the SCCU in Paris.  Second and third Canteen Units followed this first group. Upon arrival of the third group in France, the war was commencing and the Smith volunteers were only allowed to stay for the summer months. The purpose of the canteen unit was to offer supplies and serve meals to those who did not have access to the Y.M.C.A. relief huts stationed around France. These women volunteers rode in a Ford truck around the countryside, serving up to 2,000 meals daily, socializing with the locals, and providing soldiers with cigarettes and playing cards.</p>

    </bioghist>

    <scopecontent id="scope">
	
	<p>This collection focuses on the World War I relief efforts of Smith College students and graduates who were not part of the Smith College Relief Unit (SCRU).  The collection is comprised primarily of volunteer files, which include correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs, and some memorabilia.  Also included are official records consisting of organizational material and financial/personnel records.</p>
    </scopecontent>

    <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	
	<p>This collection is organized into six series:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">Series I: NEAR EAST UNIT</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">Series II: RED CROSS RELIEF UNIT</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser3">Series III: SMITH COLLEGE REFUGEE UNIT</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser4">Series IV: SERBIAN RELIEF UNIT</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser5">Series V: OTHER COLLEGE PROGRAMS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser6">Series VI: SMITH COLLEGE CANTEEN UNIT</ref>
		</item>
	</list>
    </arrangement>

<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives except where noted in the finding aid.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>Single photocopies may be made for research purposes.  Permission to publish material from the documents must be requested from the Smith College Archives.   Smith College owns copyright to any published material relating to college events and activities.  Provenance and copyright ownership of other materials is unknown and researchers are responsible for determining any question of copyright.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>War Service Records, Box #, Smith College Archives.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>The records of the War Service Records were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.</p> 
    </acqinfo>


<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->

<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->

<!-- End additional information -->


<!-- Enter Series descriptions -->
<dsc type="analyticover">
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES I.  NEAR EAST UNIT  <unitdate>(1919-1924)</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series documents the work of Smith students and graduates in the Near East.  The bulk of this series consists of the extensive correspondence of Esther Greene, Class of 1901, to her family in the United States. Greene's files include many photographs of the areas that she worked in, as well as photographs of volunteers and local residents.  Also included is the correspondence of Greene's fellow volunteers.  Much of this correspondence is with the War Service Board.  Ruth Henry Whipple's, Class of 1908, photograph album is also included in this series.  The Near East records provide a detailed look into the life of relief workers, particularly those who worked with children, established orphanages, and who were interested in hygiene.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES II.  RED CROSS RELIEF  <unitdate>(1905-1992)</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series documents the work of Smith College volunteers for the Red Cross in France.  There is organizational material included, as well as instructions for incoming volunteers.  Most of the organizational records consist of correspondence in both English and French.  The remainder of the collection includes material relating to specific volunteers.  Included is a published book of letters written by Smith volunteer, Elizabeth Stearns Tyler, Class of 1909.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES III.  SMITH COLLEGE REFUGEE UNIT  <unitdate>(1918-1919)</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series documents the work of the Smith College Refugee Unit in France.  The majority of the collection consists of correspondence by three of the five volunteers.  There is a small amount of background material pertaining to the unit.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES IV.  SERBIAN RELIEF UNIT  <unitdate>(1918-1925)</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This documents the work of a small group of women sent to do relief work in Serbia.  Some background information is included, but the majority of the materials are information files on three of the volunteers.  These files are primarily correspondence, with some organizational material.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES V.  OTHER COLLEGE PROGRAMS  <unitdate>(1918-1923)</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series contains records of two relief programs sponsored by Wellesley College and Vassar College in which Smith graduates participated. Materials consist of photographs, primarily from loose scrapbook pages.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>

<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES VI.  SMITH COLLEGE CANTEEN UNIT  <unitdate>(1918-1922)</unitdate></unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>The vast majority of the material in this series consists of the correspondence of SCCU volunteers, from each of the three Canteen Units.  Also included in these files is some miscellaneous material.  The remainder of the collection consists of memorabilia and photographs, as well as financial and organizational material.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>

</dsc>
<!-- End Series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->

<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
   <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
      <did>
         <unittitle>SERIES I. NEAR EAST RELIEF UNIT</unittitle>
      </did>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box"/>
            <unittitle><title render="bold">Individuals</title></unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family
               <unitdate>Feb-June 1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family
               <unitdate>July-Sept 1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family
               <unitdate>Oct-Dec 1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family
               <unitdate>1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family
               <unitdate>Jan-May 1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence from father
               <unitdate>June 1919-May 1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to War Service Board
               <unitdate>1919-1924</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence, miscellaneous
               <unitdate>Feb 1919-July 1923</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Manuscript
               <unitdate>1923, n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">10</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Near East Relief handbook
               <unitdate>Jan 1919-Oct 1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">11</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Reports of relief work
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">12</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Photographs
               <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">13</container>
            <unittitle>Greene, Esther (1901): Photographs
               <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">14</container>
            <unittitle>Guest, Elma Cokefair: Correspondence
               <unitdate>Aug 1919-Feb 1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">15</container>
            <unittitle>Henry, Ruth Whipple (1908): Correspondence</unittitle>
         </did>
         <note><p>[See also Smith College Relief Unit records- Mary Goodman (1901) and Box 161- photograph album]	Feb 1919-Nov 1920</p></note>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">16</container>
            <unittitle>Hill, Justine Hamilton (1916): Correspondence to War Service Board</unittitle>
         </did>
         <note><p>[See also <extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/smitharchives/manosca6_main.html">Smith College Honorary Degree files</extref>]	Feb 1919-March 1920</p></note>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">17</container>
            <unittitle>Mitchell, Myra (1906): Correspondence to War Service Board
               <unitdate>Feb 1919- Nov 1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">160</container>
            <container type="folder">18</container>
            <unittitle>Moore, Alice (1912): Correspondence to War Service Board
               <unitdate>Feb 1919- Nov 1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">161</container>
            <unittitle>Henry, Ruth Whipple (1908): Photograph album
               <unitdate>1921</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
   </c01>
   <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
      <did>
         <unittitle>SERIES II. RED CROSS RELIEF UNIT</unittitle>
      </did>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>General: Pamphlets and pins
               <unitdate>1914-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <unittitle>Individuals</unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">2</container>
            <unittitle><title render="italic">Letters of Elizabeth Stearns Tyler</title>: Publication
               <unitdate>1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>Rice, Marion McCune (1905): Clippings
               <unitdate>1905-1992</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Young, Dorothy Amy (1902): Medical record
               <unitdate>1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
   </c01>
   <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
      <did>
         <unittitle>SERIES III. SMITH COLLEGE REFUGEE UNIT</unittitle>
      </did>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>General
               <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <unittitle><title render="bold">Individuals</title></unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Merrill, Ida (1906): Correspondence to Lewis, Mary
               <unitdate>1918</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Mitchell, Myra Agnes (1906): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Shaffer, Lucy Kennedy (1908): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1918-1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
   </c01>
   <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
      <did>
         <unittitle>SERIES IV. SERBIAN RELIEF UNIT</unittitle>
      </did>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>General
               <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <unittitle><title render="bold">Individuals</title></unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">10</container>
            <unittitle>Childs, Carolyn Helfenstien (1902): Letter
               <unitdate>1925</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">11</container>
            <unittitle>Wiggin, Charlotte (1908): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">12</container>
            <unittitle>Williams, Elizabeth Sprague (1891): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1921</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
   </c01>
   <c01 id="list-ser5" level="series">
      <did>
         <unittitle>SERIES V. OTHER COLLEGE PROGRAMS</unittitle>
      </did>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">13</container>
            <unittitle>Vassar Training Camp for Nurses: Photographs
               <unitdate>1918</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">162</container>
            <container type="folder">14</container>
            <unittitle>Wellesley Good Will Delegation: Photographs
               <unitdate>1923</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
   </c01>
   <c01 id="list-ser6" level="series">
      <did>
         <unittitle>SERIES VI. SMITH COLLEGE CANTEEN UNIT</unittitle>
      </did>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">1</container>
            <unittitle>General and organizational materials
               <unitdate>1918-1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">2</container>
            <unittitle>Financial material
               <unitdate>1918</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <unittitle><title render="bold">Individuals</title></unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">3</container>
            <unittitle>Blodgett, Ruth Robinson (1905): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">4</container>
            <unittitle>Clark, Anne Elizabeth (1921): Clipping and letter
               <unitdate>1922</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">5</container>
            <unittitle>Jenkins, Anna Spaulding (1890): Correspondence and clipping
               <unitdate>1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">6</container>
            <unittitle>Russell, Elizabeth Lincoln (1903): Correspondence
               <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <unittitle><title render="bold">Unit 1</title></unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">7</container>
            <unittitle>Abbe, Ruth Kennard (1911): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">8</container>
            <unittitle>Bowman, Agnes Gertrude (1911): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1918</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">9</container>
            <unittitle>Durkee, Helen Winslow (1902): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1918</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">10</container>
            <unittitle>Fullerton, Pauline V. (1905): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1918-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">11</container>
            <unittitle>Howe, Mary Reed (1902): Report
               <unitdate>1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">12</container>
            <unittitle>McCluney, Mildred (1904): Report and photograph
               <unitdate>1918-1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">13</container>
            <unittitle>Seeber, Elizabeth (1908): Correspondence and photographs
               <unitdate>1918-1920, n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">14</container>
            <unittitle>Seymour, Mary (ex-1899): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1918-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">15</container>
            <unittitle>Souther, Edith (1902): Correspondence and report
               <unitdate>1918-1919, n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">16</container>
            <unittitle>Tuthill, Stella (1907): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1918-1921, n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">17</container>
            <unittitle>Wilson, Jean Shaw (1901): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1918-1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">18</container>
            <unittitle>Witherbee, Edna (Schell) (1908): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1918-1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <unittitle><title render="bold">Unit 2</title></unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">19</container>
            <unittitle>Bean, Margaret (1913): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">20</container>
            <unittitle>Bridgers, Ann (1915): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">21</container>
            <unittitle>Eis, Florence Marion (1916): Postcard
               <unitdate>1921</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">22</container>
            <unittitle>Hammond, May (1903): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">23</container>
            <unittitle>James, Isabel (1912): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920, n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">24</container>
            <unittitle>Nash, Margaret (1904): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1921</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">25</container>
            <unittitle>Roberts, Mildred Frances (1915): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">26</container>
            <unittitle>Scandrett, Rebekah (1915): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">27</container>
            <unittitle>Williams, Olive (1912): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <unittitle><title render="bold">Unit 3</title></unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">28</container>
            <unittitle>Beane, Katherine Edna (1908): Overview of service
               <unitdate>1921</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">29</container>
            <unittitle>Frankenstein, Sally Moss (1912): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">30</container>
            <unittitle>Hodgeman, Helen E. (1913): Photographs, passport
               <unitdate>1919, n.d.</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">31</container>
            <unittitle>Hugus, Elizabeth (1916): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">32</container>
            <unittitle>Hunt, Harriet Larnard (1913): Photographs
               <unitdate>1919</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">33</container>
            <unittitle>Knight, Katherine (1914): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">34</container>
            <unittitle>Vermilye, Katherine Rowland (1915): Postcard
               <unitdate>1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
      <c02>
         <did>
            <container type="box">163</container>
            <container type="folder">35</container>
            <unittitle>Wingate, Gladys Isabel (1908): Correspondence
               <unitdate>1919-1920</unitdate>
            </unittitle>
         </did>
      </c02>
   </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
