<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss556.xml//EN">mnsss556</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Felice Yeskel Papers, 1953-2010</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">January 27, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Yeskel, Felice</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Felice Yeskel Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1953-2010</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 695</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">4 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(4 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Activist; Educator. The papers of an activist who fought for
peace, gay rights and an end to classism. include correspondence, research, lecture notes,
published work, program files, organizational records, newspaper and magazine articles, email,
photographs, films, and computer files. Especially well-documented is Yeskel's work to end
homophobia and classism.

        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
 <p>Felice Yeskel was born and raised in Manhattan, the daughter of Harry and Phyllis Yeskel.  She
graduated from Seward Park High School in 1970, already a committed feminist and anti-war activist;
her activism continued at the University of Rochester where she earned a B.A. in 1974.  She moved
to California for a time, working there against the anti-gay Briggs initiative.  She then moved to
the Philadelphia area and earned a Master's degree in Psychology in 1979.  After 1982, Yeskel was a
leader of the Seneca Women's Peace Encampment at the same time she began working on her Ed.D. in
Organizational Development at UMass Amherst, completing her degree in 1991. Armed with the research
she did for her dissertation, she convinced the UMass administration that the University did not
adequately address the needs of its GLBTQ students.  The University then responded by opening what
would soon be known as the Stonewall Center with Yeskel as its director, a position she would hold
for the next 14 years.</p>  

<p>During the 1990s, she was also part of the Diversity Works Project which
ran workshops in area high schools aimed at fighting homophobia, sexism, racism, and classism.  In
1995, Yeskel and Chuck Collins formed United for a Fair Economy and together the two co-authored
"Economic Apartheid in America: A Primer on Economic Inequality and Insecurity."  In 2004, she
joined fellow activist Jenny Ladd in founding Class Action which, according to their Web site, is
"a non-profit organization in order to more effectively raise consciousness about the taboo topic
of class and to address classism, both locally and nationally" (
<extref href="http://www.classism.org/">http://www.classism.org/</extref>).  That
same year, Yeskel married her partner of many years, Felicia Mednick, with their then-five year old
daughter, Shira, in attendance.  After a two year battle, she died of cholangiocarcinoma at the age
of 57.  According to her obituary, Yeskel "honored her working-
class roots throughout her life.  She touched thousands of lives, enlightening, inspiring and
supporting" (<title render="italic">Daily Northampton Gazette</title>, 1/15/11).</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The personal and professional papers of an activist who fought for peace, gay rights and an
end to classism.  Papers include correspondence, research, lecture notes, published work, program
files, organizational records, newspaper and magazine articles, email, photographs, films, and
computer files. Especially well-documented is Yeskel's work to end homophobia and classism.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                         <item>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of
research copies.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works in this
collection created by Felice Yeskel.   Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by
those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the resaercher to satify
all holders of copyright</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Felice Yeskel Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<altformavail id="admin-altform">
     <head>Additional Formats</head>
		<p>Portions of this collection are in digital form and there may not be paper copies.</p>
</altformavail>

<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Felice Yeskel Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2012 by her
spouse, Felicia Mednick.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
           <p>Accessioned by  Kathleen Banks Nutter, 2012 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Gay rights -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Gay college students -- Massachusetts -- Amherst</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians -- Massachusetts -- Amherst</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Homophobia  -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Jewish women -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian activists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Pacifists -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Peace movements -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in community organization -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Working class women -- United States -- Biography -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Youth -- Services for -- United States -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Classism -- United States</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Amherst (Mass.) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</geogname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">University of Massachusetts (Amherst, Mass.) -- History -- Sources</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Stonewall Center (University of Massachusetts at Amherst)</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">United for a Fair Economy</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Class Action (Organization)</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Seneca Women's Peace Encampment</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Diversity Works</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Yeskel, Felice</persname> 

</controlaccess>

<!-- add links where needed -->
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material can be found in the Movement for a New Society Records at the Swarthmore Peace Collection; Class Action Records at UMass-Amherst Special Collections; Stonewall Center Records at UMass-Amherst Special Collections.  Interviews with Felice Yeskel are in the <extref href="mnsss511_main.html">Joan Biren Papers</extref>.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->