<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss497.xml//EN">mnsss497</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Margaret G. Frantz Papers,
1958-2005</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2010">2010</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 12.0. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">July 26, 2010</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Frantz, Margaret G.</persname>
        </origination>
        <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Margaret G. Frantz papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1958-2005</unitdate>
       <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 658</unitid>
   <physdesc label="Quantity:">
           <extent encodinganalog="300$a">21 boxes</extent>
           <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(24.25 linear ft.) </extent>
   </physdesc>

   <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
   </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
             <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
             <address>
                <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
                <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
             </address>
          </repository>
          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Professor; Pacifist; Labor reform advocate. The collection includes correspondence,
clippings, and articles, with a substantial amount from author and close friend Jessica Mitford.
Materials pertaining to Frantz's teaching career at the University of California at Santa Cruz;
topics include Women's Studies and American Studies curricula, women's rights, civil rights,
radical social movements in the U.S., and second and third wave feminism.

        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>
        
   </did>

   <bioghist id="bioghist">
          <head>Biographical Note</head>
        <p>Born in Birmingham, Alabama in 1922, Marge Frantz has been a lifelong activist.  Introduced   to radical politics and the Communist Party by her father Joe Gelders, Frantz's activism began   early, with the Young Communist League in 1935.  Frantz's Party activity ranged from selling the   Daily Worker on the New York City subway to organizing the Alabama delegation to the American   Youth Congress. Frantz finally left the Party in 1956, though her agitation far from ceased.   She was an organizer for the United Electrical Workers, campaigned for Wallace, worked for   Planned Parenthood, was a part of the free speech movement in Berkeley, and a stalwart of the   peace movement.  After she and husband Laurent (also a radical and former CP member) had four   children, Frantz returned to college (graduating from Berkeley in 1972) and went on to a PhD   from the University of California, Santa Cruz, where she spent three decades as a celebrated and   inspirational teacher.  Frantz retired from teaching, but continued her activism, and is living  with her partner Eleanor in Santa Cruz.</p>
   </bioghist>
   
  <scopecontent id="scope">
        <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
       <p>The collection includes correspondence, clippings, and articles, with a substantial amount  from author and close friend Jessica Mitford.  Materials pertaining to Frantz's teaching career  at the University of California at Santa Cruz; topics include Women's Studies and American  Studies curricula, women's rights, civil rights, radical social movements in the U.S., and second  and third wave feminism.</p>
         <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
  Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

  </scopecontent>
   <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                      <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the
  Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                      <p>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours  advance notice.</p>
                       <p>  This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
  </accessrestrict>


  <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
               <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
  </userestrict>
  <prefercite id="admin-cite">
          <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this
  collection:</p>
            <p>Margaret G. Frantz Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
  Northampton, Mass.</p>
  </prefercite>

  <accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
                 <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be
  reflected in this record.</p>
  </accruals>
  
  <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
            <p>The Margaret G. Frantz Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection
  by Margaret G. Frantz beginning in January 2010.</p>
  </acqinfo>
  
  <processinfo id="admin-process">
            <p>Accessioned by Burd Schlessinger, February 2010 </p>
  </processinfo>
  
  <controlaccess id="subj">
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">College teachers -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Jewish women</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's studies -- California</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women radicals -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women civil rights workers -- United States -- Correspondence</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Communists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
       	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Frantz, Margaret G.</persname> 
      	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Mitford, Jessica, 1917-1996</persname> 
  
           	<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Mitford, Jessica, 1917-1996</persname> 
  </controlaccess>
  <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
            <p>See also oral history of Margaret Frantz in the
            <extref href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/vof/vof-narrators.html">Voices of Feminism Oral History Project</extref>, Sophia Smith
  Collection. </p>
        </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead>
