<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryenfcoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss455.xml//EN">mnsss455</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Sister Singers Network Records, 1981-2003</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Sister Singers Network</corpname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Sister Singers Network records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1981-2007</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 569</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">10 box</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(6.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Women's music organization. Collection documents the activities of the Sister Singers Network, primarily at music festivals, as well as each member group. Types of material include correspondence, programs, publicity and directories.
 
                 </abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
    <p> In 1981, Echo (Linda Ray) of the Kansas City Women's Chorus and Linda Small of the St. Louis Women's Choir started the Sister Singers Network with a logo, letterhead, and a list of choruses. Their vision was to create a feminist network of women's choruses that could learn from each other and come together to share music. The early SSN choral festivals were part of the Ozark Women's Festivals, until the SSN outgrew them. The first separate choral festival that was hosted by the SSN was in Kansas City in 1984.  Sister Singers Network has hosted several international women's choral festivals in various cities around the United States, including Kansas City, St. Louis, Madison, Chicago, Minneapolis, Houston, Cincinnati, and Grand Rapids. From 1996 to 1999, the activity of the network dropped significantly and membership lapsed. At the National Women's Music Festival in 1999, a group of chorus women met to discuss revitalizing SSN; later that summer, a mailing went out to all the former SSN choruses, plus any new women's choruses that were known, to invite everyone to a SSN planning meeting in Chicago in October. The Grand Rapids Women's Chorus, with help from Sistrum of Lansing, MI, hosted the next Sister Singers Network Festival in Grand Rapids, Michigan in 2001, which was attended by 26 choruses. The organization is ongoing.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
    <p> Collection documents the activities of the Sister Singers Network, primarily at music festivals, as well as each member group. Types of material include correspondence, programs, publicity and directories.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                    <p>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.</p>
                     <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
                     <p>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The material in this collection may be protected by copyright. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights for permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Permission must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Sister Singers Network Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Sister Singers Network Records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2007.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger, 2007. </p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Choral music--United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Choruses, Secular (Women's voices)</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Singers--United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women singers--United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Songs and music</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's music--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women composers--United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women musicians--United States</subject>
		<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Sister Singers Networks </corpname> 
</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material in the Kansas City Womyn's Chorus Records, Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
 <altformavail id="admin-altform">
    <head>Additional Formats</head>
		<p>The various performances have been digitized and are available upon request.</p>
 </altformavail>
</archdesc>
</ead>
