<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss299.xml//EN">mnsss299</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Kate Hillis Boyd Papers, 1915-34, n.d. (bulk 1918-22)</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Maida Goodwin.</author>
		<sponsor>Processing of the Kate Hillis Boyd Papers was made possible by the generous support of the National Historical Records and Publications Commission</sponsor> 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Carrie Baldwin. 
		<date normal="2008-07-16">2008-07-16</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Boyd, Kate Hillis, 1885-1976</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Kate Hillis Boyd papers</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1915-1934</unitdate>
	<unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1918-22</unitdate>
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 597</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(.25 linear ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		YWCA volunteer, World War I, YWCA executive, YWCA overseas secretary. Papers are primarily related to her work as an Overseas Secretary for the YWCA of the U.S.A in France and Belgium during and immediately after World War I.   A large portion is a typescript of excerpts from Boyd's letters home to her mother.  There is also general biographical material and some materials from her time as General Secretary of the YWCA of Manila, Philippines, 1930-33.
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc6439.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>Kate Hillis Boyd's certificate of identification issued by <lb/>the War Work Council of the YWCA, September 18, 1919</p></daodesc></dao>

	<p>Kate Hillis Boyd was born May 14, 1885 to Kate (Gordon) and Joseph Fulton Boyd.</p>

<p>After receiving a B.A. from Wilson College in Chambersburg, Pennsylvania in 1905, Boyd attended the YWCA National Training School, 1914-15, earning a certificate in the one year course.</p>

<p>Boyd worked as YWCA Student Secretary at Winthrop College in Rock Hill, South Carolina from 1915 to 1918, then joined the YWCA's war and reconstruction efforts, serving as an Overseas Secretary in Dijon, Tours, and Paris, France from February 1918 to July 1919; and in Brussels, Belgium from October 1919 to October 1921.</p>

<p>On her return to the U.S., Boyd became Secretary for the YWCA Student Foyer for foreign college students in New York City,  October 1921 to October 1922.   She returned to her native Pennsylvania, taking the position of General Secretary of the Germantown (Pennsylvania) YWCA in September of 1923.  In April 1930 she again went overseas, this time to be General Secretary of the YWCA of Manila, Philippine Islands.</p>

<p>From 1934 until her retirement in 1950, Boyd was Assistant Social Dean at the Penn Hall School in Chambersburg, Pennsylvania.</p>

<p>In addition to her work for the YWCA and Penn Hall School, Boyd was active in the American Association of University Women, Wilson College Alumnae Association,  Red Cross, Children's Aid Society, and local women's clubs and Presbyterian churches.</p>

<p>Kate Hillis Boyd died February 26, 1976 in Chambersburg.</p>

    </bioghist>

    <scopecontent id="scope">
	
	<p>The Kate Hillis Boyd Papers consist of .25 linear ft. and are primarily related to her work as an Overseas Secretary for the YWCA of the U.S.A in France and Belgium, 1918-21.  There is also a small amount of general biographical material and some materials from her time as General Secretary of the YWCA of Manila, Philippines, 1930-33.  Types of materials include typescript correspondence; travel papers and certificates;  newspaper articles;  memorabilia; and a scrapbook from Boyd's work in Belgium containing printed materials, newspaper clippings, postcards, many photographs, and memorabilia.  </p>

<p>The bulk of the papers date from 1918 to 1922 and focus on Boyd's work in France and Belgium during and immediately after World War I.  A large portion of this material is a typescript of excerpts from Boyd's letters home to her mother.  The first part of the typescript was made by Boyd, circa 1942.   Her niece, Cornelia Cree, made the rest of the typescript in 1978, following the style of her aunt's typescript.  Cree's correspondence with the YWCA Archivist indicates that the excerpts exclude "personal matters."</p>

    </scopecontent>
<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict id="admin-access">
	<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.  </p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict id="admin-use">
	<p>Copyright ownership of Kate Hillis Boyd's writings is unknown.  Copyright to materials authored by persons other than Kate Hillis Boyd may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Kate Hillis Boyd Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>The Kate Hillis Boyd Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the Records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. in 2002.  The YWCA received them from Boyd's niece, Cornelia Cree between 1978 and 1982.</p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Maida Goodwin, May 2008.</p> 
    </processinfo>

<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
		
		<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1914-1918--War work--Young Women's Christian Association</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1914-1918--France--Personal narratives, American</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1914-1918--War work--France--Personal narratives, American</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Boyd, Kate Hillis, 1885-1976</persname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--Employees</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Young Women's Christian Associations--Philippines--History</corpname> 
	    </controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->
    <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
	<p>Related materials are in the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>

<!-- End additional information -->


<!-- Enter Series descriptions -->

<!-- End Series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->

<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>General biographical material<unitdate> 1915-34</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Europe</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>General<unitdate> 1918-22</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3-4</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence (typed excerpts) to mother from France and Belgium<unitdate> 1918-21</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Belgium: scrapbook</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <unittitle>The Philippines</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>General<unitdate> 1930-34, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence (typed excerpts) to mother from the Philippines<unitdate> 1930-33</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
