<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">


  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss567.xml//EN">mnsss567</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Rosario Morales Papers, 1980-2011</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 14.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">September 30, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Morales, Rosario, 1930-</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Rosario Morales papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1980-2011</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 712</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">3 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(3.75 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>, <language langcode="spa">Spanish</language>

</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Feminist; Communist; Author; Poet. Papers contain correspondence, writings (manuscripts, drafts, journals, free writing, publications), conference files, memorabilia, and awards that document her personal and professional life as an author, poet, feminist, and activist. Writings included here are primarily autobiographical, focusing on her identity as a Puerto Rican feminist. Morales' writings often underscore the importance of intersectionality in the feminist movement. Correspondents include Gloria Anzaldua and Cherrie Moraga, editors of the 1981 anthology <title render="italic">This Bridge Called My Back</title>.  The collection also includes some materials of her daughter, writer Aurora Levins Morales.         [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>
</did>


<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>The daughter of Puerto Rican immigrants, Rosario Morales (1930-2011) was raised in el barrio
of New York City. In 1949, Morales joined the Communist Party and married Richard Levins, the son
of Ukranian Jewish immigrants and a scientist. Together they moved to Puerto Rico in 1951 where
they became active in the Puerto Rican Communist Party and the Fellowship of Reconciliation while
working a small farm in the mountains. They eventually returned to the U.S., first to Chicago then
to Cambridge, but the people and culture of Puerto Rico remained at the center of Morales' work.
Morales and her daughter Aurora Levins Morales became active in the women's movement in the late
1960s, were a part of the Chicago Women's Liberation Union, and co-authored a book of poetry and
prose called Getting Home Alive in 1986. Despite struggles to be taken seriously as a scholar,
Rosario Morales was recognized as a major contemporary Puerto Rican writer. Morales contributed to
the groundbreaking book, <title render="italic">This
Bridge Called My Back</title>, a collection of writings by women of color
feminists, and her work appeared in numerous journals and anthologies. In addition to the Communist
Party and the Chicago Women's Liberation Union, Rosario Morales was involved in a number of other
organizations related to her identities as a feminist, Marxist, working class, Puerto RIcan woman.
Rosario Morales died in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 2011.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>The Rosario Morales Papers contain correspondence, writings (manuscripts, drafts, journals,
free writing, publications), conference files, memorabilia, and awards that document her personal
and professional life as an author, poet, feminist, and activist. The materials in this collection
primarily date back to the 1980s and 1990s, and are especially reflective of Rosario Morales'
processes as a writer. Writings included here are primarily autobiographical, focusing on her
identity as a Puerto Rican feminist. Morales' writings often underscore the importance of
intersectionality in the feminist movement. Other topics covered include communism/Marxism, writing
and publishing processes, Cuba and the Cuban blockade, and feminist theory. Of note is
correspondence with Gloria Anzaldua and Cherrie Moraga, the editors of the 1981 anthology <title render="italic">This
Bridge Called My Back</title>, including notes on public readings and publicity for the groundbreaking book
by and about women of color.  The papers also include some materials of her daughter, writer Aurora
Levins Morales.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>
 

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the
Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveat: the collection has not been fully processed and
therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>


 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works in this
collection except for materials created by Rosario Morales.  Copyright to materials authored by
others may be owned by those individuals or their assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish
reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to
identify all copyright holders.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Rosario Morales Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>



<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Rosario Morales Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by her family
in 2013.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by  Jen LaBarbera (intern), August 2013 </p>
</processinfo>

<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Latina women --  Social conditions -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Jewish women</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists -- United States</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Puerto Rico -- Social conditions</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Puerto Rican women -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Communism -- Puerto Rico</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women communists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women authors, Puerto Rican</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Morales, Rosario, 1930-</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Levins Morales, Aurora, 1954-</persname> 
<!-- Encode with Added Entry clips -->
        <persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Levins Morales, Aurora, 1954-</persname> 
</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>See also interviews with Rosario and Aurora Morales Levins in the 
<extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss291_main.html">Voices of Feminism 
Oral History Project</extref>.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
