<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
   <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss481.xml//EN">mnsss481</eadid>
  <filedesc>
   <titlestmt>
    <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Bel Kaufman Papers, 1911-2004</titleproper>
    <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
    <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd 
Schlessinger.</author>
   </titlestmt>
   <publicationstmt>
    <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith
Collection</publisher>
    <address>
     <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
     <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
    </address>
     <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2009">2009</date>
     <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
    </publicationstmt>
   </filedesc>
   <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic
DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
     <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">September 28, 2009</date>
  </creation>
  <langusage>Finding aid written in
    <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
   </langusage>
  </profiledesc>
 </eadheader>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
  <did id="main">
    <head>Collection Overview</head>
     <origination label="Creator:">
      <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Kaufman, Bel</persname>
    </origination>
    <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Bel Kaufman
 Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1911-2004</unitdate>
    <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 522</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
      <extent encodinganalog="300$a">27 boxes</extent>
      <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(33.75 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
  <!-- Encode additional languages with lang clip -->
  <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
    <language langcode="eng">English</language>, 
  <language langcode="rus">Rus</language>
  </langmaterial>
     <repository label="Location:">
       <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
       <address>
        <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
        <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
       </address>
     </repository>
      <!-- MRJ Edit as needed-->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
      Author; Teacher; Lyricist. Papers consist of files pertaining to Kaufman's activities as a high school teacher, author, lecturer and public speaker; to her travels in Russia, where there has been an abiding interest in her grandfather, the author Sholom Alacheim; and to translations of her books into the Russian language. Materials relating to her written works include manuscripts, correspondence, contracts, and notes on Kaufman's published books <title render="italic">Up the Down Staircase</title> (1964) and <title render="italic">Love, Etc.</title> (1979).
     </abstract>
    <!-- OR  [NOTE: There is no contents list for this finding aid. Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection for more information about this collection.] -->
  </did>

  <!-- Add paragraph marks to text -->
  <bioghist id="bioghist">
     <head>Biographical Note</head>
   	 <p>Belle Kaufman was born in Berlin, Germany on 11 May 1911. She was the daughter of Lala Rabiniwitz and Michael Kaufman, and  she the granddaughter of famed Yiddish writer Sholom Aleichem, on whose stories Fiddler on the Roof is based. Kaufman was raised in Odessa and Moscow before emigrating the the U.S. in  1924 at age twelve. Despite knowing no English when she came to the U.S., she graduated from  South Side High School (Newark, New Jersey) in 1929, and went on to earn her B.A. magna cum  laude from Hunter College (1934), her M.A. from Columbia University in 1936. Kaufman maried Sydney Goldstine in 1940 and they two children, Jonathan Goldstine and Thea Goldstine; the  couple later divorced. She taught high school English for many years, was assistant profesor of  English at the City University of New York and lecturer at the New School for Social Research, and has taught creative writing seminars and workshops at the University of Florida and the University of Rochester and other institutions. In the 1940s, she changed the spelling of her first name to the more androgynous first name Bel in order to sell a story to <title render="italic">Esquire </title>magazine.</p>

	 <p>Kaufman is best known as the author of <title render="italic">Up the Down Staircase</title> (1964), a novel based on her experiences as a New York City high school teacher, which was made into a play and a movie starring Sandy Dennis in 1967. First published by Prentice Hall, her book spent more than a year on the <title render="italic">New York Times</title> best-seller list, has sold more than six million copies, been translated into at least 16 languages, and is in its fifty-seventh printing. Kaufman is also the author of <title render="italic">Love, Etc.</title> (1979), a novel about coping with the  breakup of a marriage, and of many short stories. Kaufman has been a highly sought-after public speaker at education conventions and Jewish organizations throughout the country, and won  many honors and awards, including honorary degrees from several colleges and universities. Bel Kaufman died at the age of 103 on July 25, 2014 at her home in Manhattan.</p>

<p>[Source: obituary, <title render="italic">NYT</title> July 25, 2014. 
<extref href="http://nyti.ms/1t584Q9">http://nyti.ms/1t584Q9</extref>]</p>
  </bioghist>
  <!-- Add paragraph marks to text -->
 <scopecontent id="scope">
    <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
    <p>Papers consist of files pertaining to Kaufman's activities as a high school teacher, author, lecturer and public speaker; to her travels in Russia, where there has been an abiding interest in her grandfather, the author Sholom Alacheim; and to translations of her books into the Russian language. Materials relating to her written works include manuscripts, correspondence, contracts, and notes on Kaufman's published books <title render="italic">Up the Down Staircase</title> (1964) and <title render="italic">Love, Etc.</title> (1979), and numerous books and magazines containing essays and articles by Kaufman. Correspondence, contracts and documents pertaining to literary rights regarding the movie Up The Down Staircase (1967). Photographs of Kaufman and biographical materials (including interviews) are also included. Many of the documents pertaining to Russia and to Sholom Alacheim are in Russian.</p>
        <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online. Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
    
 </scopecontent>
  <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
        <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
   	<list type="simple">
                <item>The collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</item>

              	<item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
    </list></p>
 </accessrestrict>
 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
        <p>Bel Kaufman's estate retains copyright ownership for her unpublished writings. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns.  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.  Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
 </userestrict>
 <prefercite id="admin-cite">
     <head>Preferred Citation</head>
      <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this
 collection:</p>
      <p>Bel Kaufman Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton,
 Mass.</p>
 </prefercite>

 <accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
         <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be
 reflected in this record.</p>
 </accruals>
 <!-- MRJ: Edit donor info as necessary -->
 <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
      <p>Bel Kaufman began donating her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2005. Periodic additions are expected.</p>
 </acqinfo>
 <!-- Edit Processing date if necessary- year only -->
 <processinfo id="admin-process">
      <p>Accessioned by Burd Schlessinger.</p>
 </processinfo>
 <!-- Encode Subject terms -->
 <controlaccess id="subj">
   	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Kaufman, Bel</persname> 
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources</subject>
   	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">High school teachers--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
   	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Jewish women--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<title encodinganalog="730" render="italic">Kaufman, Bel. Up the Down Staircase--Sources</title> 
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Soviet Union -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</geogname> 

 </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->