<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss551.xml//EN">mnsss551</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Fannie Simon Papers, 1898-1980</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">January 27, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Simon, Fannie, 1891-1980</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Fannie Simon papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1898-1980</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 694</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Librarian; Assistant editor. The papers include Simon's unpublished manuscript,
"Following Fannie in a Changing World," which focuses on the around-the-world trip she made with
her college classmate, Margaret Hodges, in 1928-1929. There is also a small amount of
correspondence related to the manuscript,  a few photographs, newspaper clippings, and biographical
material including a detailed resume.

        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Fannie Simon was born in New York City on April 15, 1891, the daughter of Julius and Bertha
Gubner Simon.  Her father emigrated from Germany in 1885 and was able to make a prosperous living
for his family as a clothier. Thus Fannie Simon grew up in Westchester and on the Upper West Side,
with live-in servants and horseback riding in Central Park with her brother, Alexander.  In 1930
Simon moved to the Murray Hill section of Manhattan where she would live for the next fifty years.
She attended Smith College, graduating in 1914, and began working two years later, first in
advertising then in the magazine industry, primarily as on-staff librarian.  In 1932 Simon joined
the Special Libraries Association, an organization she remained active in until her death.  She was
an avid supporter of the Metropolitan Opera Guild and the New York Philharmonic Society, very
active in New York City Republican Club and the Smith College Alumnae Association, and was active
in the Church of the Incarnation, and her neighborhood association, the Murray Hill Committee.
When she retired from McCall's Magazine in 1959, as librarian and associate editor, Simon
volunteered much of her time to even more causes including, at the time of her death, working as
the coordinator of a program of conversational English for the English-Speaking Union.  Perhaps
Simon's greatest passion was world travel which began when she was a child traveling to Europe with
her family.  Shortly before she died, Simon remarked to a friend that she estimated that she had
traveled to over 150 countries, often traveling alone as she did at the age of 89 when she took
what turned out to be her last trip to Iceland in September 1980.  She published a few travel
articles but her full-length manuscript, "Following Fannie in a Changing World," remains
unpublished.  Simon died in a traffic accident in New York City on October 20, 1980; she was eighty-
nine years old.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>The papers include Simon's unpublished manuscript, "Following Fannie in a Changing World,"
which focuses on the around-the-world trip she made with her college classmate, Margaret Hodges, in
1928-1929. There is also a small amount of correspondence related to the manuscript,  a few
photographs, newspaper clippings, and biographical material including a detailed resume.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works of Fannie Simon
within this collection.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those
individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or
quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy
the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Fannie Simon Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Julie Nash and Virginia
O'Locke in 2011.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
           <p>Accessioned by  Kathleen Banks Nutter, 2013 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Travel writers -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Female friendship -- United States -- History -- 20th century</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Voyages around the world -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Simon, Fannie, 1891-1980</persname> 

</controlaccess>
<!-- add links where needed -->
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Julie Nash and Virginia O'Locke in 2011.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
