<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
   <eadheader audience="internal" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b">
      <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss178.xml//EN">mnsss178</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Patsy T. Mink Papers, 1965-1982 (bulk 1965-1975)
        </titleproper>
            <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
            <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Sarah Keen.</author>
            <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            <date encodinganalog="260$c">2004 </date>
            <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded using Perl scripts and edited in XMetal 2.0. Encoded by Laura Cutter.
        <date>2004-04-20</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2005-09-23">2005-09-23</date>
            <item>mnsss178 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02-5c.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter id="front">
      <titlepage>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection Smith College
         
            </publisher>
         <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Patsy T. Mink Papers, 1965-1982 (bulk 1965-1975)
      </titleproper>
         <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
         <num>MS 105
      </num>
         <author encodinganalog="245$c">Sarah Keen
      </author>
         <date>2003
      </date>
         
         <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         <p>©  2004  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did id="main">
         <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Mink, Patsy T.</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Patsy T. Mink papers</unittitle><unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1965-1982</unitdate>
            <unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1965-1975</unitdate>
         
         <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 105</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Quantity:">
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">5 boxes</extent>
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(2 linear ft.)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            </repository>
         <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Lawyer, legislator, and local official.  The Mink Papers focus primarily on her first tenure as a representative to the U.S. House of Representatives from Hawaii, 1965 to 1977.  Types of materials include speeches, photographs, press releases, articles, legislative bills, and an oral history transcript.  Topics include education, the status of women, women in politics, foreign relations with Vietnam and China, labor unions, the armed forces and national defense, and minority rights.</abstract>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
            <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <bioghist id="bioghist">
         
         <p> Patsy Mink was born in Paia Maui, Hawaii on December 6, 1927, the daughter of Suematsu and Mitama (Tateyama) Takemoto.  She was valedictorian of the Maui High School Class of 1944.  Mink began her collegiate studies at the University of Hawaii, but left after her sophomore year to attend Wilson College in Chambersburg, Pennsylvania.  The academic environment at Wilson did not suit Mink and she transferred to the University of Nebraska after one semester.  There she instigated a letter-writing campaign against the University's racially discriminatory housing practices, a crusade that was ultimately successful.  She was also elected president of the Unaffiliated Students of the University of Nebraska.  However, her time in Nebraska was cut short by illness and she returned to Hawaii for treatment and to recuperate.</p>
         <p> Mink resumed her studies at the University of Hawaii, majoring in zoology and chemistry, and in 1948 earned her B.A.  She went on to earn her Doctor of Jurisprudence (J.D.) from the University of Chicago in 1951 and later received honorary degrees from Chaminade College (Honolulu, Hawaii) in 1975, from Syracuse University in 1976, and from Whitman College (Walla Walla, Washington) in 1976.  Just before graduating in 1951, she married John Francis Mink, a graduate student in geophysics at the University of Chicago.  Their first and only child, Gwendolyn, was born in 1952.  Soon after her birth, the Minks moved to Hawaii.</p>
         <p> Mink became a member of the Hawaii Bar in June 1953 after having to prove that she was a resident of Hawaii.  The court claimed that her legal domicile changed to Pennsylvania, John Mink's place of legal residence, when they got married even though she never had lived there.  Though she gained admission to the Bar, in the ensuing months, she encountered much resistance from employers who balked at the prospect of hiring a married female lawyer with a child.  She decided to open her own private practice in Honolulu, which she maintained until 1965 and again from 1987 to 1990.</p>
         <p> In addition to operating her own law practice, Mink participated in a number of other activities and ventures.  At the University of Hawaii, she was a lecturer in business law from 1952 to 1956 and again from 1959 to 1962.  She served as counsel for the Territory of Hawaii House of Representatives in 1955, and went on to become a member of the Territory of Hawaii House of Representatives, serving from 1956 to 1958, and of the Senate in 1959.  She continued her political service to Hawaii after it entered the Union in 1959, winning election to the Hawaii State Senate in 1962, where she served until 1964.</p>
         <p> During this time Mink was very active in the Democratic Party.  She helped found the Young Democrats Club of Oahu and served as Charter president from 1954 to 1956.  In 1957 she was elected vice-president of the National Young Democratic Clubs of America and served until 1959.  She was a delegate to the Democratic National Convention in 1960, 1972, and 1980.</p>
         <p> In 1964 Hawaii gained another Congressional seat due to reapportionment.  Mink ran for the seat and won.  She held the seat for the Second Congressional District until 1977.  During this time in Congress, Mink was a proponent of women's rights, civil rights, education, and reducing poverty.  She authored the Women's Educational Equity Act, opposed the Vietnam war, and supported Title IX of the Higher Education Act Amendments.</p>
         <p> In 1976 Hiram Fong retired from his Senate seat.  Mink chose to run for his seat and lost to Spark Matsunaga in the primary.  In 1977 President Jimmy Carter appointed Mink Assistant Secretary of State for Ocean and International, Environmental, and Scientific Affairs.  She resigned from this position in 1978.  From 1979 through 1980 she was a member of the National Advisory Committee of the White House Council on Families.  Mink also served as national president of Americans for Democratic Action from 1978 to 1981.</p>
         <p> Mink and her husband then moved back to Hawaii.  It was not long before she was back in the world of politics.  From 1983 to 1987 Mink was a member of the Honolulu City Council, serving as chair from 1983 to 1985.  She was also Chair of the Housing Commission from 1986 to 1987.  In 1986 she ran for governor of Hawaii and lost in the primary.  She ran for mayor of Honolulu in 1988 but lost again in the primary.</p>
         <p> After the death of Senator Matsunaga in 1990, Representative Daniel Akaka was appointed Senator.  Mink decided to run for his open seat, which was in her former district, and won.  She served on many Congressional committees and was active in conferences, delegations, and caucuses, including the Congressional Caucus for Women's Issues (1990-2002), serving as Chair of that Caucus's Task Force on Economic and Educational Equity from 1993 to 1994.</p>
         <p> Mink earned many honors and awards throughout her distinguished career, including the Leadership for Freedom Award from Roosevelt College in Chicago in 1968, the Alii Award from the 4-H Clubs of Hawaii in 1969, the Freedom Award from the Honolulu chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) in 1971, the Distinguished Humanitarian Award from the YWCA of St. Louis in 1972, the Creative Leadership in Women's Rights Award from the NEA in 1977, and the Human Rights Award from the American Federation of Teachers in 1975.</p>
         <p> Patsy Mink died of viral pneumonia on September 28, 2002, in Honolulu, Hawaii.  In November of 2002, she was posthumously elected to the One Hundred Eighth Congress.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="scope">
         
         <p> The Patsy T. Mink Papers consist of 2 linear feet and are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1965 to 1982.  Types of materials include speeches; photographs; press releases; journal and newspaper articles; an oral history transcript; and legislative bills. The bulk of the papers date from 1965 to 1975 and focus on Mink's first tenure as a member of the U.S. Congress.  Major topics found throughout these papers, though mostly in her speeches, include education; the status of women; election, tax and governmental reform; women in politics; foreign relations with Vietnam and China; labor unions and reform; the armed forces and national defense; and minority rights.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
         
         <p>This collection is organized into three series:</p>
         <list>
            <item>
               SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
            </item>
            <item>
               SERIES II. LEGISLATIVE ACTIVITIES
            </item>
            <item>
               SERIES III. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
            </item>
         </list>
      </arrangement>
      <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
         <head>Information on Use</head>
         <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
               <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
          </p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
               <p>Permission to cite the papers for quotations or for publication beyond "fair use" must be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.  The family of Patsy Mink retains copyright ownership for her writings.  Copyright to materials authored by persons other than Patsy Mink is owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns.  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.
          </p>
            </userestrict>
         </descgrp>
         <prefercite id="admin-cite">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
            <p>Patsy T. Mink Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
            <head>Additions to the Collection</head>
            <p>Additions to the collection are not expected.
        </p>
         </accruals>
         <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>History of the Collection</head>
            <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
               <p>Patsy T. Mink donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1971 to 1982.
          </p>
            </acqinfo>
             <processinfo id="admin-process">
               <p>Processed by Sarah Keen, 2003.</p>
            </processinfo>
         </descgrp>
      </descgrp>
      <controlaccess id="subj">
         <head>Search Terms</head>
         
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Asian American women-History-United States-Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Education-United States-History-20th century-Sources </subject>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Hawaii-Politics and government-1950- -Sources </geogname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Legislators-United States-History-20th century-Sources </subject>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Mink, Patsy T., 1927-</persname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in politics-United States-History-20th century-Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women legislators-United States-History-Sources </subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's rights-United States-History-Sources </subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women-Legal status, laws, etc.-United States-History-20th century-Sources</subject>
      </controlaccess>
      <descgrp id="addinfo" type="add">
         <head>Additional Information</head>
         <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
            <head>Related Material</head>
            <p>The bulk of her papers are at the Library of Congress in Washington, D.C., with an additional small portion at Wichita State University in Wichita, Kansas.  The finding aid for the papers at Wichita State can be accessed online at http://specialcollections.wichita.edu/collections/ms/95-24/95-24-A.html.
        </p>
         </relatedmaterial>
      </descgrp>
      <dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
         <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Contents</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Biographical data,<unitdate> 1965</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Newspaper clippings,<unitdate> 1970-72</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">4</container>
                  <unittitle>Oral history interview transcript,<unitdate> 1979</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">5</container>
                  <unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate>undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES II. LEGISLATIVE ACTIVITIES</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Congressional publications</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                     <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">6</container>
                     <unittitle>
                        <title>Capitol News Highlights</title>, <unitdate>Mar 1975</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                     <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">7</container>
                     <unittitle>
                        <title>Reports from Washington</title>,<unitdate> 1968-74</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">8</container>
                  <unittitle>Legislative bills,<unitdate> 1966-72</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">9</container>
                  <unittitle>Press releases,<unitdate> 1971-76</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES III. SPEECHES AND WRITINGS</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">10</container>
                  <unittitle>Articles,<unitdate> 1969-74</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Speeches</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Addresses to private organizations</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04 level="file">
                     <did>
                        <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                        <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">11-15</container>
                        <unittitle>
                           <unitdate>1965-70</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04 level="file">
                     <did>
                        <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                        <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">1-9</container>
                        <unittitle>
                           <unitdate>1971-73</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04 level="file">
                     <did>
                        <container type="box" label="mixed materials">3</container>
                        <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">1-6</container>
                        <unittitle>
                           <unitdate>1974-82, undated</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <container type="box" label="mixed materials">3</container>
                     <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">7-13</container>
                     <unittitle>Commencement addresses,<unitdate> 1965-75</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Congressional statements</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04 level="file">
                     <did>
                        <container type="box" label="mixed materials">4</container>
                        <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">1-11</container>
                        <unittitle>
                           <unitdate>1965 - Jul 1971</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04 level="file">
                     <did>
                        <container type="box" label="mixed materials">5</container>
                        <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">1-10</container>
                        <unittitle>
                           <unitdate>Aug 1971-1975, undated</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
