<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">


  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss572.xml//EN">mnsss572</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Marianne Walters Papers, 1969-2000</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 14.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">September 30, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Walters, Marianne</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Marianne Walters papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1969-2000</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 581</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">8 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(8.25 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Social worker. The papers document Walters' involvement in the Women's Project in Family Therapy in Philadelphia, PA, which she founded, and the Family Therapy Practice Center in Washington, D.C., which she also founded. The collection also includes personal
and professional correspondence, writings, and documents pertaining to speaking engagements, and grants, projects, and workshops in which she was involved.  The collection is strong in the subject areas of feminist family therapy; therapy for members of single-parent, low-income households; and mother/daughter and father/daughter relationships.  [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>
</did>


<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Marianne Walters was born in Washington, DC in 1930.  She graduated from Woodrow Wilson High School.  She received her bachelor's degree from the University of California at Berkeley in 1952 and her MSW from the University of Illinois in 1954. Her marriage to Joseph Hart Walters ended in divorce;  the couple had three daughters: Lisa, Suzanna, and Pamela. Throughout the 1960s, Walters was involved in civil rights marches, war protests, abortion rights sit-ins and gay rights demonstrations. She also worked with the Southern Christian Leadership Conference during the 1968 Poor People's March on Washington, helping organize Resurrection City, a tent city on the Washington Mall.  From 1963 to 1966, Walters was chief social worker for a pilot project sponsored by the Center for Youth and Community Studies at Howard University, and from 1966 to 1980 she was a family therapist in Philadelphia.  From 1975 to 1980, she served as executive director of the Family Therapy Training Center at the Philadelphia Child Guidance Clinic, where she was known for her work with single-parent, low-income families.</p>

<p>  In 1978, she founded the Women's Project in Family Therapy and, after returning to her home town of Washington, DC, founded the Family Therapy Practice Center there in 1980. It was one of the first family clinics in the country to be run by a woman.  The Center trains therapists and counselors, administers research projects, and works with area family service agencies such as a local shelter for abused and runaway youth. The Center also provides family therapy services to underserved populations in the area.  Walters was the author of numerous articles and monographs, and the editor of several books. She was co-author, along with colleagues at the Women's Project, of <title render="italic">The Invisible Web : Gender Patterns in Family Relationships</title> (1988). Marianne Walters died on February 21, 2006.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>The Marianne Walters Papers document Walters's involvement in the Women's Project in Family Therapy in Philadelphia, PA, which she founded, and the Family Therapy Practice Center in Washington, DC, which she also founded. The collection also includes personal and professional
correspondence, and documents pertaining to speaking engagements, and grants, projects, and workshops in which she was involved.  The collection is strong in the subject areas of feminist family therapy; therapy for members of single-parent, low-income households; and mother/daughter and father/daughter relationships. Writings by Walters are also included.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>
 

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:  the collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
                         <item>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance
notice.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>


 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works created by
Marianne Walters in this collection.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by
those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions
or quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and
satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Marianne Walters Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>

<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Marianne Walters in 2007.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by  Burd Schlessinger, 2007 </p>
</processinfo>

<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Family social work -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Family psychotherapy -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Family therapists -- Biography</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminist therapy -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Low-income single mothers -- United States -- Social conditions</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Clinical psychology -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Social work education -- Study and teaching -- United States</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Walters, Marianne</persname> 

</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
