<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss459.xml//EN">mnsss459</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Townsend-O'Brien-Hoffheimer Family Papers, 1878-1991</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>

     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
 
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
 
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <famname encodinganalog="100 3" source="lcnaf">Townsend-O'Brien-Hoffheimer Family</famname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Townsend-O'Brien-Hoffheimer family papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1878-1991</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 302</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">7 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(8 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
   
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Professor, languages; Naturalist; Civic volunteer; Army Intelligence officer, World War II; Author; Teacher. The Townsend-O'Brien-Hoffheimer Family papers consists primarily of correspondence between these three generations of women and other family;  diaries of Smith College years for both mother and daughter.             </abstract>
</did>
 
<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>The Townsend-O'Brien-Hoffheimer Family Papers include material from Charlotte Townsend (?-1926); Margaret Townsend O'Brien (1889-1961); Charlotte Townsend O'Brien Hoffheimer (1919-1991); and Margaret Townsend O'Brien II (1917-  ). Of these three generations of women, two generations were Smith students.  After their Smith graduations Margaret Townsend O'Brien II earned a Ph.D. from Harvard and taught languages and  Charlotte Townsend O'Brien Hoffheimer served as a WAC officer in World War II, deciphering Japanese code.  The collection also includes two generations of naturalists and two  interfaith marriages (Margaret Townsend O'Brien married an Irish Catholic and Charlotte Townsend O'Brien Hoffheimer  married a Jewish man). Charlotte Townsend O'Brien Hoffheimer volunteered for numerous social and civil organizations.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>The Townsend-O'Brien-Hoffheimer Family Collection consists primarily of correspondence between these three generations of women and other family.  Two-thirds of the collection consists of  letters from Margaret O'Brien Townsend (I) and  the remaining third is composed of letters from her daughter, Charlotte Townsend O'Brien. There are letters from Smith College and some diaries are also document Smith years for both mother and daughter.  Margaret Townsend O'Brien's I's letters discuss daily boarding school life and close relationships with female classmates.  Other subjects discussed include Margaret Townsend O'Brien's bout with serious illness when she was young; Margaret II's career as a professor of languages; and Charlotte Townsend O'Brien Hoffheimer's army experiences. The letters are rich in detail about personal development, family life, and similar subjects.   Charlotte Townsend O'Brien suggested that "her greatest historical accomplishment, like her mother's, was probably the private transmission of a cultured, reverent view of nature to the younger generation." </p>   
   <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
 </scopecontent>


    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                    <p>Researchers must sign an Access Agreement Form, agreeing to protect confidentiality, before using this collection.</p>
                    <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use. </p>
</accessrestrict>

     <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The material in this collection may be protected by copyright. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights for permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Permission must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
     </userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Townsend-O'Brien-Hoffheimer Family, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>


<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>
     <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Townsend-O'Brien-Hoffheimer Family was donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Michael H. Hoffheimer in 1994.</p>
     </acqinfo>


<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Family--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Mothers and daughters--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Naturalists--United States</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Smith College--Students--History--Sources</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Education--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1939-1945--Women--Personal narratives, American</subject>
	<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Nature stories</genreform> 
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">United States--Social life and customs--19th century--Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Courtship--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Marriage--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">United States--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources</geogname> 

         	<famname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Hoffheimer family</famname> 
	<famname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">O'Brien family</famname> 
	<famname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Townsend family</famname> 

</controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->
</archdesc>
</ead>
