<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss390.html">mnsss390</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">G.J. Stillson MacDonnell Papers, 1970-1987</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       </titlestmt>
       <publicationstmt>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
         <address>
           <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
         </address>
         <date calendar="gregorian" era="ce">© 2006</date>
         <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by
 Margaret Jessup.
          <date>2006-12-01</date>
     </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter id="front">
    <titlepage>
      <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb />Smith College<lb /></publisher>
   <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">G.J. Stillson MacDonnell Papers, 1970-1987</titleproper>
   <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
   <num>MS 70</num>

   <date encodinganalog="260$c">2006</date>
   

       <p>© 2006 Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
   </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
 <did id="main">
 	<head>Collection Overview</head>
 <origination label="Creator:">
     <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">MacDonnell, G.J. Stillson</persname>
 </origination>
   <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">G.J. Stillson MacDonnell Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1970-1987</unitdate>
 <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 70</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">3 boxes</extent>
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(3.75 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
    <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>

  </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
 <!-- MRJ: EDIT ABSTRACT  -->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Lawyer; Civic leader; Lobbyist. Papers document the Connecticut women's movement in the 1970s and 1980s, including women's organizations such as the Feminist Credit Union, the Coalition of Connecticut Organizations Concerned with Women's Issues, the Connecticut Commission on the Status of Women, the first rape crisis service and the first battered women's shelter in Connecticut. Topics include the Equal Rights Amendment, gay rights, married women's surname, and taxation of single people. NOTE: There is no container list online for this finding aid.  You may contact the Sophia
Smith Collection if you want one sent to you.
    </abstract>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
    <head>Biographical Note</head>
       <p>G.J. Stillson MacDonnell was born in Danbury, Connecticut in 1947 and graduated from New York University. She received a law degree from the University of Connecticut in 1973.  In 1974 she started an independent practice in Hartford and 5 months later joined a Hartford law firm.  She was founder and attorney for Hartford Rape Crisis Service; chair of Coalition of Connecticut, an organization concerned with women's issues; attorney and board member of Connecticut Feminist Federal Credit Union in New Haven. MacDonnell frequently worked as unpaid lobbyist for feminist organizations and testified before Connecticut legislator for the ERA, abortion rights, divorce, sexual assault laws, and gay rights.  In 1969 she a joined larger firm working with legal issues of employee benefits.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
       <p>The G.J. Stillson MacDonnell papers document the Connecticut women's movement in the 1970s and 1980s.  They include material on women's organizations such as the founding of the Feminist Credit Union, the Coalition of Connecticut Organizations Concerned with Women's Issues, the Connecticut Commission on the Status of Women, the first rape crisis service and the first battered women's shelter in Connecticut.  Also represented are MacDonnell's legal activities in Connecticut, working with, and lobbying for, women's issues in the state legislature, including the Equal Rights Amendment, gay rights, and various civil rights campaigns. Additional research files include material on the history of married women's surname; Vivian Kellems' research on taxation of single people; and issues of women's periodicals and newspapers.</p>
      <p> NOTE: There is no container list online for this finding aid.  You may contact the
Sophia Smith Collection if you want one sent to you.</p>
</scopecontent>
 
     <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
      <head>Information on Use</head>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
         <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
          <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection.</p>
          <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to
use.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
        <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
        </userestrict>
    </descgrp>
      <prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>G.J. Stillson MacDonnell Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
Northampton, Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>
</descgrp>

   <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
       <head>Search Terms</head>
<!-- HIGHLIGHT EACH SEARCH TERM AND CLICK ON APPROPRIATE SUBJECT CLIPS -->
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Kellems, Vivien, 1896-1975</persname> 
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">MacDonnell, G.J. Stillson</persname> 
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abortion--Law and legislation--Connecticut--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Equal rights amendments--United States --History --Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists--Connecticut--Biography--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Married women--United States--Names</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in politics--Connecticut--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women lawyers--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Legal status, laws, etc.--Connecticut--20th century--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Services for--Connecticut--History--Sources</subject>


 </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->