<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss431.xml//EN">mnsss431</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Camp Bonnie Brae Records, 1917-2007 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Camp Bonnie Brae (East Otis, Mass.)</corpname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Camp Bonnie Brae Records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1917-2007 (ongoing)</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 592</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">13 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(11 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Camp for girls. Records document camp activities and include  photographs; administrative records from the camps founding in 1919 through 2007, including correspondence, reports, minutes, financial information, information about staff, songbooks, publicity materials, and publications; and as well as files pertaining to buildings and grounds.
 
                 </abstract>
        

</did>
 

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Historical Note</head>
     <p>Camp Bonnie Brae, located in East Otis, Massachusetts, is the oldest continuously operating Girl Scout camp in the United States. Begun in 1919, the camp is administered by the Girl Scouts of Pioneer Valley in East Longmeadow, Massachusetts. The original building was an inn, also called Bonnie Brae, and was owned by Loring P. Lane.  Edith Sinnett, first director of the Springfield Girl Scouts, and her friend, Edith G. Newell, wished to see the organization establish a summer camp, and in the summer of 1919 they rented Bonnie Brae from the Lane family and gave public notice that Girl Scouts could apply to attend. The fee was five dollars per week. The program for summer included nature study, as well as tennis, basketball, baseball, and volleyball. The official uniform was middy blouse and bloomers. No high heels or silk stockings were allowed. A bugler and a cook were hired for the summer, and two dietitians from Boston planned the menus for the camp.  The success of the 1919 camp season made certain the continuation of the project, so accordingly the Girl Scout Council bought the 227 acres of land, the buildings, and the furniture from Mr. Lane for $10,000. Counselors served on a volunteer basis, and came from various occupations around the Springfield area. The camp maintained a 1:7 staff to camper ratio. In 1921, several troops of the Springfield Council donated money for scholarships so that girls who lacked the fees could attend. The camp has always accommodated persons of all races, creeds, and economic backgrounds. Also in 1921, the waterfront program at Camp Bonnie Brae was reorganized by an instructor from the American Red Cross. The campers were divided into three groups according to their swimming skills, and great emphasis was placed on graduating from one group to the next. The system of water buddies as a means of keep track of swimmers was instituted at Camp Bonnie Brae, the first camp in the country to do so. To enable Bonnie Brae to accommodate older girls, and to offer a better program for younger scouts, property was purchased a half-mile from Bonnie Brae and a Brownie Camp established there in 1941. Also in 1941, the Second Western Hemisphere Encampment was held at Camp Bonnie Brae. Girls from fourteen countries and from all over the United States attended. The guest of honor was Eleanor Roosevelt, and during her visit she spoke with the girls about democracy, proper nutrition, the bases of a post-war peace, and international cooperation. The camp has expanded its facilities over the years to include more campers and offer more activities. As of 2007, the summer program accomodated 140 girls from around the country and the world. There are also non-residential programs offerd in spring, fall, and winter.</p>
</bioghist>


<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The Camp Bonnie Brae Records consist of extensive documentation of camp activities, notably photographs; files pertaining to construction and maintenance of buildings and grounds, including maps, blueprints, drawings, and photographs; and administrative records from the camps founding in 1919 through 2007, including correspondence, reports, minutes, financial information, information about staff, songbooks, publicity materials, and publications.  Thre are also documentary films, slides of camp grounds and activities, a camp scrapbook, and memorabilia.  Recent additions pertain to Adeline Friedlander, from her time as a camper at Camp Bonnie Brae in the late 1920s and early 1930s; materials from her funeral (2007),  and from the dedication of the Girl Scouts of Western Massachusetts's Adeline M. Friedlander Museum and Visitor Center (2009).  A small amount of clippings and photographs relating to the camp, collected by Friedlander, is also included.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

<p>Note: the films from this collection have been digitized and are available to 
<extref href="https://media.smith.edu/departments/ssc/cbb/cbb_playlist.html">view online</extref>.</p>
        
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
        <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
   	<list type="simple">
             <item>Partially restricted access - contact the Sophia Smith Collection for more information.</item>
               	<item>Researchers must sign an Access Agreement Form before using this collection, agreeing to protect the confidentiality of living persons.</item>
              	<item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
    </list></p>

</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Camp Bonnie Brae Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

    <altformavail id="admin-altform">
		<head>Additional Formats</head>
	<p>The films from this collection have been digitized and are available to 
<extref href="https://media.smith.edu/departments/ssc/cbb/cbb_playlist.html">view online</extref>.</p>
    </altformavail>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Camp Bonnie Brae Records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Shelly Kolb and Jill Paul in 2007.</p>
</acqinfo>


<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger, 2008. </p> 
</processinfo>


<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American girls--Massachusetts--History--Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Camp Bonnie Brae (East Otis, Mass.)--History--Sources</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Camps--Massachusetts--History--Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Girl Scouts of the Pioneer Valley--History--Sources</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Girl Scouts of Western Massachusetts</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Girls--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Girl Scouts of the United States of America--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Girls--Societies and clubs--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Girls--Health and hygiene--United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Race relations--Massachusetts</subject>
</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material:  Photographs at the Connecticut Valley Historical Museum (Springfield, Mass.)</p>
	
    </relatedmaterial>


</archdesc>
</ead>
