<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss445.xml//EN">mnsss445</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Diann L. Neu Papers, c1977-2005 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>

     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Neu, Diann L., 1948-</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Diann L. Neu papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">c1977-2005 (ongoing)</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 532</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">5 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(5.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Theologian; Feminist; Psychotherapist.  Papers document Neu's education in theology; her work and activism re: articulating and advocating radical new forms of feminist theology, and in re-defining the role of women in the church; her participation in numerous conferences about women in the church; and materials pertaining to her two books, <title render="italic">Return Blessings: Ecofeminist Blessings Renewing the Earth</title> (2002) and <title render="italic">Women's Rites: Feminist Liturgies for Life's Journeys</title> (2003). Types of material include correspondence, interviews, lecture notes, minutes, sermons, speeches, transcripts, writings, slides, and audiovisual material.
 
                 </abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
     <p>Diann L. Neu was born in 1948.  She earned her Masters in Clinical Social Work from The Catholic University of America, her Master of Sacred Theology degree from The Jesuit School of Theology at Berkeley, and her Doctor of Ministry in International Feminist Theology from the San Francisco Theological Seminary.  Trained in liturgy and spirituality, she has done extensive work in designing liturgies for national and international conferences as well as for her own women-church base community in the Washington, DC area.   In 1983, Neu and her partner, Mary E. Hunt, founded the Women's Alliance for Theology, Ethics, and Ritual (WATER) in Silver Spring, MD.  In private practice as a psychotherapist, as well as in her affiliation with WATER, she counsels women and men from widely divergent backgrounds in individual, couple, and group sessions.  Neu lectures and conducts workshops throughout the United States, in Latin America and Europe, and has published numerous books of rituals and articles on the subject of feminist approaches to liturgy, spirituality, and therapy. She has received many awards for her work and is the author of two books, <title render="italic">Women's Rites: Feminist Liturgies for Life's Journey</title>  (2002) and <title render="italic">Return Blessings: Ecofeminist Liturgies Renewing the Earth</title> (2003). Her publications from WATERworks Press are <title render="italic">Peace Liturgies</title>; <title render="italic">Gathered at Sophia's Table: A Feminist Peace Seder</title>; <title render="italic">Women-Church Sourcebook</title>; <title render="italic">Women of Fire: A Pentecost Event</title>; <title render="italic">Women and the Gospel Traditions</title>; <title render="italic">Women-Church Celebrations</title>; <title render="italic">A Seder of the Sisters of Sarah</title>; <title render="italic">Miriam's Sisters Rejoice</title>; and 	<title render="italic">Together at Freedom's Table</title>.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The Diann L. Neu Papers consist of information about Neu's education, including her M.A. thesis and Ph.D. dissertation in theology; her work and activism re: articulating and advocating radical new forms of feminist theology, and in re-defining the role of women in the church; materials documenting her participation in numerous conferences about women in the church; and materials pertaining to her two books, <title render="italic">Return Blessings: Ecofeminist Blessings Renewing the Earth</title> (2002) and <title render="italic">Women's Rites: Feminist Liturgies for Life's Journeys</title> (2003).  Neu's efforts to define and promulgate a feminist, woman-oriented perspective in Christian liturgy are particularly well-documented. Types of material include correspondence, email, interviews, lecture notes, agendas, minutes, sermons, speeches, transcripts, writings, and slides. there is also a significant amount of audiovisual material documenting interviews, lectures, and sermons by Neu.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                    <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
                     <p>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</p>
                     <p>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The material in this collection may be protected by copyright. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights for permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Permission must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Diann L. Neu Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Diann L. Neu in 2005.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger in 2005. </p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Ecofeminism--Religious aspects</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminist spirituality--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminist theology--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbianism--Religious aspects--Christianity</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Liturgics--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Religion--Study and teaching--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women and religion--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in Christianity</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Women's Alliance for Theology, Ethics and Ritual</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Hunt, Mary E., 1951-</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Neu, Diann L., 1948-</persname> 


        	<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf"> Hunt, Mary E., 1951-</persname> 
</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material in the
          <extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss438_main.html">Mary E. Hunt Papers</extref> and the
          <extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss462_main.html">Women's Alliance for Theology, Ethics and Ritual Records</extref>, Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>

</archdesc>
</ead>
