<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
   <eadheader audience="internal" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b">
      <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss141.xml//EN">mnsss141</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Jane Addams Papers, 1904-1960
        </titleproper>
            <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
            <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Amanda Izzo.</author>
            <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            <date encodinganalog="260$c">2003 </date>
            <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded using Perl scripts and edited in XMetal 2.0. Encoded by Brook Hopkins.
        <date>2003-07-01</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2005-09-23">2005-09-23</date>
            <item>mnsss141 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02-5c.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter id="front">
      <titlepage>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection Smith College
         
            </publisher>
         <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Jane Addams Papers, 1904-1960
      </titleproper>
         <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
         <num>MS 1
      </num>
         <author encodinganalog="245$c">Amanda Izzo
      </author>
         <date>2001
      </date>
         
         <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         <p>©  2003  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did id="main">
         <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Addams, Jane, 1860-1935</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Jane Addams papers</unittitle>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1904-1960</unitdate>
         <unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1904-1936</unitdate>
         <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 1 UUID:6efa6ad3-4acb-44c0-ab0e-65dbc9c65939</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Quantity:">
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">2 boxes</extent>
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1.5 linear ft.)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            </repository>
         <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Founder, Hull House, Chicago; pacifist; labor organizer; settlement house worker; and women's rights advocate. The Addams papers contain primarily published material and duplicates of materials from the Swarthmore Peace Collection. Included are articles, books, memorials, and memorabilia about Addams, as well as writings and speeches by her.  There is a small amount of original correspondence, plus photographs and drawings of Jane Addams and Hull House.</abstract>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
            <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <bioghist id="bioghist">
         

         <p>(Laura) Jane Addams was born on 6 September 1860 in
    Cedarville, Illinois. She was the youngest of five children
    of John Huy Addams and Sarah Weber Addams. Her father was a
    prosperous mill owner and a leader in state politics; he
    served for sixteen years as an Illinois state senator. Her
    mother died when Addams was only two years old. Her father
    married Anna H. Haldeman in 1865, which added two
    stepbrothers to the family. Jane Addams was profoundly
    influenced by her father. He encouraged her education and
    ambition; however, when she set her heart on attending Smith
    College, he refused to send her so far away from home. In
    1877, she entered Rockford Female Seminary in nearby
    Rockford, Illinois. In 1881, Addams was the valedictorian of
    her graduating class. One year later she received a
    bachelor's degree when the school became the Rockford College
    for Women.</p>
         <p>Addams planned to study medicine and become a doctor. In
    1881, she began her schooling at the Women's Medical College
    of Pennsylvania. Her father's sudden death and her own ill
    health forced Addams to abandon her medical studies. In 1882,
    she had surgery to remedy a congenital spinal defect. Addams,
    accompanied by her stepmother, traveled in Europe from 1883
    until 1885. In London's East end she observed urban poverty
    first hand; this exposure left a lasting impression on
    Addams. In 1887, Addams returned to Europe with Ellen Gates
    Starr, a Rockford classmate. On this trip, which included a
    visit to Toynbee Hall, a settlement house in London's East
    End, Addams and Starr formulated ideas about establishing a
    settlement house in the U.S. that would directly address the
    human consequences of rapid industrialization, immigration,
    and urban poverty.</p>
         <p>After their return to the United States in 1899, Addams
    and Starr leased a dilapidated mansion in one of the poorest
    immigrant slums of Chicago on the corner of Halstead and Polk
    streets. Hull House, which was named after the original
    owner, was the first settlement house in America. Its mission
    was to "investigate and improve the conditions in the
    industrial districts of Chicago" and function as a center of
    civic and social life in a neighborhood that consisted of
    multiple immigrant groups. It was both an educational and a
    philanthropic activity. Addams, Starr, and other activists
    and reformers who resided at Hull House learned first-hand
    the needs of a diverse urban community. Hull House residents
    raised money; found volunteers, especially among the growing
    number of female college students and graduates; helped sick
    children, displaced families, and the unemployed; taught
    vocational and educational classes; and offered their support
    to Chicago's working people. Hull House provided numerous
    activities and services including: health and child care,
    clubs for both children and adults, an art gallery, kitchen,
    gymnasium, music school, theater, library, employment bureau,
    and a labor museum.</p>
         <p>Through her work at Hull House, Addams became heavily
    involved with civic affairs of Chicago and was a leader in
    the social reform movement. She fought for legislation
    regarding housing, sanitation, factory inspection, and
    immigrant rights. She also effectively campaigned for child
    labor laws and other protective legislation. Addams became
    strongly allied with the labor movement and allowed union
    organizing meetings to be held at Hull House. In 1910, she
    arbitrated a garment strike involving 90,000 workers. That
    year she also became Vice President of the American Branch of
    International Association for Labor Legislation. Addams was a
    feminist and supported the women's suffrage campaign. She
    served as Vice President of the National American Woman
    Suffrage Association (1911-14). She was also active in the
    Progressive Party and especially supported its platform for
    industrial safety.</p>
         <p>Hull House brought Jane Addams world-wide celebrity, and
    she was recognized as a pioneer in the field of social work.
    However, with the onset of war in Europe in the 1910s, public
    opinion turned against Addams as she became increasingly
    active in the pacifist and internationalist movements. In
    1915, Addams co-founded the Women's Peace Party (WPP). Addams
    and the WPP established strong networks of peace activists in
    the U.S. and abroad, and in 1919, the WPP evolved into the
    Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, a
    still-thriving organization that "works to achieve through
    peaceful means world disarmament, full rights for women,
    racial and economic justice, an end to all forms of violence,
    and to establish those political, social, and psychological
    conditions which can assure peace, freedom, and justice for
    all." Jane Addams served as the first president of WILPF
    (1919-1929). In 1931, Addams was awarded the Nobel Peace
    Prize for her pacifist activism. She was the first American
    woman to receive this honor.</p>
         <p>Addams wrote prodigiously throughout her life, and the
    profits from her books were her main source of income. Some
    of her notable works are Newer Ideals of Peace (1907), Twenty
    Years at Hull House (1910), The Long Road of Women's Memory
    (1916), Peace and Bread in Time of War (1922), and The Second
    Twenty Years at Hull House (1930). She received honorary
    degrees from numerous colleges and universities including:
    Wisconsin, Smith, Yale, Tufts, Northwestern, Chicago, and
    Bryn Mawr. Among her many other achievements and commitments,
    Jane Addams was a founding member of the NAACP (1909) and the
    ACLU (1920). She died of cancer in 1935, and she was buried
    at her childhood home in Cedarville, Illinois.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="scope">
         
         <p>The Jane Addams papers consist of 1.5 linear feet of
    material. They contain primarily duplicates from the
    Swarthmore Peace Collection. There is some biographical
    information including articles (1898-1961), obituaries
    (1935), memorials (1935-60), and typescripts of radio
    broadcasts about her (1932-40). Organizational and historical
    information about the Women's International League for Peace
    and Freedom is included in the memorials section. There are
    typescripts of speeches by Addams (1912-33), which provide
    her perspective on topics including social service, women's
    issues, and World War I. Many reprints of articles
    (1898-1935) by Addams also offer insight as to her opinion on
    a variety of subjects. Some topics addressed in this section
    are: nationalism, peace, politics, labor, suffrage, women's
    rights, WWI, and social work.</p>
         <p>There are some articles and printed material regarding
    Hull House (1897-1950), and a few photographs and pictures of
    Addams and Hull House. A small amount of correspondence
    consists of a few original autographed letters to friends
    (1903-1934).</p>
         <p>The Jane Addams Papers are closely related to the <extref href="mnsss64_main.html">Ellen
        Gates Starr Papers</extref> in the Sophia Smith Collection.
    Researchers may wish also to consult the Peace and Settlement
    House Collections for further information about the Women's
    International League for Peace and Freedom and Hull House, as
    well as the Schwimmer-Lloyd and Madeleine Zabriskie Doty
    Papers (re: WILPF) and the Jessie Lloyd O'Connor Papers
    (O'Connor was a resident/worker at Hull House).</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
         <head>Information on Use</head>
         <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
               <p>The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
          </p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
               <p>The copyright owner of this collection is unknown. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.
          </p>
            </userestrict>
         </descgrp>
         <prefercite id="admin-cite">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
            <p>The Jane Addams Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <altformavail encodinganalog="530" id="admin-altform">
            <head>Additional Formats</head>
            <p>The Swarthmore College Peace Collection is the primary repository for Jane Addams's papers. There is a microfilm version available, of which the Sophia Smith Collection has a portion of the correspondence series.
        </p>
         </altformavail>
         <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>History of the Collection</head>
            <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
               <p>The Jane Addams Papers were given by various donors, mostly unknown. Swarthmore donated a significant amount of duplicates from their Peace Collection in 1951.
          </p>
            </acqinfo>
            <processinfo id="admin-process">
               <p>Reprocessed by Amanda Izzo, 2001.</p>
            </processinfo>
         </descgrp>
      </descgrp>
      <controlaccess id="subj">
         <head>Search Terms</head>
         
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Addams, Jane,
                        1860-1935</persname>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">Hull House
                        (Chicago, Ill.)--History--Sources</corpname>
         <name>Women's International League for Peace and
                        Freedom--History</name>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women social
                        reformers--United States--History--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Social
                        settlements--United States--History--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">
                        Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources</subject>
         <name>Women in labor movement--United
                        States--History--20th century--Sources</name>
         <name>Peace movements--History--20th
                        century--Sources</name>
         <name>Women and peace--History</name>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Chicago
                        (Ill.)--Social conditions--20th century--Sources</geogname>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">
                        Europe--Description and travel--Sources</geogname>
      </controlaccess>
      <descgrp id="addinfo" type="add">
         <head>Additional Information</head>
         <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
            <head>Related Material</head>
            <p>Related material can be found in the <extref href="mnsss64_main.html">Ellen Gates Starr Papers</extref>, Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
            <p>Primary collection of Jane Addams Papers at Swarthmore Peace Collection, Swarthmore College.
        </p>
         </relatedmaterial>
      </descgrp>
      <dsc id="contlist" type="in-depth">
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">A</container>
               <unittitle>Contents and National Union Catalog of
            Manuscripts sheet</unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">1</container>
               <unittitle>Articles by Jane Addams,
            <unitdate>1910</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">2</container>
               <unittitle>Articles about Jane Addams,
            <unitdate>1906-78</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">3</container>
               <unittitle>Bibliography</unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">4</container>
               <unittitle>Biographical fact sheet</unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">5</container>
               <unittitle>Citations, honors, and prizes,
            <unitdate>1926-32</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>Newspaper clippings</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">6</container>
                  <unittitle>About Jane Addams,
              <unitdate>1898-1961</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">7</container>
                  <unittitle>Obituaries,
              <unitdate>1935</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">8</container>
                  <unittitle>Book reviews of books by and about Jane
              Addams</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">9</container>
                  <unittitle>Zurich Peace Conference (International Conference of Women),
              <unitdate>1919</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">10</container>
                  <unittitle>Bailie, Helen Tufts,
              <unitdate>1928</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">11</container>
                  <unittitle>Miss Blake,
              <unitdate>1930</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">12</container>
                  <unittitle>Miss Browne,
              <unitdate>1903</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">13</container>
                  <unittitle>Miss Fitts,
              <unitdate>1904, 1927, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">14</container>
                  <unittitle>Mack, Rebecca Robins,
              <unitdate>1933, 1934</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>Hull House</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">15</container>
                  <unittitle>Newspaper clippings and
              articles</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">16</container>
                  <unittitle>Printed material,
              <unitdate>1897-1950, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">17</container>
                  <unittitle>Yearbook,
              <unitdate>1925, 1929, 1934</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>Memorials</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">18</container>
                  <unittitle>Memorial service programs and Jane Addams
              memorial medal by Nancy Cox McCormack,
              <unitdate>1935</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">1</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">19</container>
                  <unittitle>Jane Addams Centennial,
              <unitdate>1960</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">20</container>
               <unittitle>Photographs and pictures of Jane Addams and
            Hull House</unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">21</container>
               <unittitle>Radio broadcast (NBC),
            <unitdate>1932, 1936, 1940</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">22</container>
               <unittitle>Speeches on various topics,
            <unitdate>1912-33</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>Articles by Jane Addams</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">23</container>
                  <unittitle>Education,
              <unitdate>1907, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">24</container>
                  <unittitle>Immigration,
              <unitdate>1905-19</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">25</container>
                  <unittitle>Labor, 1898(?)-
              <unitdate>1935, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">26</container>
                  <unittitle>League of Nations,
              <unitdate>1919-20</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">27</container>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous: Gordon Dewey, John Dewey,
              Egypt, food, Jenkin Lloyd Jones, juvenile
              delinquency, Julia Lathrop, Mexico, old age, women,
              <unitdate>1898-1935, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">28</container>
                  <unittitle>Nationalism,
              <unitdate>1919-34, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">29</container>
                  <unittitle>Peace,
              <unitdate>1913-35, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">30</container>
                  <unittitle>Playgrounds,
              <unitdate>1907-12</unitdate>
              (?)</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">31</container>
                  <unittitle>Politics,
              <unitdate>1905-24, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">32</container>
                  <unittitle>Prohibition,
              <unitdate>1929-35</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">33</container>
                  <unittitle>Prostitution,
              <unitdate>1911-28</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">34</container>
                  <unittitle>Settlements,
              <unitdate>1892-1919</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">35</container>
                  <unittitle>Social questions,
              <unitdate>1908-31, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">36</container>
                  <unittitle>Social work,
              <unitdate>1909-33</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">37</container>
                  <unittitle>Suffrage,
              <unitdate>1908-13, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">38</container>
                  <unittitle>Tolstoy,
              <unitdate>1902-28</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">39</container>
                  <unittitle>Women's rights,
              <unitdate>1915-30</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="box" label="mixed materials">2</container>
                  <container type="folder" label="mixed materials">40</container>
                  <unittitle>World War I,
              <unitdate>1915-33, undated</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-serOV">
            <did>
               <unittitle>OVERSIZE MATERIALS</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <container type="map-case" label="mixed materials">Flat File</container>
                  <unittitle>Drawings, includes Jane Addams and Hull
            House, by Gwenyth King Brown,
            <unitdate>1958</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>ON SHELF</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Cathedral of Compassion: Dramatic Outline of
            the Life of Jane Addams, 1860-1935. Violet Oakley (1955)
            </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02 level="file">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>By Addams</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Jane Addams, A Centennial Reader,
              <unitdate>1960</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Twenty Years at Hull House,
              <unitdate>1910</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>The Long Road of Woman's Memory,
              <unitdate>1916</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03 level="file">
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>The Second Twenty Years at Hull House,
              <unitdate>1930</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
