<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss529.xml//EN">mnsss529</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Alliance Against Women's Oppression Records, 1980-1989</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Sharon Davenport, revised by Nichole Calero.</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2013">2013</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Jeanne Lowrey. 
		<date normal="2013-03-26">2013-03-26</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	  </langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Alliance Against Women's Oppression</corpname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Alliance Against Women's Oppression records</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1980-1989</unitdate>
	
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 699</unitid>
	<physloc label="Location Number:">12 boxes</physloc>
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">5.75 linear ft.</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
, <language langcode="spa">Spanish</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		International women of color organization, Welfare rights activists, Reproductive rights and Women's health advocates. The Records are primarily related to the Bay Area Chapter of the Alliance and contain documents that articulate and demonstrate the challenges of developing a revolutionary mass organization through position and discussion papers, drafts, and publications produced by the Alliance. There is abundant documentation of the processes of coalition and social investigation that AAWO engaged in reproductive rights advocacy.   The collection is rich in documentation of the organization Somos Hermanas in Nicaragua.   Types of materials include committee reports; meeting notes; political discussion papers; study guides. 
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	
		<p>In August of 1980, the Alliance Against Women's Oppression (AAWO) was formed out of a process of transformation and struggle begun in the Third World Women's Alliance (TWWA) in late 1979. The newly formed organization resolved to focus its organizing activities primarily on the struggle for women's rights and equality and against the racialized, gendered, classed sexism of the developed North. The AAWO announced itself as a multi-racial alliance of lesbian and straight women. Women of color lesbian issues that had been stubbornly ignored by the mainstream women's movement were part of the political line of the AAWO. </p>

<p>Continuing work initiated and produced by the TWWA, the AAWO persistently clarified the intersectionality of race, gender, class, and sexuality in its political analysis of capitalism and the conditions of women in the transnational economy. AAWO work areas included infant mortality, reproductive rights, sterilization abuse, Central American and African Women's liberation struggles, and Lesbian and Gay rights. The AAWO also continued the political education work of International Women's Day (IWD). AAWO members produced discussion and position papers for AAWO members and the public. AAWO had chapters in Boston, New York, Louisville, Seattle, and Washington, D.C.</p>

<p>In order to take up the struggle of women's oppression nationally and internationally, AAWO created coalitions and joined their efforts with other social justice organizations locally and globally. Some of the organizations they were closely associated with were Somos Hermanas, the Nicaraguan Women's Association (AMNLAE), MADRE, South African Women's Organization, Line of March (LOM), and the National Campaign to Restore Abortion Funding (NCRAF).  The AAWO identified itself with socialist, womanist/feminist politics, and provisionally based their political line on a Marxist class analysis. </p>

<p>The AAWO joined their efforts with the Reproductive Rights National Network (R2N2) to advocate for abortion rights for low-income women while also calling attention to the involuntary sterilization of migrant and immigrant women of color. In 1984 in response to the U.S.'s continuing intervention in Nicaragua, AAWO organized a delegation, Somos Hermanas, in alliance with the Nicaraguan women's mass organization, AMNLAE. 
</p>	
<p>AAWO dissolved by 1990. The Women of Color Resource Center (1989 to present) was formed with some members from the TWWA and AAWO. Activist organizational work stretching back to the civil rights movement, the Black Women's Caucus of SNCC, the Third World Women's Alliance and the Alliance Against Women's Oppression was evident in the activist and advocacy politics of the Women of Color Resource Center.
</p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="scope">
	
<p>	The Alliance against Women's Oppression Records consists of 5.75 linear ft. and are primarily related to the Bay Area Chapter of the Alliance. The collection contains many documents that articulate and demonstrate the challenges of developing a revolutionary mass organization.  The collection is a good source of position and discussion papers, drafts, and AAWO publications, produced by the Alliance. The "United Front Against War and Racism" is a political discussion paper that articulates some of AAWO's political strategy.  Through the Coalition Against Infant Mortality (CFIM), 1979 - 1982, AAWO continued the infant mortality activism begun in the TWWA. For the beginnings of this important project of the AAWO, see the TWWA Records also held by the Sophia Smith Collection.  </p>

<p>The collection has abundant documentation of the processes of coalition and social investigation that AAWO engaged in reproductive rights advocacy.   The collection is rich in documentation of Somos Hermanas's activities in Nicaragua.  Types of materials include committee reports; meeting notes; political discussion papers; study guides.

</p>

<p>The bulk of the papers date from 1983 to 1988 and focus on the Alliance's many projects organizing activities primarily on the struggle for third world women's rights and equality nationally and internationally.
</p>
    </scopecontent> 
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	
	<p>This collection is organized into seven series:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">I. ADMINISTRATIVE MATERIALS </ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">II. POLITICAL PAPERS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser3">III. PUBLICATIONS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser4">IV. AFFILIATED ORGANIZATIONS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser5"> V. SUBJECTS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser6">VI. PHOTOGRAPHS </ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser7">VII. OVERSIZE</ref>
		</item>
	</list>
    </arrangement>


<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.   </p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the records of the organization. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  Individual authors in AAOW publications retain copyright. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College as holders of the physical property. </p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Please cite papers as follows: "Alliance Against Women's Oppression Records."</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>Cheryl Johnson, Vicki Alexander, Barbara Morita, and Melanie Tervalon donated records to the Women of Color Resource Center Collection/Archives which were then donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by the Third World Women's Alliance Alumni Association Archives Committee. </p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Sharon Davenport, 2005. Revised by Nichole Calero, Fall 2012</p> 
    </processinfo>

<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
		
		<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abortion -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American women -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources
</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Asian American women -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Birth control -- United States -- History -- Sources
</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Civil rights -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Ethnicity -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Infants -- Mortality -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Hispanic American women -- History -- United States -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Indian women -- United States -- Social conditions -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">International economic relations</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">International Women's Day -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Latin American women -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Minority women -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reproductive health -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sterilization (birth control) -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">United States -- Race relations</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Welfare rights movement -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Economic conditions -- 20th century</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- El Salvador -- Social conditions</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- International cooperation</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Health and hygiene -- Developing countries</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Health and hygiene -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Political activity -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's health services -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's rights -- Developing countries</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Working class women -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Alliance Against the Oppression of Women (U.S.)</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Third World Women's Alliance</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Jones, Diane</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Morita, Barbara</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Tervalon, Melanie</persname> 
	    </controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->
    <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
	<p>Additional records are housed at the Mary McLeod Bethune Council House - National Archives for Black Women's History, Amistad Research Center, and Duke University.  Related materials in the SSC include <extref href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/vof/vof-intro.html">Voices of Feminism</extref> interviews with Frances Beal and Linda Burnham, and the <extref href="mnsss527_main.html">Third World Women's Alliance Records</extref>.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>

<!-- End additional information -->


<!-- Enter Series descriptions -->
<dsc type="analyticover">
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES I. ADMISTRATIVE MATERIALS  <unitdate>(1979-1988)</unitdate></unittitle>	
<physdesc>
		<extent>4.25 linear feet</extent>
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series consists of the organization's reports, financial materials, meeting agendas, meeting notes, histories, and committee reports. The bulk of  sub series Committees is comprised of organizational materials from the Coalition to Fight Infant Mortality (CFIM). The CFIM was originally organized within the Third World Women's Alliance (TWWA) and continued its work when the TWWA disbanded and reformed as the AAWO. Among the CFIM files are their community investigation into Alameda County's high mortality rate, correspondence to and from the Alameda County Grand Jury, the Grand Jury report, the Alameda County Health Care Services Agency report to the board of supervisors of the Alameda County Hospital, and the house hearings on infant mortality. The subseries, Reproductive Rights contains information from national committees that fought for reproductive rights such as the Action Committee for Abortion Rights (ACAR), the National Committee to Restore Abortion Funding (NCRAF), the Reproductive Rights National Network (R2N2) and the Seattle Reproductive Rights Alliance (SRRA). The subseries Somos Hermanas contains memos, correspondence, publications and planning notes from the organization, as well as photos and details from a delegation's trip to Nicaragua in 1986. </p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES II. POLITICAL PAPERS  <unitdate>(1982-N.D.)</unitdate></unittitle>
		<physdesc>
			<extent>.25 linear feet</extent>
		</physdesc></did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series consists of papers created by the AAWO on issues that they recognized as intersecting with their goals.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS  <unitdate>(1963-88)</unitdate></unittitle>
		<physdesc>
			<extent>.25 linear feet</extent>
		</physdesc>
</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series consists of brochures, discussion papers, flyers, the history of the organization and other publications produced by the group. </p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01> 



 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES IV. AFFILIATED ORGANIZATIONS  <unitdate>(1980-1987)</unitdate></unittitle>
		<physdesc>
			<extent>.5 linear feet</extent>
		</physdesc></did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series consists of information on, and publications from, the organizations listed in the finding aid. 
</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01> 

<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES V. SUBJECTS  <unitdate>(1978-1985, n.d.)</unitdate></unittitle>
		<physdesc>
			<extent>.25 linear feet</extent>
		</physdesc></did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series consists of research materials on the subjects listed. 

</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01> 
  
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>VI. PHOTOGRAPHS  <unitdate>(1984-1986, n.d.)</unitdate></unittitle>
		<physdesc>
			<extent>.25 linear feet</extent>
		</physdesc></did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series consists of undated group photographs. 

</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01> 



 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>VII. OVERSIZE MATERIALS <unitdate/></unittitle>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>Consists of posters from Nicaragua. </p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>  

</dsc>
<!-- End Series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->

<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Committees</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
               <unittitle>Coalition to fight infant mortality (CFIM)                    <unitdate>1978-1984, n.d.</unitdate>                </unittitle>
 <note><p>[hand written notes in CFIM attributed to Barbara Morita and Melanie Tervalon]</p>
 </note>
</did>

 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>AAWO assessments, 1979 - <unitdate>82, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>ACHCSA report to board of supervisors,<unitdate> 1980</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Children's hospital, 1981 - <unitdate>82, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4-6</container>
 <unittitle>Community investigation, I-Team,<unitdate> 1979-1980, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>First National Conference on Black Women's Health Issues<unitdate> 1983</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Grand jury correspondence and report,<unitdate> 1979-1980</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>House hearings on infant mortality, <unitdate>26 Mar 1982</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Letters and statements of support,<unitdate> 1978-80</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Newsletter, clippings, press releases,<unitdate> 1979-84, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <unittitle>International women's day committee (WCCIWD)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">3-8</container>
 <unittitle>International women's day (IWD),<unitdate> 1981-88 , n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Kwanza committee,<unitdate> 1979-81, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Lesbian/gay task force,<unitdate> 1981-86 , n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
               <unittitle>Nairobi, third world conference on women,                    <unitdate>1985</unitdate>                </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Notes, articles, and memos</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Conference Materials</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
               <unittitle>Reproductive rights,                    <unitdate>1982-86, n.d.</unitdate>                </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">5-6</container>
 <unittitle>Action committee for abortion rights (ACAR),<unitdate> 1981-85</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>National campaign to restore abortion funding, (NCRAF),<unitdate> 1984-87, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>National campaign to restore abortion funding (NCRAF),<unitdate> 1984-87, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">2-3</container>
 <unittitle>Reproductive rights national network (R2N2),<unitdate> 1982-84, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Rosie Jimenez-<unitdate>October 3rd </unitdate>coalition, 1982</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Seattle reproductive rights alliance (SRRA),<unitdate> 1985, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Steering Committee,<unitdate> 1981</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
               <unittitle>Somos Hermanas,                    <unitdate>1984-88</unitdate>                </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>AAWO memos<unitdate> 1984-1988</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Development plans and memoranda<unitdate> 1985-1987</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Louisville chapter,<unitdate> 1986-1987, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Nicaragua delegation, health colloquium,<unitdate> 1983</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Nicaragua delegation, member notes,<unitdate> 1986</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Nicaragua delegation, photographs<unitdate> 1986</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Nicaragua delegation, orientation<unitdate> 1986</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">3-4</container>
 <unittitle>Organization notes, national<unitdate> 1986-1988</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">5-6</container>
 <unittitle>Publications<unitdate> 1985-1989, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>World peace congress, Copenhagen<unitdate> 1986-1987</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Financial material,<unitdate> 1983-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Histories,<unitdate> 1980; 1989; n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
            <unittitle>Meetings,                 <unitdate>1981-88</unitdate>             </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Chapter meetings</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Bay area<unitdate> 1981-88</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 <c05>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">2-3</container>
 <unittitle>Summation meeting,<unitdate> 1988</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c05>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Boston, MA,<unitdate> 1988, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Louisville, KY,<unitdate> 1988-89, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>New York, NY,<unitdate> 1988, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Washington, D.C.,<unitdate> 1985-86, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <unittitle>National meetings</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>First national congress,<unitdate> 1983</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Second national congress,<unitdate> 1986</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Second national congress, continued<unitdate> 1986</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>National council,<unitdate> 1983-84</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>National council,<unitdate> 1985</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>National council,<unitdate> 1986</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>National council,<unitdate> 1987</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">6-7</container>
 <unittitle>National council,<unitdate> 1988</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Executive,<unitdate> 1983</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Executive,<unitdate> 1984</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Executive,<unitdate> 1986</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Executive,<unitdate> 1987</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Executive,<unitdate> 1988</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">4-9</container>
 <unittitle>Member's notebook, Diane Jones, Bay area,<unitdate> 1983-88</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Membership,<unitdate> 1981, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Chants and songs, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Stationary, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Propaganda and educational work, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>South African women's day,<unitdate> 1985</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Study guides</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">5-6</container>
 <unittitle>Study guides<unitdate> 1981, 1982, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Member's notebook, Diane Jones, Bay area,<unitdate> 1982</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">8-9</container>
 <unittitle>Orientation seminar, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Substance abuse task force,<unitdate> 1985</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Zionism,<unitdate> 1983</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. POLITICAL PAPERS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Israeli invasion of Lebanon,<unitdate> 1982</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Reproductive rights,<unitdate> 1982</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>United front against war and racism, (UFAWR) <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Women's liberation and the worldwide struggle against imperialism, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>Brochures, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">17</container>
 <unittitle>Discussion papers,<unitdate> 1983-87</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">18</container>
 <unittitle>Flyers,<unitdate> 1987, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">19</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Our History</title>, <unitdate>n.d. </unitdate>[also located in history folder]</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">20</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Women's voices from Nairobi</title>,<unitdate> 1985</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES IV. AFFILIATED ORGANIZATIONS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Associación de mujeres de El Salvador (AMES),<unitdate> 1983, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Associación de mujeres Nicaraguenses (AMNLAE),<unitdate> 1980-88, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Jesse Jackson presidential campaign(JJC),<unitdate> 1984-88, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Rainbow coalition (JJC),<unitdate> 1985-87</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Line of March (LOM),<unitdate> 1984; 1989; n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Publications, LOM, <title render="italic">Frontline</title>,<unitdate> 1983-87</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">7-8</container>
 <unittitle>Women's commission, LOM,<unitdate> 1988-89 , n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Madre,<unitdate> 1984</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Women's Building of the Bay Area,<unitdate> 1984</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser5" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES V. SUBJECTS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Feminization of poverty,<unitdate> 1978, 1983, 1984, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Gay/Lesbian,<unitdate> 1981</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Middle East/Palestine,<unitdate> 1985, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Reproductive rights,<unitdate> 1985, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Socialist feminism,<unitdate> 1981</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>South African women,<unitdate> 1984, 1985, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Soviet women,<unitdate> 1985</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Zimbabwe women, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser6" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">12</container>
 <unittitle>MEP,<unitdate> 1984</unitdate>; IWD, 1986 [some photos in Somos Hermanas; Louisville chapter]</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser7" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES VII. OVERSIZE</unittitle>
 </did>
	<c02>
		<did>
			<unittitle>Posters
			</unittitle>
		</did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flate file</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Women to Women: Guatemalan Women Speak</title><unitdate>1983</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flate file</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Guerilla Madre </title></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flate file</container>
 <unittitle>CPF #2</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
