<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss437.xml//EN">mnsss437</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Isabel Holden Papers, 1972-2005</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Holden, Isabel, 1913-2007</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Isabel Holden papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1972-2005</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 585</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">4 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1.75 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Volunteer; Hospital volunteer; Animal welfare advocate.  Papers consist primarily of diaries which she began in 1971, the same year her husband retired, to "record what it was like to grow old and die in Northampton." There are some gaps in the diaries, which are quite detailed, introspective, and reflective of the people and goings on in Holden's life. Three spiralbound volumes of course notes, and a few miscellanous fragments, are also included.
 
                 </abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Isabel Anderson Holden was born in Montclair, New Jersey. She attended Bennington College in Vermont. In 1937, she married Richard S. Holden and they had a daughter, Constance Holden. The Holdens moved to Northampton, Massachusetts in 1948 where he was president of the Northampton National Bank. Richard Holden died in 1998.  Isabel Holden, also known to her friends as Matthew, was a horsewoman, animal lover, local historian, and was active in civic and intellectual life of Northampton.  She served as vice president and then president of the Northampton Historical Society (now Historic Northampton) from 1955 to 1981; published articles on local history; volunteered at the Veterans Administration Hospital and later for Hospice; and taught music for several years at the Smith College Campus School.  She was also involved with the SPCA; was a Friends of the Forbes Library, and a member of the Monday Afternoon club, which she joined in 1951.  In her later years Holden moderated seminars for Learning in Retirement on pastoral poetry, Scotland, and Shakespeare.  She also was also a major contributor to the Shakespeare Oxford Society (defending Edward de Vere, Earl of Oxford, as the true author of the works of Shakespeare).  The Holdens lived on Round Hill Road in Northampton and had a summer home in Salisbury, Vermont.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>The Isabel Holden Papers consist primarily of diaries which she began in 1971, the same year her husband retired, to "record what it was like to grow old and die in Northampton." There are some gaps in the diaries, which are quite detailed, introspective, and reflective of the people and goings on in Holden's life. Three spiralbound volumes of course notes, and a few miscellanous fragments, are also included.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                    <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Isabel Holden Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Isabel Holden in 2007.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger, 2007. </p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Aged women--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Northampton (Mass.)--History--Sources</geogname> 
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Salisbury (Vt.)--History--Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Diaries</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Holden, Isabel, 1913-2007</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Holden, Richard S.</persname> 
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
