<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss427.xml//EN">mnsss427</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Dolores Alexander Papers, 1945-1998</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Alexander, Dolores, 1931-</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Dolores Alexander papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1945-1998 </unitdate><unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1960s-70s</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 582</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">21 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(25.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Writer; Reporter; Lesbian activist. The Dolores Alexander Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and other documents pertaining to Alexander's work as a writer (freelance and as employed by Time, Inc.); files pertaining to Alexander's activism in NOW, Women Against Pornography, and to broader feminist and lesbian issues; files documenting the history of Mother Courage Restaurant in New York; books and audiovisual materials on the subject of achieving financial independence, and Alexander's personal financial information and records. A small amount of biographical information is also included.        </abstract>

</did>
 

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Dolores Alexander (b.1931) was raised in a working-class Italian community in Newark, NJ, and educated in Catholic schools. She received her B.A. in Language and Literature from the City College of New York in 1961. During her senior year of college she was chosen by The New York Times to work for 10 months as a paid "stringer" or "cub reporter" to gain experience in journalism. After graduation, she worked from 1961 to 1964 as a reporter, copy editor, and bureau chief for Newark Evening News. Alexander then moved to Newsday, where she worked as a reporter, copy editor, and assistant women's editor, and was feature writer for Newsday's weekend magazine from 1964 to 1969.  Alexander became active in NOW in 1966 after coming across a press release announcing the creation of a new women's rights organization. With her background in media, she chaired the Monitor Subcommittee of the National Task Force on Image of Women in Mass Media. In 1969, Alexander became the first executive director of the National Organization for Women (NOW). As executive director, she established a national office for NOW in New York City, expanded NOW's membership base nationally, and edited NOW Acts, NOW's national newsletter. Resigning in May 1970 in protest against NOW's homophobic policies and practices, Alexander continued to lecture on women's rights, and worked with the New Feminist Talent Collective, a speaker agency formed by Jacqui Michot Ceballos in response to the demand for speakers on the women's movement. In addition, she opened and ran Mother Courage, a feminist restaurant in Greenwich Village, with partner Jill Ward during the 1970s. She was one of the founders and organizers of Women Against Pornography and worked with New York Radical Feminists. Alexander was also a board member of the National Association for Repeal of Abortion Laws (NARAL); member of the advisory board of New York chapter of NOW; and member of New York Newspaper Women's Club.  She continued to be active in women's causes, including the North Fork Women for Women Fund, a nonprofit group that raised money for women facing health-care emergencies, and the Herstory Writer's Workshop, a community writing project for women interested in writing memoirs. She has been present at many significant events of the women's movement: integrating the Want Ads in the New York Times, the lesbian purge of NOW, the National Women's Conference in Houston in 1977, and the UN Fourth World Conference on Women in Beijing in 1995. Alexander remains active in the lesbian community on the North Fork of Long Island. </p>
</bioghist>


<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>The Dolores Alexander Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and other documents pertaining to Alexander's work as a writer (freelance and as employed by Time, Inc.); files pertaining to Alexander's activism in NOW, Women Against Pornography, and to broader feminist and lesbian issues; files documenting the history of Mother Courage Restaurant in New York; books and audiovisual materials on the subject of achieving financial independence, and Alexander's personal financial information and records. A small amount of biographical information is also included.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
        <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
   	<list type="simple">
              <item>The collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</item>
             <item>Partially restricted access - contact the Sophia Smith Collection for more information.</item>
               	<item>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.</item>
              	<item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
    </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The material in this collection may be protected by copyright. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights for permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Permission must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Dolores Alexander Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>


<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Dolores Alexander Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Dolores Alexander in 2003.</p>
</acqinfo>


<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger, 2007. </p> 
</processinfo>


<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminism--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Journalists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian activists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian feminism--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Pornography--Social aspects--United States--History</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Mother Courage Restaurant</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">National Organization for Women</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Women Against Pornography</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Alexander, Dolores</persname> 


</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material:  NOW Records, papers of NOW officers, and the Women Against Pornography Records are at the Schlesinger Library, Harvard University.  See also <extref href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/vof/vof-intro.html">Voices of Feminism Oral History Project</extref> and North Fork Women For Women Fund Records, Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>

</archdesc>
</ead>
