<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss456.xml//EN">mnsss456</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Linda Stein Papers, 1974-2008</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Stein, Linda</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Linda Stein Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1974-2008</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 495</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">3 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Visual artist; Feminist; Political activist; Founder and president, Have Art: Will Travel! Inc. (HAWT); Founder and president, the Art Club (Tribeca). The papers document the evolution of Stein's work both as an artist and as a political activist; her dialogue with other artists, peers and family; public events; her personal thoughts, and private life. The collection includes exhibition catalogs and announcements, press coverage, work documentation, lectures and presentations, writings, speeches, diaries and journals, correspondence, videos, and photographs.
 
                 </abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc2231.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>"Margaret Sanger 380" <lb />watercolor painting by Stein, n.d.</p></daodesc></dao> 
     <p>Linda Stein received her B.A. from Queens College and her M.F.A. from the Pratt Institute.  In 1974, she founded  Have Art: Will Travel! Inc. (HAWT), a non-profit corportation, to help artists, particularly women, to teach, exhibit, and sell their art.  In 1993, she founded the Art Club, a Tribeca gallery providing free exhibit space for non-profit organizations promoting feminism, diversity, and reproductive rights. Stein recently received the National Association of Women Artists award as their 2017 Artist Honoree for Commitment to the Arts.  And in October 2017 the New York City Art Teachers Association/UFT will honor Stein with their Artist of the Year award. </p>

<p>She has exhibited her work in solo and group shows and has been widely published, receives frequent commissions, and is represented in numerous private and museum collections.  Stein is also active in the art world as a panelist and moderator, has appeared on radio and television shows, and is a member of the Board of Directors of the Veteran Feminists of America.  In her own words: "It was as an artist in the 1970s that I became obsessed with the face.... An active feminist, I enjoy making portraits of internationally famous women..." (From "The Face: An Obsession").  Stein resides in New York City.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The Linda Stein Papers document the evolution of Stein's work both as an artist and as a political activist; her dialogue with other artists, peers and family; public events; her personal thoughts, and private life. The collection includes exhibition catalogs and announcements, press coverage, work documentation, lectures and presentations, writings, speeches, diaries and journals, correspondence, videos, and photographs.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                    <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Linda Stein Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Linda Stein in 2003.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger, 2008. </p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women artists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in art</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sculptors--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Stein, Linda--Exhibitions</persname> 
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
