<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss536.xml//EN">mnsss536</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Tonya Gonnella Frichner Papers, 1999-2012</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">January 27, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Frichner, Tonya Gonnella</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Tonya Gonnella Frichner papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1999-2012</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 703</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">9 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(8.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>,
<language langcode="spa">Spanish</language>

</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Lawyer; President and Founder, American Indian Law Alliance; Professor of Native
American History, Law and Human Rights. Primarily professional papers. Major topics include social conditions and legal status of
North American Indians, and related issues such as health care, environmental issues, land rights,
and international rights of indigenous peoples.
        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Tonya Gonnella Frichner was born in Syracuse, New York, the daughter of Maxine and Henry Gonnella.  A citizen of the Onondaga Nation (Snipe Clan), she has devoted her personal and professional life to ensuring human rights for Indigenous Peoples, both within North America and around the world.   Frichner graduated from St. John's Catholic Academy, a high school in Syracuse. She earned a Bachelor of Science Degree, magna cum laude, from St. John's University in New York City in 1980 and her Juris Doctor from the City University of New York School of Law in 1987. Shortly after graduating from law school, Frichner served as a delegate for and was of legal counsel to the Haudenosaunee  (Iroquois) Confederacy at the UN Sub-Commission on the Human Rights/Working Group on Indigenous Populations in Geneva, Switzerland.  Also since 1987, she has sat on the Board of Directors and serves as legal counsel to the Iroquois Nationals Lacrosse Project, the national team of the Haudenosaunee Confederacy.  She sits on several other boards, including the Seventh Generation Fund for Indian Development and the Boarding School Healing Project.</p>

<p>In 1989 Frichner founded, and has served as President since then, of the American Indian Law Alliance, an Indigenous Peoples advocacy group based in New York City.  The Alliance is a NGO with Consultative Status to the United Nations Social and Economic Council and Frichner has also served a three-year term (2008-2010) as the North American Representative to the United Nations Permanent Forum on Indigenous Issues.  Simultaneously, she has taught Federal Indian Law, Human Rights Law and Native American History at several New York City-area colleges and universities, including City College, the City University of New York (1991-1999); Hunter College (1993); New York University (1994); and Manhattanville College (2000-2008).  Tonya Gonnella Frichner resides in New Jersey with her husband, Herb Frichner, a businessman and Adjunct Associate Professor at the Fashion Institute of Technology. She has received numerous awards in recognition of her work, including the Harriet Tubman Humanitarian Achievement Award, the Female Role Model of the Year from the Ms. Foundation for Women, the Thunderbird Indian of the Year Award,the Ellis Island Medal of Honor, and the NY County Lawyers Association Award for Outstanding Public Service. She also received an honorary degree from Colby College in 2012. She died February 14, 2015.</p>

</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>Primarily professional papers including final reports, proposals, and a variety of pamphlets
and informational booklets.  Major topics include social conditions and legal status of North
American Indians, and related issues such as health care, environmental issues, land rights, and
international rights of indigenous peoples.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of
research copies.</item>
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works in this
collection created by Tonya Frichner. Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by
those individuals or their assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or
quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify all copyright
holders.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Tonya Gonnella Frichner Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton,
Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Tonya Frichner beginning in
2012.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
           <p>Accessioned by  Kathleen Banks Nutter and Jesse Kline, 2013 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Indian women -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Indians of North America -- Legal Status, laws, etc. -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Indians of North America -- New York (State) -- Social life and customs</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Indians of North America -- Women -- Health and hygiene -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Indigenous peoples -- Civil rights</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Indigenous women -- Social conditions -- Congresses</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Human rights</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women lawyers -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Iroquois Indians -- Social life and customs</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Onondaga Indians -- Government relations</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">United Nations -- Representatives</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Permanent Forum on Indigenous Issues (United Nations)</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Frichner, Tonya Gonnella</persname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">American Indian Law Alliance</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">UN Declaration on the Rights of Indigenous Peoples</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Seventh Generation Fund</corpname> 

</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
