<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss365.xml//EN">mnsss365</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a"> Green Street Lesbian Rooming House Records</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Wendy Essery.</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2013">2013</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Ashlynn August. 
		<date normal="2013-09-24">2013-09-24</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	  </langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Green Street Lesbian Rooming House (Northampton, MA)</corpname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:"> Green Street Lesbian Rooming House Records</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1977-1999</unitdate>
	<unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1977-1986</unitdate>
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 554</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">5 boxes</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(2.5 linear ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		Women's rooming house. The collection consists of house logbooks including announcements, phone messages, minutes of occasional house meetings, and personal messages between residents.  The entries are revealing of the women's personal lives, daily life in the rooming house, and the Northampton lesbian community. 
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	<head>Historical Note</head>
	<p>The Green Street Rooming House was a lesbian cooperative started in the Elmhurst apartment house at 66 Green St in Northampton, Massachusetts. It operated from circa 1975 to 1992. From the 1960's on, Northampton had become a haven for lesbian and feminist activity. Some residents of the boarding house were students at the five colleges, and others were lesbians coming out of the closet seeking freedom to express their sexuality. The rooming house was established as a lesbian-only residence with a designated live-in manager who functioned as a liaison between the residents and the landlord. The house operated in a cooperative spirit by rotating cleaning chores and sharing in the preparation of meals. A notebook was always kept in the central hallway for residents to write messages to each other.  </p>

<p>The owner and landlord, Michael Cohen and his assistant manager John Knowles, provided basic house supplies, such as toilet paper, soap, light bulbs and cleaning products and also authorized maintenance for heat, electric and plumbing. Initially, the landlord was not told that the current lesbian tenants were starting a lesbian-only household. Eventually, he found out and thought it amusing that a group of women wanted to maintain a cooperative community in a rooming house. In 1992 the building was sold to Housing and Economic Resources for Women and it eventually became a co-ed rooming house. In 2007 it was bought by Smith College and was torn down in 2013.</p>

<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="center" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc7369greenst.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>66 Green Street, 2013</p></daodesc>
	</dao>
    </bioghist>

    <scopecontent id="scope">
	<head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
	<p>This collection contains forty-six spiral bound notebooks that were used for communication between the residents, not only to record house meetings but also as a resource for finding new tenants. These house logbooks include announcements, phone messages, artwork, minutes of occasional house meetings, and personal messages between residents.  The entries reveal aspects of the women's personal lives, daily life in the rooming house, and the Northampton lesbian community.</p>

<p>Various local women's events and organizations are mentioned repeatedly, such as The Common Womon Club; Lesbian Gardens; contra dances and women's dances at The Hanger and dances in Hartford, Connecticut; Rhythm Queens Softball Team; Eve's garden; Valley Women's Martial Arts School; Queer Disco; WomonFyre bookstore; Lesbian Connection magazine; Izquierda - Shabatu; Valley Women's Voice; Women in Construction program; and a Chris Williams concert at Smith College.  Some national events, such as the Michigan Womyn's Music Festival, are mentioned as well.</p>

<p>In January 1983 there is discussion of the murder of a resident by another resident outside of Northampton. The accused was incarcerated at Bridgewater State Mental Hospital for fifteen years, at which time she went to trial and confessed. The residents living in the house at the time of the murder were visited by the FBI, newspaper and TV stations, all looking for details to publish and sensationalize the story.</p>

<p>Over the years residents were active in feminist and lesbian causes, including the "Virginia to Vermont Bike-a-thon," a fund for the Lesbians Mother's Defense Fund whose riders stopped in Northampton at the invitation of the residents. Another cause supported the Women's Pentagon Action in October 1980 that resulted in thirty-six women being sent to jail for thirty days. When a Green Street restaurant laid-off three "dykes" in one day, the establishment was picketed. Another boycott involved a window display at "Strut," a shoe store downtown.</p>

<p>Violence against women is a recurring theme in the notebooks. Incidents discussed include a "Peeping Tom," attacks on women in the Green Street area and a "creepy guy" downtown who made lewd gestures to women.  A late 1979 logbook mentioned how Springfield experienced thirteen rapes in five weeks.</p>

<p>Resident lesbians worked in non-traditional jobs and had a variety of skills and were adept at such things as car repair, carpentry, painting, and riding motorcycles. They engaged in friendly banter, shared meals and watched out for each other. Communication of common daily issues that emerge in cooperative living, such as late rents, food theft, leaky plumbing, neglect of housekeeping chores, phone bills, and disregard for house rules are peppered throughout the logbooks. There is also a folder of newspaper articles that provide further insight into the murder in 1983.</p>

<p>The donor of the collection provided written summaries for some logs found in box one and two with named residents and topics. The collection also includes excerpts of the mission statement and long term goals and objectives of The Valley Women's History Collaborative (VWHC), a group that formed in 1998. </p> 
    </scopecontent>

<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, with the following exception:  Researchers must sign an Access Agreement Form before using this collection, agreeing to protect the confidentiality of living persons.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to writings by the donor of the collection only. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  Copyright to writings authored by others is owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns.  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.  </p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Green Street Lesbian Rooming House Records", Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass."</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>The Green Street Lesbian Rooming House Records were donated by Paige Bridgens in 2006.  </p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Wendy Essery (Fraenkel Intern), 2012</p> 
    </processinfo>

<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
		<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Communal living -- Massachusetts -- Northampton</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Female friendship -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminism -- Massachusetts -- Pioneer Valley -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Gay rights -- Massachusetts -- History</subject>
		<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Green Street Lesbian Rooming House (Northampton, MA)</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Housing, Cooperative -- Massachusetts -- Northampton -- History -- Sources</subject> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian communities -- Massachusetts -- Northampton -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians -- Massachusetts -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians -- Violence against women -- Massachusetts</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians -- Political activity -- Massachusetts</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians -- United States -- Social life and customs</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Northampton (Mass.) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</geogname>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in sports -- Massachusetts -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject> </controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->
    <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
	<p>Related materials, including oral histories of some residents, can be found in the <extref href="http://www.library.umass.edu/spcoll/umarmot/?p=571">Valley Women's History Collaborative Records</extref> in the UMASS-Amherst Special Collections.</p>
	<p>For more on the history of the building and its tenants, see the Smith College Archives 
	<extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/smitharchives/manosca104_main.html">Buildings Records</extref>.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>


<!-- End additional information -->


<!-- Enter Series descriptions -->

<!-- End Series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->
<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I SERIES</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Valley Women's History Collaborative: printed materials,<unitdate> 1998-1999, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>General: clippings, <unitdate>Jan 1983</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>House logbooks</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2-9</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>Feb 1977 - Mar 1980</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">1-13</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>Mar 1980 - Aug 1981</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">1-9</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>10 Aug 1981-19 Nov 1982</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">1-7</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>Nov 1982 - Sept 1984</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">1-8</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>Mar 1985 - Aug 1992</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
