<ead>
 <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924" audience="internal" id="head" relatedencoding="MARC21">
		<eadid publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss590.xml//EN" countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss">mnsss590</eadid>
		<filedesc>
			<titlestmt>
				<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Women of Rock Oral History Project oral histories</titleproper>
				<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Maureen Callahan and Jasmine Jones.</author>
				<sponsor>The project was made possible with the support of a Helen Gurley Brown Magic Grant.</sponsor>
			</titlestmt>
			<publicationstmt>
				<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
				<address>
					<addressline>Northampton, Massachusetts</addressline>
				</address>
				<date encodinganalog="260$c">2017</date>
				<p>Copyright to this finding aid has been given to the public domain via the use of a Creative Commons CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication.</p>
			</publicationstmt>
		</filedesc>
		<profiledesc>
			<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded by Maureen Callahan and Jasmine Jones <date>2017-03-29</date>
			</creation>
			<langusage>Finding aid written in <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
			</langusage>
		</profiledesc>
	</eadheader>

	<frontmatter id="front">
		<titlepage>
			<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
			<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Women of Rock Oral History Project oral histories finding aid</titleproper>
			<num/>
			<author encodinganalog="245$c">Maureen Callahan and Jasmine Jones</author>
			<date encodinganalog="260$c">2017</date>
		</titlepage>
	</frontmatter>

	<archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
		<did id="main">
			<head>Collection Overview</head>
			<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Women of Rock Oral History Project oral histories</unittitle>
			<unitdate label="Dates:" normal="2014/2015">2014-2015</unitdate>
			<unitid label="Collection Number:" encodinganalog="099" countrycode="US">MS 756</unitid>

			<physdesc label="Quantity:">
				<extent encodinganalog="300$a">16 items</extent>
			</physdesc>
			<langmaterial label="Language of Material:" encodinganalog="546"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
			</langmaterial>

			<repository label="Location:">
				<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</corpname>
				<address>
					<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
				</address>
			</repository>
			<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">The Women of Rock Oral History Project documents the lives and careers of women in rock who have been underrepresented or omitted from rock journalism and historical scholarship. The project, created and managed by Tanya Pearson, seeks to facilitate a more comprehensive cultural history, by women, for women and gender non-conforming individuals who have historically been silenced or overlooked as a result of their gender.</abstract>
		</did>
		<bioghist id="bioghist">
			<head>Project History</head>
			<p>The Women of Rock Oral History Project began as an independent study project by Tanya Pearson while she was at Smith College. During that time, and since graduating, Pearson has collected the stories of musicians who rose to prominence before the advent of modern web-based tools for documenting their lives and work. This project is ongoing.</p>
		</bioghist>
		<scopecontent id="scope">
			<head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
			<p>This collection includes oral histories of women and gender non-conforming rock musicians prominent from the late twentieth century to the present. Interview narrators were chosen by Tanya Pearson. Interviews are available as videorecordings; transcripts will be available after 2025.</p>
		</scopecontent>

		<descgrp id="admin">
			<head>Information on Use</head>
			<descgrp>
				<head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
				<accessrestrict id="admin-access">
					<p>Most videorecordings of interviews of this collection are open for research use and accessible on the web. Some oral histories are only accessible at Smith College Special Collections. Transcripts to most oral histories will be available in 2025.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict id="admin-use">
					<p>Copyright to most oral histories is held by Tanya Pearson until 2025. After 2025, copyright will pass to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</descgrp>
			<accruals id="admin-accruals">
				<head>Additions to the Collection</head>
				<p>Periodic additions to collection are expected.</p>
			</accruals>

		</descgrp>

		<controlaccess id="subj">
			<head>Search Terms</head>
			<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011170779">Bag, Alice</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2009018284">Ballance, Laura</persname>
			<persname source="local" encodinganalog="600">Barber-Way, Mish</persname>
			<persname source="local" encodinganalog="600">Cafritz, Julie</persname>
			<persname source="local" encodinganalog="600">de Buhr, Alice</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no98016009">Dorsey, Gail Ann</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2016077201">Gonzales, Michelle Cruz</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no00092784">Gordon, Nina, 1967-</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n92021038">Hersh, Kristin</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n82098226" encodinganalog="600">Lunch, Lydia</persname>
			<persname source="local" encodinganalog="600">Pearson, Tanya</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2008041472">Post, Louise</persname>
			<persname source="local" encodinganalog="600">Roessler, Kira</persname>
			<persname source="local" encodinganalog="600">Ross, Cynthia</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2011143738" encodinganalog="600">Samson, JD, 1978-</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2012109306" encodinganalog="600">Schemel, Patty, 1967-</persname>
			<persname source="local" encodinganalog="600">Sparks, Donita</persname>
			<persname source="local" encodinganalog="600">Sumner, Kate</persname>
			<persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/no2005057503">Timony, Mary</persname>
			<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh92002582">Women rock musicians</subject>
			<subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85147655">Women musicians</subject>
			<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="lcsh" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/subjects/sh85095238">Oral history</genreform>
		</controlaccess>

		<dsc type="in-depth" id="list-contlist">
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Alice Bag</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2015-07-08">2015 July 8</unitdate>
					<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210522506/8330ba2d53" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Alice Bag">
	</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Alice Bag discusses her upbringing in East L.A., her relationship with her parents and how those early experiences dictated her personality and musical output. She details the burgeoning punk scene in Los Angeles in the 1970s, the formation of The Bags, subsequent success within the scene and appearance in the cult documentary Decline of Western Civilization. She also discusses an influential trip to Nicaragua, her career in teaching, feelings about women's place in rock music, specifically women of color and their place within the historical rock narrative.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Singer, musician, author, educator and feminist Alice Bag co-founded pioneering LA punk band, The Bags, one of the first wave of punk bands to form in the mid-1970s. She has remained active in music, performing in bands Castration Squad, Stay at Home Bomb, Cholita!, and has published two memoirs. Bag recorded her first full length album, Alice Bag, on Don Giovanni records in 2016.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Kate Sumner interview with Laura Ballance</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2015-04-24">2015 April 24</unitdate>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history Ballance discusses her childhood, the development of her interest in music, and the creation and history of Superchunk and Merge. Ballance describes her family's supernatural interests and the impact of a traumatic home invasion in Little Rock, Arkansas, in which her mother was raped when Ballance was eight years old. She reflects on the impact of gender and motherhood on her career as a musician and business owner. The interview also covers how living in the South affected the development of her musical career, and the challenge of being a musician with hyperacusis. The interview concludes with Ballance reflecting on her proudest moments.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Laura Ballance (b. 1968) is a musician and business owner in Durham, North Carolina. She is the bassist in the rock band Superchunk and co-founder, along with Mac McCaughan, of Merge Records. Superchunk began in 1989, and Merge grew up alongside it as a method to release small-scale recordings by Superchunk and other independent/local acts. In 1992, Merge released their first full-length album, Tossing Seeds by Superchunk, and in 2010, released Arcade Fire's The Suburbs, which won the Grammy for Album of the Year in 2011. By 2012, the label had over 450 releases and had established itself as an indie-rock institution. In the summer of 2013, Ballance announced that she would no longer be touring with Superchunk as a result of her worsening hearing issues. She continues to record with the band and runs Merge.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Mish Barber-Way</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2016-10-10">2016 October 10</unitdate>
					<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/211582343/4bcad70c65" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Mish Barber-Way">
					</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Mish Barber-Way discusses her upbringing in Vancouver, her relationship with her parents, siblings and friends, her experiences as a high school and college student and her involvement in the local music scene. She details the formation of White Lung, her relationship with her bandmates, the band's trajectory to success and her eventual move to the United States. Barber-Way also discusses her musical influences, feminism, sexism, and her experience as a working musician, journalist and writer.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Mish Barber-Way is a singer, musician, writer and fronts the Candian punk band, White Lung. She is the sex and relationship columnist in the Vancouver newspaper, <emph altrender="italic">Westender</emph>, and is a writer and reporter for <emph altrender="italic">Broadly</emph> and <emph altrender="italic">Vice</emph>. She currently lives in the suburbs of Los Angeles with her husband.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Julie Cafritz</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2015-01-22">2015 January 22</unitdate>
<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210631435/96a357e15c" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Julie Cafritz">
	</dao>
				</did>
<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Julie Cafritz details her childhood, relationships with family members, and her upbringing in Washington, D.C. She describes her college career at Brown University, a traumatic event that occurred while she was a student, and the pivotal moment in which she decided to join a band without ever having played a musical instrument. Cafritz recounts notable relationships with bandmates in Pussy Galore, Free Kitten and STP, and candidly discusses musicianship, gender and personal relationships. The interview concludes with Cafritz reflecting on motherhood and work&#47;life balance.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Julie Cafritz is a guitarist&#47;vocalist who started her career in the seminal garage noise band, Pussy Galore in NYC in the mid-1980s. She went on to form STP and later, Free Kitten, with Kim Gordon of Sonic Youth in the 1990s.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Alice de Buhr</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2016-10-06">2016 October 6</unitdate>
					<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210677455/7d7fa908bc" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Alice de Buhr">
					</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Alice de Buhr details growing up a tomboy in Mason City, Iowa, her relationship with her parents, siblings and friends, and her introduction to the drums in second grade. She details her parents divorce, her experience coming out as gay in 1967, subsequent hospitalization, and move to California. De Buhr details her early music career, the formation and eventual success of Fanny, and the events that led to the bands dissolution. She talks openly about her post-Fanny life and career and her feelings about the bands legacy and her place in rock history.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Alice de Buhr was a founding member and the drummer of Fanny, the first all-woman rock band to release an album on a major label in the U.S. After leaving Fanny in 1973, she spent the next 11 years in the music business; first at an independent distributor of Motown, Mercury and A &amp; M Records. In 1984 she left her position as Local Marketing Coordinator – Southern California A &amp; M Records to pursue interests in the video industry. She currently represents MTI Home Video as a national key accounts representative and owns a small DVD/video distribution company. She resides in Tucson, AZ.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>A redacted version of this oral history is available for research without restriction. The full version will be available in 2032.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Alice de Buhr until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Gail Ann Dorsey</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2016-07-20">2016 July 20</unitdate>
					<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210625793/e7cfe2364e" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Gail Ann Dorsey">
	</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Gail Ann Dorsey discusses growing up in Philadelphia, her relationship with her mother and siblings, and her early interest in music and screenwriting. She talks about discovering the bass guitar, auditioning for her first band, her college career as a film major and her eventual move to London and New York to pursue music. She details her experience as an African American woman, bassist and and an artist working within multiple genres. Dorsey talks openly about her relationship with David Bowie, as a member of his band for twenty years, her career as a top session player and solo artist, and her experience with record labels. The interview concludes with her thoughts on the importance of the documentation of women in music and her greatest personal achievement.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Gail Ann Dorsey is a musician, vocalist, bassist and top session musician, best known for her work with David Bowie, She has recorded three solo albums, and has supported Olivia Newton John, Tears for Fears, Lenny Kravitz, Boy George, Indigo Girls, Gang of Four and Gwen Stefani, among others. Dorsey continues to perform and tour.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Gail Ann Dorsey until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Michelle Gonzales</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2016-08-20">2016 August 20</unitdate>
					<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210642383/78dbb5d360" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Michelle Gonzales">
					</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Michelle Gonzales discusses her upbringing in Tuolumne, CA., with her mother and brother. She discusses early childhood events, experiences in school and with peers and her introduction to music, via the flute. Gonzales recounts her introduction to punk and the formation of her first band Girl Fight, and later Spitboy. She details the punk scene, her place within it as a young xicana woman, and as a drummer, in a working, touring, hardcore band. Gonzales also talks candidly about Spitboy's breakup, her personal relationships, sexuality, marriage, motherhood the about writing her memoir.</p>
					<p>There are two corrections that the narrator has made to her interview. At 39:31, when she says, "marched up and down Haight Street," it should be Telegraph Avenue. "Paula and Karen" at 45:14 should be Adrienne and Karen.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Michelle Gonzales is a musician, author and teacher. She played drums and wrote lyrics for three bands during the 1980s and 1990s: Bitch Fight, Spitboy, and Instant Girl. In 2001 and 2003, she earned degrees in English/creative writing from Mills College, where she also minored in ethnic studies. Michelle has published in anthologies, literary journals, and <emph altrender="italic">Hip Mama</emph> magazine. She teaches English and creative writing at Las Positas College, and lectures at colleges and art spaces around the country. She released her memoir, <emph altrender="italic">Spitboy Rule: Tales of a Xicana in a Female Punk Band</emph> in 2016.  She lives with her husband, son, and their three Mexican dogs in Oakland, California. </p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Nina Gordon and Louise Post</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2015-01-12">2015 January 12</unitdate>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history Nina Gordon and Louise Post discuss their early lives and the fortuitous meeting that led to the formation of Veruca Salt. The interview focuses on their personal experiences within the band, as successful female musicians in the mid to late 1990s, the difficulties that led to their 17-year estrangement, and the events that led to their subsequent reunion.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Nina Gordon (b. 1967) and Louise Post (b. 1966) are vocalists and guitarists of the rock band, Veruca Salt. Co-founded in 1993, the band reached critical and commercial success in 1994 with the release of their first album American Thighs. The band signed to Geffen Records and gained popularity when the single "Seether" became a hit. After releasing the EP Blow it Out Your Ass, It's Veruca Salt (1996) and a second full-length album, Eight Arms to Hold You (1997), Gordon left the band and embarked on a brief solo career and Post recorded two more albums and an EP under the Veruca Salt moniker. In 2014, the original lineup reunited and toured the United States and Australia. Their first album in 17 years, Ghost Notes, was released in July 2015. </p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>A redacted version of this oral history is available for research without restriction. The full version will be available in 2040.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Louise Post until 2040; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Kristin Hersh</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2014-12-14">2014 December 14</unitdate>
<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210954933/58e9a11c36" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Kristin Hersh">
	</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history Kristin Hersh describes her childhood in Rhode Island and how her musical inclination was dictated by her long undiagnosed synesthesia. She a traumatic bicycle accident and its effect on her personal life and songwriting. The interview details her work, musical output and role as wife, mother, and rock icon.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Kristin Hersh (b. 1966) was born in Atlanta and raised in Newport, Rhode Island. She learned guitar from her father and quickly developed her own unique style of playing. She formed Throwing Muses with her stepsister, Tanya Donnelly, and some high school friends in 1981, playing shows with bands like Talking Heads and eventually touring with the Pixies. Hersh continued performing as Throwing Muses until 1997 when she went on to continue her successful solo career. She formed power-rock trio 50 Foot Wave in 2003 and founded CASH Music [Coalition of Artists and Stakeholders], a collection of tools for artists and labels to sell, share, and promote music directly to their fans. In 2010 she released her memoir, Rat Girl, detailing her teenage years in Newport, Rhode Island. Throwing Muses re-formed in 2003 and the original lineup toured the U.S. in 2014.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Lydia Lunch</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2014-12-06">2014 December 6</unitdate>
<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210506005/c027840f9a" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Lydia Lunch">
	</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Lydia Lunch details her teenage years in Rochester, New York and her move to New York City as a 14 year-old runaway with aspirations of becoming a spoken word artist. She recounts her early experiences and relationships in New York in the mid 1970s and details her notable musical and artistic projects and significant collaborations. She discusses her motivations, reputation and sexuality as well as her immense output of physical work and her plans for the future.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Lydia Lunch (b. 1959) moved to New York City from Rochester in her early teens, intent on performing spoken word. She spawned the No Wave movement with her band Teenage Jesus and the Jerks who appeared on the Brian Eno produced No New York compilation and performed in Eight Eyed Spy and Beirut Slump before embarking on a solo career. Lunch has collaborated and performed with countless writers, musicians and artists, most notably: J.G. Thirlwell, Thurston Moore and Sonic Youth, Nick Cave and The Birthday Party, No Trend, Rowland S. Howard, Richard Kern, Exene Cervenka, Henry Rollins, Donita Sparks, Jerry Stahl, Hubert Selby and William S. Burroughs. She was a key player in the Cinema of Transgression movement, acting in a series of short films directed by Richard Kern. She is a critically acclaimed author and tireless spoken word performer, continuing to define underground music, art and literature with her distinct confrontationalist approach.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Kira Roessler</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2016-10-07">2016 October 7</unitdate>
					<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210819787/edae1edf27" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Kira Roessler">
					</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history Kira Roessler discusses her childhood, her relationship with her parents and brother, the development of her interest in music, and her involvement in the early punk scene in Los Angeles. Roessler discusses her experiences joining and forming bands and how she came to join Black Flag at the height of their career. She details her time with the band while a college student at UCLA, and her eventual firing. She also discusses her thirty year collaboration with Minutemen founder, Mike Watt.  The interview also covers Roessler's current career as a dialogue editor.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Kira Roessler (b. 1962) is a musician, bassist, singer, and Emmy award winning dialogue editor. She was the bass player for  Black Flag from 1983-1985 and co-founded the two-bass duo, Dos, with Mike Watt from Minutemen. She currently resides in Los Angeles, CA and works as a dialogue editor on theatrical films.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>
						Tanya Pearson interview with Cynthia Ross</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2016-12-27">2016 December 27</unitdate>
					<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/214443478/a49fc6ecb8" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Cynthia Ross">
					</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Cynthia Ross details her childhood and adolescence, growing up in Toronto. She discusses her artistic nature, relationship with her sisters and parents, particularly her mother. Ross talks about the music scene in Toronto, the formation of the B-Girls and eventual move to New York City. She discusses personal and professional relationships with punk icons, and how the B-Girls helped shape the New York scene with their unique sound. Ross details the B-Girls break up, motherhood, marriage, education, her careers, and passion for human rights and social justice.The interview concludes with her thoughts on aging, the history of women in rock and her return to New York to pursue music once again.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Cynthia Ross is a bass player and founding member of the hugely influential punk band The B-Girls. She has shared the stage with Blondie, the B-52's, the Dead Boys and the Clash, among others. Ross has pursued several careers, always with a focus on social justice and human rights. She is a mother, a writer, an artist and currently plays bass in New York Junk. </p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Cynthia Ross until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>
					Tanya Pearson interview with JD Samson</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2015-01-06">2015 January 6</unitdate>
<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/210830006/a493b72ff9" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with JD Samson">
	</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history JD Samson describes her upbringing and experiences as a gay teenager and activist in small town Ohio and the pivotal moment that fostered her interest in film and visual arts. She discusses her time in New York City at Sarah Lawrence College, her involvement in the local music scene and joining her first band, Le Tigre, with Riot Grrrl figurehead, Kathleen Hanna. Samson details her experience within the music business as a female identified "gender-outlaw" and how this experience diverges from the "women of rock" category. </p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>JD Samson (b. 1978) grew up in Pepper Pike Ohio where she came out as a lesbian at age 15. A visual artist, she went on to attend Sarah Lawrence College where she majored in experimental film and graduated in 2000. Samson joined electro-feminist band, Le Tigre with Kathleen Hanna and Johanna Fateman as projectionist, producer and then full-fledged band member. Samson founded DJ project MEN after Le Tigre disbanded and toured with Peaches and Gossip. She has a songwriting and publishing deal through Universal Music Publishing Group and has written songs for Christina Aguilera and Pussy Riot.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>
						Tanya Pearson interview with Patty Schemel</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2016-08-17">2016 August 17</unitdate>
					<dao linktype="simple" actuate="onrequest" show="new" href="https://vimeo.com/211089595/4552352456" title="Link to Tanya Pearson interview with Patty Schemel">
					</dao>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Patty Schemel discusses her upbringing in Marysville, WA., her relationship with her parents and siblings, her early musical influences and interest in the drums. She details her experience in school, with her peers, and how she came out to her mother. Schemel offers insight into the Seattle music scene and discusses her single minded approach to turning drums into a career. She discusses her move to CA, where she joined Hole, and her trajectory to rock stardom, descent into drug addiction, and how she eventually overcame those obstacles. Schemel also talks at length about women's place in rock history, her involvement in Girls Rock camps, relationships with friends and colleagues, becoming a parent, and coming to terms with her her identity as a gay woman and recovering addict.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Patty Schemel is a musician, drummer, who rose to prominence as a member of the rock band Hole. Schemel continues to play music in the band Upset, volunteers at Girls Rock Camp and gives drum lessons, in addition to owning a dog daycare/boarding business. She lives in Los Angeles with her wife and daughter.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is available for research without restriction.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Patty Schemel until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Donita Sparks</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2015-07-21">2015 July 21</unitdate>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Donita Sparks discusses her upbringing in Chicago, including hobbies, interests, family and her introduction to rock music. She speaks candidly about her move to Los Angeles after high school, the music scene there and the space she occupied within it. Sparks details the formation of L7, the bands success, subsequent dissolution and current reunion. She addresses her feminism, women's contributions to rock music and her opinion regarding the Women of Rock category.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Donita Sparks is guitarist, vocalist and founding member of the seminal hard rock band, L7.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>This interview is currently not available for research.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
			<c01>
				<did>
					<unittitle>Tanya Pearson interview with Mary Timony</unittitle>
					<unitdate normal="2014-12-28">2014 December 28</unitdate>
				</did>
				<scopecontent>
					<p>In this oral history, Mary Timony discusses her childhood in Washington, D.C. and her interest in music from a young age. She details her high school and college experience, including the music scene in Washington, D.C. in the early 1990s and how her participation in the musical community helped to curb her social anxiety. Timony recalls her college career, the formation of her band, Helium, and what led to their disbandment. She discusses her musical output, collaborations, relationships and some of the double standards that women rock musicians face.</p>
				</scopecontent>
				<bioghist>
					<p>Mary Timony (b. 1970) is a multi-instrumentalist who founded the band Autoclave in Washington D.C. and gained greater recognition as singer and guitarist in the Boston, Massachusetts band, Helium in the mid 1990s. Timony has released two solo albums and collaborated with a number of musicians on outside projects throughout her career. In 2011, she formed Wild Flag with members of Sleater Kinney and released an album before forming the critically acclaimed Ex Hex in 2014. When she's not touring, Timony teaches guitar lessons in Washington, D.C.</p>
				</bioghist>
				<accessrestrict>
					<p>A redacted version of this oral history is available at the Smith College Special Collections reading room. The full version will be available in 2055.</p>
				</accessrestrict>
				<userestrict>
					<p>Copyright to this oral history is owned by Tanya Pearson until 2025; after that time, copyright will transfer to Smith College.</p>
				</userestrict>
			</c01>
		</dsc>
	</archdesc>
</ead>
