<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss439.xml//EN">mnsss439</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women  (U.S. branch) Records, 1967-2001 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women</corpname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women  (U.S. branch) Records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1967-2001 (ongoing)</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 529</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            International athletic association. The International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women Records at Smith represent the U.S. branch of the organization.  The collection includes histories, including information about Dorothy Ainsworth; documents pertaining to various IAPESGW congresses and conventions; and IAPESGW bulletins, newsletters, and reports.
 
                 </abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Historical Note</head>
     <p>The International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women was founded to provide "an international forum and vehicle for women physical educators to meet together and share ideas, methods, programs, problems, and solutions."  Dorothy Ainsworth served as the first president. The first international Congress was held in 1949 in Copenhagen with two hundred fifty delegates attending from twenty-five nations, and since then quadrennial congresses have been held at various locations around the world.  Ainsworth established the United States branch in 1961 and appointed Catherine Allen as its representative; she served until 1969.  The organization informs its membership by means of a semi-annual newsletter and an annual Journal. From its inception and as recently as 1998, IAPESGW served as an affiliate of the National Council of Women, a satellite organization of the International Council of Women.  By virtue of its NCW/ICW affiliation, IAPESGW was recognized as an NGO by the United Nations.  IAPESGW is a member of the International Women's Group and the International Council of Sport and Physical Education.  The organization is ongoing, and as of 2005 membership included forty-five countries across all five continents.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women Records at Smith represent the U.S. branch of the organization.  The collection includes histories, including information about Dorothy Ainsworth; documents pertaining to various IAPESGW congresses and conventions; and IAPESGW bulletins, newsletters, and reports.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                    <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The material in this collection may be protected by copyright. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights for permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Permission must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women  (U.S. branch) Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The International Association of Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women Records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Barbara Kelly in 2005.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger, 2005. </p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Physical education for women--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sex discrimination in sports--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sports for women--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Health and hygiene--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women athletes--History--Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Ainsworth, Dorothy Sears, 1894-</persname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">International Association for Physical Education and Sport for Girls and Women--History--Sources</corpname> 
</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material located in the Dorothy Ainsworth Papers in the Smith College Archives.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>

</archdesc>
</ead>
