<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss372.html">mnsss372</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">New Jersey Project Records, 1969-2006</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       </titlestmt>
       <publicationstmt>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
         <address>
           <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
         </address>
         <date calendar="gregorian" era="ce">© 2006</date>
         <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by
 Margaret Jessup.
         <date>2006-12-01</date>
     </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter id="front">
    <titlepage>
      <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb />Smith College<lb /></publisher>
   <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">New Jersey Project Records, 1969-2006</titleproper>
   <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
   <num>MS 548</num>
   <date encodinganalog="260$c">2006</date>
   

       <p>© 2006 Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
   </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
 <did id="main">
 	<head>Collection Overview</head>
 <origination label="Creator:">
     <corpname  encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">New Jersey Project</corpname >
 </origination>
   <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">New Jersey Project records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1969-2006</unitdate>
 <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 548</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">57 boxes</extent>
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(71.25 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
    <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>


  </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
 <!-- MRJ: EDIT ABSTRACT  -->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Feminist advocacy and educational program. Collection is a rich source of information about issues of race, class, and gender in higher education, in New Jersey specifically, and the efforts of that State to address them among its college and university students and
faculty. Types of materials include administrative files, publications, correspondence and
emails, reports, writings, books, photographs, conference packets, audiocassettes, DVDs,
videocassettes, grant applications, financial information, articles, and photographs.
NOTE: There is no container list online for this finding aid.  You may contact the Sophia
Smith Collection if you want one sent to you.
    </abstract>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
    
       <p>The New Jersey Project on Inclusive Scholarship, Curriculum and Teaching was established by the State of New Jersey as the first statewide, state-funded gender and multi- cultural scholarship and curriculum project in the U.S.  Its diverse activities, which dealt with virtually all aspects of the learning experience, promoted and supported curriculum transformation and faculty/student development regarding issues of gender, race, ethnicity, class, culture, and sexuality. </p>

	<p>The Project published a journal, Transformations; sponsored ALANA, a support network for women of color in higher education in New Jersey; conducted conferences, workshops, and regional network meetings; held annual residential Summer Institutes for New Jersey college faculty; sponsored art exhibitions, poetry readings, and other special events; and made awards to students who demonstrated excellence in feminist scholarship during their undergraduate studies. </p>

	<p>In 1994, The New Jersey Project was awarded the national Progress in Equity Award from the American Association of University Women's Legal Advocacy Fund, and in 2001, the National Association for Multicultural Education honored the Project with its Multicultural Program Award. Paula Rothenberg served as Director of the New Jersey Project for many years.  The organization ceased operating in 2006.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      

        <p>The New Jersey Project Records document the organization from its inception through its termination in 2006.  The collection is a rich source of information about issues of race, class, and gender in higher education,  in New Jersey specifically, and the efforts of that State to address them among its college and university students and faculty. Types of materials include administrative files, publications, correspondence and emails, reports, writings, books, photographs, conference packets, audiocassettes, DVDs, videocassettes, grant applications, financial information, articles, and photographs.</p>
      <p> NOTE: There is no container list online for this finding aid.  You may contact the
Sophia Smith Collection if you want one sent to you.</p>
</scopecontent>
 
     <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
      <head>Information on Use</head>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
         <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
          <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following restriction:</p>
	<p>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must request boxes 48 hours in advance.</p>
          <p>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.</p>
          <p>Note: this collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
        <p>Copyright to unpublished materials may be  owned by the creator, or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
        </userestrict>
    </descgrp>
      <prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>New Jersey Project Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
Northampton, Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>

</descgrp>

   <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
       <head>Search Terms</head>
<!-- HIGHLIGHT EACH SEARCH TERM AND CLICK ON APPROPRIATE SUBJECT CLIPS -->
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">New Jersey Project</corpname> 
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Rothenberg, Paula S., 1943-</persname> 
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sex discrimination in education--United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Education--New Jersey--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Multiculturalism--Study and teaching (Higher)--New Jersey</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Education, Higher--New Jersey--Curricula</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Multicultural education--New Jersey--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's studies--New Jersey</subject>

 </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
