<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss203.html">mnsss203</eadid>

	<filedesc>
		<titlestmt>
			<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">New England Learning Center for Women in Transition (NELCWIT) Records, 1975-2001 (ongoing)</titleproper>
			<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
			<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Amanda Izzo.</author>
		</titlestmt>
		<publicationstmt>
			<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
			<address>
				<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
			</address>
			<date encodinganalog="260$c">2005</date>
			<p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
		</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
	<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Jennifer Smar. 
		<date>2005-11-30</date>
	</creation>
	<langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

  <frontmatter id="front"> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb />Smith College</publisher> 
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">New England Learning Center for Women in Transition (NELCWIT) Records, 1975-2001 (ongoing)</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle> 
		<num>MS 459</num> 
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Amanda Izzo</author> 
		<date encodinganalog="260$c">2005</date> 
		 
		 
		<p>© 2005 Smith College. All rights reserved.</p> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 

<archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
		<origination label="Creator:">
			<corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">New England Learning Center for Women in Transition (Greenfield, Mass.)</corpname>
		</origination>
		<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">New England Learning Center for Women in Transition records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1975-2001 (ongoing)</unitdate>

		<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 459</unitid>
		
		<physdesc label="Quantity:">
			<extent encodinganalog="300$a">2 boxes</extent>
			<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1.75 linear ft.)</extent>
		</physdesc>
		<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
            <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langmaterial>

         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            </repository>

		<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
			Women's shelter. The NELCWIT Records include reports, planning board minutes, personal writings, fundraising and outreach materials,  articles and clippings, and publications.  The collection documents the organization's administration, shelter and counseling services, and educational programs from its founding in 1976 to the present. Included are personal writings by survivors of domestic violence and abuse; research papers; and publicity and printed materials related to issues of domestic violence and sexual abuse in Western Massachusetts and beyond.
		</abstract>
</did>

<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->

<bioghist id="bioghist">
<head>Historical Note</head>
<p>The New England Learning Center for Women in Transition (NELCWIT) targets the needs of women and children in largely rural Franklin County, Massachusetts who have experienced domestic or sexual abuse. NELCWIT was the brainchild of a collective of Franklin County women who, particularly influenced by the self-help ethos of 1970s feminism, devised a means of raising awareness and providing solutions for violence in the home. Working at a time when municipal agencies offered no services for women leaving abusive homes and law enforcement routinely encouraged battered wives to make amends with their husbands, the founders established NELCWIT as a direct service and support agency. Rejecting the prevailing mentality that domestic abuse was a matter to be settled within the family and that it was primarily the fault of the victim, NELCWIT compelled local social service agencies to consider the hands-on approach to preventing and resolving domestic violence.
</p>

<p>The group opened an office in 1976, relying solely, at first, on volunteered staff and resources to offer counseling, information, and an ad hoc shelter program that housed women and children fleeing abusive situations in the private homes of supporters. By the late 1970s, successful fundraising efforts and job funding disbursed through the Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA) allowed NELCWIT's programming to flourish. NELCWIT established a space that functioned exclusively as an emergency shelter and networked successfully with other women's groups and social service and law enforcement agencies to devise solutions to domestic violence and sexual abuse. Unfortunately, the service was much needed: rural isolation made it difficult for many victims to get the psychological and material support necessary to escape abusive situations, and the region's high unemployment and economic hardships produced a stressful atmosphere that contributed to family violence.</p>

<p>At its inception, the group functioned as a strictly feminist, anti-hierarchical enterprise. Administration was managed collectively, "personal sharing" was on most meeting agendas, and "process meetings" assured that no single volunteer or employee exercised too much influence. Around 1980, at the height of its rise to prominence as a self-starting and well-utilized service provider, local selectmen pulled NELCWIT's CETA funding, citing the organization's collective administration (which was seen as providing insufficient oversight) and "anti-male" bias as justification. NELCWIT waged a successful battle to recapture the funding, but the impasse marked the first of several funding crises and a shift to a more traditional administrative structure (although the organization continued to be led and staffed primarily by women). Its longevity and status as a pioneer in the field of providing shelter, support, and prevention of domestic abuse helped to establish it as a recipient of United Way funding and as an influential player in the social services landscape of Franklin County. While NELCWIT has not abandoned its core mission of addressing domestic abuse, its programming has branched out to include outreach to abusers and efforts to stop racism. NELCWIT remains an active organization.</p>

</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
<head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
<p>This partially processed portion of NELCWIT Records consists of 1.75 linear ft. and documents the organization's founding and programming from 1975 to 2001. The date spans of 1976-81 and 1987-2001 are particularly well represented. Confidential client and shelter records are not included as part of the collection, and they will not be deposited at the Sophia Smith Collection. </p>

<p>SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION pertains to the creation and ongoing management of NELCWIT. The material contained in its Board of Directors and Planning Board committee files trace the organization's evolution from its conception to the creation of an effective agency with a paid staff and a large list of clientele. The committee work gives considerable evidence of the difficulty of reconciling the founders' egalitarian ideals with the day-to-day operations of a growing group, particularly in the sometimes-hostile environment of greater Franklin County. These factors are also evident in the administrative correspondence, internal news sheets, and fundraising files. In addition, the series' fundraising files indicate the intensive, creative efforts necessary to sustain a non-profit organization. The Personnel files include materials from reunions of NELCWIT staffers, and a small file of statistics for 1977 indicate the range of functions the organization served.</p>

<p>SERIES II. PROGRAMS contains materials of some of NELCWIT's ancillary efforts, including conferences, an anti-racism initiative of the 1990s, and participation in the Franklin County Coalition for a Safe Community (FCCSC). The FCCSC sponsored Violence Awareness Prevention Awareness events and was the result of a coalition among the county's health and human service agencies and organizations. This series also contains the records of the Woman of the Year banquet sponsored by NELCWIT from 1989-95. Woman of the Year efforts solicited input from the citizens of Franklin County to single out and celebrate the achievements of a local woman; it also served as a means of generating awareness and advertising revenue for NELCWIT. </p>

<p>NELCWIT's primary programming work is best documented in SERIES III.  PUBLICITY AND WRITINGS.  Publicity includes articles and newspaper clippings about the organization, as well as printed material produced by NELCWIT for outreach and fundraising purposes. Clippings from local newspapers trace the services provided by NELCWIT over the thirty-year course of its existence, documenting its emergency services, efforts to compel recognition of the toll of abuse, and the long-term counseling and support groups offered as means to cope with and healing from violence. News coverage also records the changing atmosphere in which NELCWIT was received, beginning with receptivity toward its efforts initially being found primarily in the alternative and feminist press and eventually garnering a greater appreciation and recognition for its work. A series of domestic violence-related homicides in Franklin County in the late-1980s brought a spate of press coverage to Franklin County and highlighted the necessity for domestic abuse awareness and prevention. The printed material produced by NELCWIT includes newsletters, brochures, fundraising appeals, and informational packets. These materials illustrate the variety of programs undertaken throughout the years and demonstrate one of the primary means by which NELCWIT sought to help women empower themselves, which was to provide the information and resources to recognize and escape abusive relationships. </p>

<p>Writings include a report, "Domestic Abuse of Women in Franklin County, Massachusetts," (1978) and a Master's Thesis, "New England Learning Center for Women in Transition: The Planning Stages of a Residential Learning Center for Women in Transition," (1978) give in-depth accounts of NELCWIT's treatment approaches and the type of situations in which it was called to assist. Files relating to the writing project "Shattered Silences" have considerable historical value. In 1991, NELCWIT solicited writings related to abuse for a published booklet. The poetry and prose pieces can be read as both therapeutic exercises for survivors and a means to implode the silences and misinformation surrounding sexual and physical abuse. </p>

<p>SERIES IV. SUBJECT FILES consists of printed materials which provide more general reference information and background on matters of violence; spousal, child, and sexual abuse; and feminism. These materials were possibly used by staff and clients as resource files.
</p>
</scopecontent>


<arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	<head>Organization of the Collection</head>
	<p>This collection is organized into four series:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">I. ADMINISTRATION</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">II. PROGRAMS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser3">III. PUBLICITY AND WRITINGS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser4">IV. SUBJECT FILES</ref>
		</item>
	</list>
</arrangement>
<arrangement id="scope-arr">
<head>Arrangement of the Collection</head>
	<p>Note: This collection has not been fully processed;therefore:
	  <list>
		<item>Folders may not be clearly labeled or numbered.</item>
		<item>Some materials may not be in folders.</item>
		<item>Materials may not be in logical order within folders.</item>
		<item>The container list may not be very detailed, or completely accurate.</item>
		<item>There may be duplicates of some materials.</item>
		<item>Locations of materials are subject to change when collection is fully processed at a later date.</item> 
		<item>Some items may be fragile or deteriorated, requiring further preservation treatment.</item></list></p>

	<p>Please:
	  <list>
		<item>Handle fragile or deteriorated items with extreme care.</item>
		<item>Remove one file at a time and place a flag in its place in the box.</item>
		<item>Put items and folders back in their original order.</item>
		<item>When citing materials do not use box and/or folder numbers as they may change.</item>
		<item>We know you are trying to be helpful, but please refrain from making corrections to the lists or the folders.</item>
	 </list>
	</p>
</arrangement>
<!-- End collection level metadata -->

<!-- Enter administrative information -->


<descgrp id="admin">
	<head>Information on Use</head>
	<descgrp>
		<head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
		<accessrestrict id="admin-access">
			<p>The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, except for a small portion of restricted material. Researchers must sign an Access Agreement form agreeing to preserve the anonymity of individuals represented in the collection. </p>
		</accessrestrict>
		<userestrict id="admin-use">
			<p>Copyright to materials produced by NELCWIT has been transferred to the Sophia Smith Collection. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."</p>

		</userestrict>
	</descgrp>
 	<prefercite id="admin-cite">
		<head>Preferred Citation</head>
		<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
		<p>New England Learning Center for Women in Transition Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
	</prefercite>

 <altformavail id="admin-altform">
		<head>Additional Formats</head>
	<p>The video tapes in this collection have been digitized and are available to 
<extref href="https://media.smith.edu/departments/ssc/nelcwit/nelcwit_playlist.html">view online</extref> (Smith campus only).</p>
    </altformavail>
	<accruals id="admin-accruals">
		<head>Additions to the Collection</head>
		<p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this finding aid.</p>
	</accruals>
	<descgrp>
		<head>History of the Collection</head>
		<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
			<p>The New England Learning Center for Women in Transition donated its records to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 2001.</p> 
		</acqinfo>
		<processinfo id="admin-process">
			<p>Preliminary processing done by Amanda Izzo, 2005.</p> 
		</processinfo>
	</descgrp>
</descgrp>



<!-- End administrative information -->

<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->


<controlaccess id="subj">
<head>Search Terms</head>

<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">New England Learning Center for Women in Transition (Greenfield, Mass.)--History--Sources</corpname>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abused women--Services for--Massachusetts--History--Sources</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists--Greenfield (Mass)--History--Sources</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Family violence--Massachusetts--History--Sources</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Rural women--Massachusetts--History--Sources</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sexual abuse victims--Services for--United States.</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Legal status, laws, etc.--Massachusetts--History</subject>
<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's shelters--Massachusetts--History--Sources</subject>
<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Franklin County (Mass.)--History--Sources</geogname> 
</controlaccess>



<!-- end controlled access terms -->

<!-- Enter additional information -->





<!-- End additional information -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->


<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
<head>Contents List</head>
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>By-laws, <unitdate>circa 1970s</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Board of Directors</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2-3</container>
 <unittitle>Agendas, minutes, reports, lists, and notes,<unitdate> 1975-83</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Membership forms,<unitdate> 1978</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Director search: job description, interview material, and notes, <unitdate>circa 1981</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Planning board committee (includes miscellaneous committees)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">6-8</container>
 <unittitle>Minutes and agendas,<unitdate> 1975-78</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Notes, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence,<unitdate> 1977-83</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Fundraising and organizational development</unittitle>
 <note>
 <p>
 <ref target="list-ser2">[see also SERIES II. PROGRAMS--Woman of the Year Banquet]</ref></p>
 </note>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Bowl-a-thon fundraiser: press releases, notes, and scorecards,<unitdate> 1978-80</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Proposals, process committee materials, notes, budgets, and reports,<unitdate> 1975-81, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Fundraisers' committee: notes, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>Completed fundraisers: correspondence, drafts, and notes,<unitdate> 1989-92</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Mini-grants: fundraising correspondence,<unitdate> 1988-92</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">16-17</container>
 <unittitle>Major gifts campaign: correspondence, research materials, pledges, lists, and notes,<unitdate> 1991-92</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">18</container>
 <unittitle>Research and notes, circa early<unitdate> 1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">19</container>
 <unittitle>Ideas and research,<unitdate> 1990s</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">20</container>
 <unittitle>Funding and budget: notes,<unitdate> 1987, 1998-2001</unitdate>, n.d.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">21</container>
 <unittitle>Internal news sheets,<unitdate> 1978</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">22</container>
 <unittitle>Office space: New Salem Academy building use proposal and photographs, circa 1976; and correspondence and bills,<unitdate> 1981-83</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Personnel</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">23</container>
 <unittitle>Reunion: correspondence, publicity, mailing lists,<unitdate> 1986, 2001</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">24</container>
 <unittitle>Job listings, <unitdate>2001</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">25</container>
 <unittitle>Volunteer application materials and notes,<unitdate> 1991</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">26</container>
 <unittitle>Statistics,<unitdate> 1977</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. PROGRAMS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">27</container>
 <unittitle>Anti-racism work, <unitdate>circa 1997</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Conferences</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">28</container>
 <unittitle>Memoranda and publicity,<unitdate> 1976-77</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">29</container>
 <unittitle>Sexual assault conference: registration and notes,<unitdate> 1988</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Franklin County Coalition for a Safe Community</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">30</container>
 <unittitle>Stationery, financial, and facility information,<unitdate> 1994</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">31</container>
 <unittitle>Violence Prevention Awareness Events: correspondence, memoranda, minutes, mailing lists, and notes,<unitdate> 1993-95</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">32</container>
 <unittitle>Press releases, clippings, and writings,<unitdate> 1994-95, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">33</container>
 <unittitle>Shelter admission forms, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">34-41</container>
 <unittitle>Woman of the Year Banquet: correspondence, program material, nominations, photographs, and notes,<unitdate> 1989-95</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. PUBLICITY AND WRITINGS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">42-44</container>
 <unittitle>Publicity</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Clippings and printed material about NELCWIT and Franklin County,<unitdate> 1976-2001, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">45</container>
 <unittitle>First NELCWIT flier,<unitdate> 1976?</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">46</container>
 <unittitle>Informational packet: articles, fliers, and statistics,<unitdate> 1980s</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">47-48</container>
 <unittitle>Printed materials: handouts, announcements, and fundraising appeals from NELCWIT,<unitdate> 1987-2001, n.d. (circa 1980s-90s)</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">49</container>
 <unittitle>Statements, press releases, "position papers,"and miscellaneous information about NELCWIT,<unitdate> 1970s</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>NELCWIT newsletter,<unitdate> 1986, 1990-2001</unitdate></unittitle>
 <note>
 <p>
 <ref target="list-ser1">[see also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION--Internal news sheets]</ref></p>
 </note>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Writings</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Reports (including CETA-funded "Domestic Abuse of Women in Franklin County, Massachusetts"),<unitdate> 1977-78</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>"New England Learning Center for Women in Transition: The Planning Stages of a Residential Learning Center for Women in Transition," Master's thesis by Susan Weinberg (Goddard: Cambridge),<unitdate> 1978</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Shattered Silences</title>: collection of writings about abuse sponsored by NELCWIT,<unitdate> 1991</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Printed book and page proofs</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence, financial material, and notes,<unitdate> 1991-92</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Writing submissions and correspondence  [Closed: folders have been removed]</unittitle>
 </did>

 </c04>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES IV. SUBJECT FILES</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">6-9</container>
 <unittitle>Printed material and clippings,<unitdate> 1970s-90s</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Newsletters and magazines</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Feminist publications,<unitdate> 1970s-80</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Ecumenical Resource Consultants: newsletter,<unitdate> 1993</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>




<!-- End container list -->

</archdesc>
</ead>
