<ead>
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601"
repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924" audience="internal" id="head"
relatedencoding="MARC21">


  <eadid publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss520.xml//EN" countrycode="us"
mainagencycode="mnsss">mnsss520</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Carol Hutchings Maynard Papers, 1905-2002</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2012">2012</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">February 20, 2012</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Maynard, Carol Hutchings, 1895-1973</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Carol Hutchings Maynard
Papers</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:">1905-2002</unitdate><unitdate
type="bulk" encodinganalog="245$g">1910s-50s</unitdate>
      <unitid label="Collection Number:" encodinganalog="099" countrycode="us"
repositorycode="mnsss">MS 674</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">3 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language of Material:" encodinganalog="546">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <!-- MRJ Edit as needed-->
           <abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">
            Farmer; Teacher; Poet; Suffragist. Papers document an unconventional life, from suffrage campaigns of her youth to the artistic output
of her later years. Materials related to Maynard's art and her career as a farmer and educator showcase an unusual set of interests and talents. Maynard retained clippings and correspondence from her difficult tenure at a South Carolina reform school. Papers from the Massachusetts Refomatory for Women feature writing assignments completed by inmates. Creative output includes poetry written largely from the 1930s and 1950s, drawings and prints, and a short memoir. The scrapbooks are exceptional resources for memorabilia, photographs, and clippings from Maynard's time as a suffrage activist, a "farmerette" of the Women's Land Army, and an employee of the Montrose School for Girls.


         </abstract>
       
</did>

 <!--  Add paragraph marks to text -->
<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
     <p>Carol Hutchings Maynard, known as "Hutch," was born to Caroline (Baxter) and Edwin Maynard in
Mount Vernon, New York on 15 August 1895. The second of five children, she was raised in Worcester,
Massachusetts. She graduated from Classical High School in 1915. Following graduation, Maynard
settled in New York City, where she became active in the campaign for women's suffrage, canvassing
and marching on behalf of New York suffrage leagues. Her work was publicized in Worcester
newspapers. In 1918, she enlisted in the Woman's Land Army of America, a war-time venture that
trained women to perform agricultural labor. The colloquially termed "farmerettes" were deployed to
replace male farm workers engaged by the war. Maynard completed Land Army training at Wellesley
College and was stationed at Bedford, New York. After the war, she traveled west as a self-
described vagabond, settling in Alaska for a period of time in the early 1920s. There, she lived
alone and took work in the salmon canneries.</p> 

<p>From the 1930s forward, Maynard was employed as an educator and agriculturalist at a series of secondary schools. This phase of her career started at
women's reform institutions. She was hired by the South Carolina State Industrial School for Girls
in 1928 but was soon dismissed by the state governor in a controversial case targeting the
institution's leadership. Subsequently, she took employment at the Montrose School for Girls in
Reistertown, Maryland. In 1935, Maynard applied for a position with the farm program at the newly
opened Putney School, a preparatory high school in Vermont that emphasized progressive ideals and
manual labor. Initially camouflaging her gender by submitting an application under the name "C.H.
Maynard," Maynard was hired to manage the school's farm. She also supervised the student work
program, which was the labor-oriented segment of the curriculum. In the late 1930s, Maynard took a
hiatus from Putney, worked at the Massachusetts Reformatory for Women in Framingham, and returned
to Putney in 1944. Her association with the Putney School continued for the remainder of her life.</p>

<p>In her positions at each of these educational institutions, Maynard combined her passions for
agriculture, animal husbandry, and creative writing. She encouraged her students to do the same,
offering instruction in dairying and poetry alike. Maynard herself was an artist, dramatist, and a
prolific poet. Her poetry frequently focused on agricultural life--animals, plants and seasons--but
was far-ranging, touching upon love, loss, and the arts. From the 1940s to the 1960s, she developed
the farming side of her career as a tester for the Vermont Dairy Herd Improvement Association. She
also was involved in the 4-H and was active in civic life, serving as a member of the town's school
board and planning commission. She took particular interest in the town and school gardens, and
after her death, the Hutch Maynard Fund was started at the Putney School to support its greenhouse.
Hutch Maynard died on January 7, 1973 at the age of 77.</p>
</bioghist>
 <!--  Add paragraph marks to text -->
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
    <p> The Carol Hutchings Maynard Papers document diverse facets of her unconventional life, from
the suffrage campaigns of her youth to the artistic output of her later years. Materials pertaining
to the Maynard family history can be found in photographs, many of which are unidentified, and in a
small amount of family correspondence. There are also photos and biographical material about Carol
Hutchings Maynard. Her civic interests are reflected in a small amount of correspondence pertaining
to Putney town and school issues in the 1960s. The newspaper clippings labeled "Trip West" were
presumably collected during her travels as an itinerant laborer. Materials related to Maynard's art
and her career as a farmer and educator showcase an unusual set of interests and talents. Maynard
retained clippings and correspondence from her difficult tenure at a South Carolina reform school.
Papers from the Massachusetts Refomatory for Women feature writing assignments completed by
inmates. Creative output includes poetry written largely from the 1930s and 1950s, drawings and
prints, and a short memoir. The scrapbooks are exceptional resources for memorabilia, photographs,
and clippings from Maynard's time as a suffrage activist, a "farmerette" of the Women's Land Army,
and an employee of the Montrose School for Girls.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
       
</scopecontent>
 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">

<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	   <list type="simple">
    		<item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
                     <item>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.</item>
	   </list>
</p>
</accessrestrict>


<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works in this collection created by Carol Maynard.  Copyright to other works in the collection may be owned by the creator, or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Carol Hutchings Maynard Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton,
Mass.</p>
</prefercite>



<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Carol Maynard Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2011 by her executor Elizabeth Mills.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by Amanda Izzo, April 2011 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Farm life -- Vermont -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Juvenile delinquency -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Poets, American -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Putney (Vt.) -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reformatories for women -- Massachusetts -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Rural women -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Single women -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Suffrage -- New York (State) -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women adventurers -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women artists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women authors, American -- 20th century -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women farmers -- United States -- History -- 20th century</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women poets, American -- 20th century -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women prisoners -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1914-1918 -- Women -- United States -- Personal narratives</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1939-1945 -- Women -- United States -- Personal narratives</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Maynard, Carol Hutchings, 1895-1973</persname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">MCI-Framingham (Correctional facility )</corpname>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Putney School -- Faculty</corpname>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Women's Land Army of America -- History</corpname>

</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->

