<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss546.xml//EN">mnsss546</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Hedda Nussbaum Papers, c1940s-2009
(ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">January 27, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Nussbaum, Hedda, 1942-</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Hedda Nussbaum papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">c1940s-2009 (ongoing)</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 642</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">22 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(14 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Author; Editor. Papers include diaries (closed); correspondence to Nussbaum from others
re: Steinberg case; legal files re: case Hedda Nussbaum v. Joel Steinberg; writings and talks by
Nussbaum;  Nussbaum's published books; videos, including interviews and TV broadcasts featuring
Nussbaum, and documentaries about domestic violence; photographs of Nussbaum and family; artwork;
and memorabilia.

        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Hedda Nussbaum was born on August 8, 1942 in New York, NY to Emma Rosenthal and William
Nussbaum. She earned her B.A. at Hunter College (1964) and her Paralegal Certificate from Mercy
College (1991). Prior to entering the public eye in the media frenzy that resulted from the 1987
beating death of her six-year-old adopted daughter, Lisa Steinberg, she worked as an editor of
children's books at Random House.  Although initially implicated in the crime, charges against
Nussbaum were dropped prior to the trial and she testified against her husband, Joel Steinberg, who
was convicted of manslaughter and served fifteen years in prison. Trial proceedings revealed that
Steinberg had for years abused Nussbaum physically and psychologically, and her book, <title render="italic">Surviving
Intimate Terrorism</title> (2005), shows the complexity of domestic violence and does much to explain her
denial of the danger of her situation and that of her children (the couple also had a younger
adopted child, Mitchell).  In the years that followed Lisa Steinberg's death, Nussbaum worked to
rebuild her life and had numerous reconstructive plastic surgeries. She also co-facilitated a
support group for battered women for about eight years and later worked as a paralegal for an
organization that helps battered women. In 1995, she began giving talks about abuse at colleges and
shelters but when Steinberg was released from prison in 2004, she receded from public attention.
Nussbaum is also the author of two children's books:  <title render="italic">Plants Do Amazing Things</title> (1977) and <title render="italic">Animals
Build Amazing Houses</title> (1979).</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>Papers include diaries (closed); correspondence to Nussbaum from others re: Steinberg case;
legal files re: case Hedda Nussbaum v. Joel Steinberg; writings and talks by Nussbaum;  Nussbaum's
published books; videos, including interviews and TV broadcasts featuring Nussbaum, and
documentaries about domestic violence; photographs of Nussbaum and family; artwork; and memorabilia.
</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>Access to original audiovisual material is restricted.</item>
                         <item>Portions of collection are stored offsite; researchers must give 48
hours advance notice.</item>
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>Hedda Nussbaum retains copyright to her works within this collection.  Copyright to
materials created by others are owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission
must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the
responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Hedda Nussbaum Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated by Hedda Nussbaum beginning in 2009.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
           <p>Accessioned by Burd Schlessinger; Kathleen Banks Nutter, 2009 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abused women -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Child abuse -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Domestic violence -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Family violence -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Trials (murder) -- New York (State) -- New York</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Nussbaum, Hedda, 1942-</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Steinberg, Joel Barnet, 1941-</persname> 

</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
