<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss238.html">mnsss238</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Dorothea De Schweinitz and Louise De Schweinitz  (Darrow) Papers, 1912-
1997</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
        <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
       </titlestmt>
       <publicationstmt>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
         <address>
           <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
         </address>
         <date calendar="gregorian" era="ce">© 2005</date>
         <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by
 Margaret Jessup and Jennifer Smar.
           <date>2006-04-07</date>
 <!-- CHANGE TO TODAY'S DATE IF NECESSARY -->
     </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter id="front">
    <titlepage>
      <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb />Smith College<lb /></publisher>
   <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Dorothea De Schweinitz and Louise De Schweinitz  (Darrow) Papers, 1912-1997    (bulk dates 1970-1980)</titleproper>
   <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
   <num>MS 398</num>
   <date encodinganalog="260$c">2005</date>
   
     <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon
 Foundation.</sponsor>
       <p>© 2005  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
   </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
 <did id="main">
 	<head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">De Schweinitz, Dorothea, 1891-</persname>
         </origination>
   <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Dorothea De Schweinitz and Louise De
Schweinitz  (Darrow) Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1912-1997</unitdate>
        <unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1970-1980</unitdate>
 <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 398</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">4 boxes</extent>
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(3.5 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
    <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>

  </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            </repository>
 <!-- MRJ: EDIT ABSTRACT  -->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Papers of Louise de Schweinitz Darrow, physician and birth control advocate include correspondence, diaries, photographs and memorabilia. Papers of Dorothea de Schweinitz, social worker and labor researcher, include correspondence documenting her trip to Germany, 1913, where she first learned of class issues, management and labor issues, and an oral history.
    </abstract>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
    <head>Biographical Note</head>
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc6444.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>Dorothea de Schweinitz and Louise de Schweinitz <lb />Darrow at the dedication of the Zinzendorf <lb />bust in Bethlehem, PA, May 16, 1973</p></daodesc></dao>
       <p>Dorothea de Schweinitz (1891-1980) was born in Nazareth, PA. She was the third child of Paul and Mary de Schweinitz. She attended the Moravian Parochial School and graduated from Smith College in 1912. Later she studied at the Universities of Wisconsin and Chicago and obtained her M.A. at Columbia University in 1929. She spent twenty years in employment and vocational guidance work in the YWCA in New York, in developing a Junior Employment Service in the public schools of Philadelphia, in the Industrial Research Department of the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, and in assisting in the development of a demonstration office in Philadelphia of the Pennsylvania State Employment Service and in research in the U.S. Employment Service in Washington. During this period she wrote two books: <title render="italic">How Workers Find Jobs, A Study of 4,000 Hosiert Workers in Philadelphia</title> and <title render="italic">Occupations in Retail Stores</title>. She was president of the Philadelphia Vocational Guidance Association in 1924-25 and of the National Vocational Guidance Association in 1925-26. The next twenty years she spent in employer-labor relations as regional director of the National Labor Relations Board in St. Louis, chief of the Committee Standards Branch, War Production Board (an activity concerned with labor-management cooperation through joint production committees) with headquarters in Washington, and as an industrial relations specialist in the Wage Stabilization Board. After World War II she obtained a grant from the Wertheim Committee of Harvard University and in 1949 her book on the war period, <title render="italic">Labor and Management in a Common Enterprise</title>, was published by the Harvard University Press. In 1966 her book <title render="italic">Labor-Management Consultation in the Factory, the Experience of England, Sweden and Germany</title>, was published. This was the result of a year's independent research in the countries indicated. After retirement de Schweinitz gave her attention to the problems of Georgetown in Washington, D.C. She was instrumental in obtaining the 1950 "Old Georgetown" Act in which the U.S. Congress established Georgetown as a Historic District under the protection of the Commission of Fine Arts. She was also the moving spirit in forming Historic Georgetown, Inc., which rescued from demolition the Thomas Sim Lee buildings at 30th and M Streets. On 27 Feb 1974 de Schweinitz received a Smith College Medal.</p>

	<p>Dr. Louise de Schweinitz Darrow was born in Nazareth, PA, in 1898. A 1918 graduate of Smith College, she studied at Columbia University and received her medical degree from Johns Hopkins Medical School in 1924. She practiced medicine at Yale University and the community Health Well Baby Clinics in New Haven CT. and later was the examining physician and patient coordinator in the children's rehabilitation unit of University of Kansas Medical Center. She was active in community affairs. She died at the age of 99, April 3, 1997.</p>

</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
       <p> The collection contains material about both Dorothea de Schweinitz and her sister, Louise de Schweinitz Darrow. The material about Dorothea includes biographical material (including an oral history taken by Jackie van Voris in 1972); correspondence to family documenting her trip to Germany in 1913, where she first learned of class issues, management and labor issues, and was introduced to the field of social work; correspondence with family and friends (1913-1980); an undated diary; publications, and correspondence and clippings pertaining her historic preservation work in Georgetown, D.C.  Material of Louise de Schweinitz Darrow's includes letters to her parents (1933-41) and her children (1967-91) and two diaries (1912, 1914).  There are also photographs and family history material.</p>
            <p> NOTE: The container list for this collection is available in the Sophia Smith Collection.  Please contact us to request a copy.</p>
</scopecontent>

     <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
      <head>Information on Use</head>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
         <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
          <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection.</p>
          <p>This collection has not been fully processed.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
         <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
        </userestrict>
    </descgrp>
      <prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Dorothea De Schweinitz and Louise De Schweinitz  (Darrow) Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>
     <accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
        <head>Additions to the Collection</head>
          <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
      </accruals>
</descgrp>

   <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
       <head>Search Terms</head>
<!-- HIGHLIGHT EACH SEARCH TERM AND CLICK ON APPROPRIATE SUBJECT CLIPS -->
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">De Schweinitz, Dorothea, 1891-</persname> 
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Darrow, Louise de Schweinitz, 1898-1997</persname> 
    <geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Germany (West)--Description and travel--Sources</geogname> 
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Industrial relations--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Labor--Research--20th century--Sources</subject>
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Smith College--Students--History--Sources</corpname>
    <famname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Schweinitz family</famname> 
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Moravian Church--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women physicians--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--New York--History--Sources</corpname> 
<!-- Added Entries -->
         <persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Darrow, Louise de Schweinitz, 1898-1997</persname> 
 </controlaccess>
<descgrp id="addinfo" type="add">
<head>Additional Information</head>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>See also
<extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/smitharchives/manosca115_main.html">Dorothea De Schweinitz Papers</extref> in the Smith College Archives.</p>
</relatedmaterial>
</descgrp>
</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->