<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss447.xml//EN">mnsss447</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Kathleen O'Shea Papers, 1910-2006</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">O'Shea, Kathleen A., 1944-</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Kathleen O'Shea papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1910-2006</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 578</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">6 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(6 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Author; Lesbian activist; Social reform advocate; Catholic nun. Papers include documents and memorabilia from O'Shea's childhood, including her education in becoming a nun; correspondence; photographs; and a small amount of materials pertaining to lesbian former nuns.  Photographs such luminaries as Toni Morrison, Joyce Carol Oates, Angela Davis, bell hooks, Sister Helen Prejean, and David Kaczynski (brother of infamous "Unabomber" Ted Kaczynski). Also included is research related to O'Shea's writings on women on death row with files on sixty-five women prisoners, including correspondence from some, and video tapes about women in prison, including Aileen Wuornos. 
                 </abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
     <p>Kathleen O'Shea was born in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma, in November 26, 1944. She was adopted in infancy by Sarah Alida Conde O'Shea and James O'Shea and grew up in Salina, Kansas.  In eighth grade she decided to become a nun in the Catholic Church.  In 1958 she became an Aspirant of the Apostolic School at Nazareth Motherhouse in Concordia, Kansas, but was sent home at the end of the year to wait until she was "more mature."  In 1960, O'Shea began her Postulancy at St. Joseph's Villa in Peapack, New Jersey, graduating in 1962.  She entered the Immaculate Heart Novitiate in Glen Cove, New York in August, 1961, and became a nun (Sister Mary Fidelis) in 1963.  O'Shea was a nun for 30 years, after which she began work as social worker doing research on female offenders, with an emphasis on women on death row.  She is the author of 	<title render="italic">Female Offenders: An Annotated Bibliography</title> (1997), <title render="italic">Women and the Death Penalty in the United States: 1900-1998</title> (1999), and <title render="italic">Women on the Row: Revelations From Both Sides of the Bars</title> (2000), which was nominated for a Pulitzer.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>Papers include documents and memorabilia from O'Shea's childhood, including her education in becoming a nun; correspondence with close friends; and photographs of O'Shea and friends; and a small amount of materials pertaining to lesbian former nuns.  Photographs of events feature such luminaries as Toni Morrison, Joyce Carol Oates, Angela Davis, bell hooks, Sister Helen Prejean, and David Kaczynski (brother of infamous "Unabomber" Ted Kaczynski). Also included is research related to O'Shea's writings on women on death row with files on sixty-five women prisoners, including correspondence from some, and video tapes about women in prison, including several about Aileen Wuornos.  O'Shea has provided extensive annotation, explanatory notes, and biographical information, which add to the collection's richness and depth.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                    <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
                     <p>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Kathleen O'Shea Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Kathleen A. O'Shea in 2007.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger, 2007. </p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Catholic women--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Capital punishment--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Death row--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Death row inmates--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian nuns--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Nuns--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women and religion--United States--History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women murderers--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women prisoners--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">O'Shea, Kathleen A.</persname> 
</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material in the Sarah Alida Conde O'Shea Papers, Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>

</archdesc>
</ead>
