<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss539.xml//EN">mnsss539</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Alice O. Howell Papers, 1932-2011 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">January 27, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Howell, Alice O., 1922-</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Alice O. Howell papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1932-2011 (ongoing)</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 660</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">17 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(18.25 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Teacher; Author; Astrologer. Collection includes personal papers and
materials pertaining to Howell's career as an astrologer and teacher and practitioner of Jungian
cosmology/psychology:  a lengthy oral history; teaching materials; diaries; writings; correspondence; publicity materials; subject files; and memorabilia.

        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
     <p>Alice Orcutt Howell was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts, the daughter of Penelope King and
Reginald Wilson Orcutt.  From the age of five, she lived abroad with her parents, traveling through
thirty-seven countries on four continents by the age of eighteen.  They lived in hotels and
boarding schools, never staying more than three months in one place, and Howell became fluent in
English, French, German and Italian.  She earned a Deutsch Diploma at the Buser Institute in
Switzerland with a major in German literature and a minor in World History, and later took
postgraduate courses at the New York School for Social Research.  Disillusioned with traditional
Christianity and searching for spiritual meaning, beginning at age thirteen Howell read the holy
books of many of the great religions, including the Bible, the Koran, the Upanishads, the
Dhammapada, and the Tao Te Ching, as well as Greek and Norse mythology. She also studied the work
of Jung, Freud, St. Ignatius and William James, as well as that of prominent astrologers.  In 1944
she began a serious study of astrology under Marc Edmund Jones.  She married Douglass Morse Howell
and with him raised four children. She taught English and History in private schools on Long
Island, New York for eighteen years, and also worked as a secretary to several people, including
Norman Cousins, Editor of the Saturday Review of Literature, and Walter Russell, sculptor and
physicist.  During World War II, Howell worked in the U.S. Office of Censorship, censoring German
and French mail in New York City.</p>

   <p>Beginning in mid-life, Howell's interests in religion,
astrology and psychology coalesced and her life took a different turn.  Her most important
professional contribution has been to "prove astrology a useful diagnostic adjunct to Jungian
psychology", and for many years she taught the subject to analysts at the Jung Foundation and at
the C. G. Jung Institutes in Chicago and Los Angeles.  Howell has traveled the world, lectured
widely, led many seminars, and is the author of nine books: <title render="italic">Jungian Symbolism in Astrology</title> (1987),
<title render="italic">Dove in the Stone: Finding the Sacred in the Commonplace</title> (1988), <title render="italic">Jungian Synchronicity in the
Astrological Signs and Ages: Letters From An Astrologer </title>(1990), H<title render="italic">ow Like An Angel I Came Down:
Conversations With Children on the Gospels</title> (1991), <title render="italic">Web in the Sea: Jung, Sophia, and the Geometry
of the Soul</title> (1993), <title render="italic">Beejum book</title> (2002), <title render="italic">Lara's First Christmas</title> (2004), <title render="italic">Heavens Declare:
Astrological Ages and the Evolution of Consciousness </title>(2006), and <title render="italic">From the Archives of the Heart:
Collected Poems </title>(2010). In 1980 she married her second husband, Walter A. Anderson, who died in 1998. Alice Howell died in Monterey, MA, on October 28, 2014.</p>

<p>[source: interview with Howell by Kate Scholly in the Dec/Jan 2009 issue of <title render="italic">Mountain Astrologer</title>]
</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>Collection includes personal papers and materials pertaining to Howell's career as an
astrologer and teacher and practitioner of Jungian cosmology/psychology:  a lengthy oral history of
Alice O. Howell conducted by Nancy Parker in July 2007 (audiorecording); teaching materials;
published and recorded interviews with Howell; diaries; a written draft of her autobiography and
other writings; extensive correspondence with colleagues, friends and students; publicity
materials; subject files; and memorabilia.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                         <item>Portions of collection are stored offsite; researchers must give 48
hours advance notice.</item>
                         <item>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of
research copies.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>Alice O. Howell retains copyright to her unpublished works. Copyright to materials
authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be
obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the
researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Alice O. Howell Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>Alice Howell  donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in in 2010.
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
           <p>Accessioned by Kathleen Banks Nutter, 2010 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Astrologers -- United States -- Biography</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Astrology -- Study  and teaching</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Jungian psychology -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Spirituality -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Howell, Alice O., 1922 -</persname> 

</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
