<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss318.html">mnsss318</eadid>
<!-- ADD CORRECT FILENAME TO LINE ABOVE: MNSSS#  (in 2 places) -->
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">International Women's Tribune Centre Records, 1970-2000
(ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
        <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
       </titlestmt>
       <publicationstmt>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
         <address>
           <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
         </address>
         <date calendar="gregorian" era="ce">© 2005</date>
         <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by
 Margaret Jessup.
         <date>2006-05-02</date>
 <!-- CHANGE TO TODAY'S DATE IF NECESSARY -->
     </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter id="front">
    <titlepage>
      <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection Smith College </publisher>
   <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">International Women's Tribune Centre Records, 1970-2000 (ongoing)</titleproper>
   <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
   <num>MS 373</num>
   <author encodinganalog="245$c">Amy Hague</author>
   <date encodinganalog="260$c">2005</date>
   
     <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon
 Foundation.</sponsor>
       <p>© 2005  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
   </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
 <did id="main">
 	<head>Collection Overview</head>
 <origination label="Creator:">
     <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">International Women's Tribune
 Centre</corpname>
 </origination>
   <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">International Women's Tribune Centre records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1970-2000 (ongoing)</unitdate>
 <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 373</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">122 boxes</extent>
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(145 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
    <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>


  </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
 <!-- MRJ: EDIT ABSTRACT  -->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">International women's organization. Records consist of administrative and project files;
correspondence with funding agencies and project participants; board minutes and agendas; and  the records of the NGO Planning Committees. These include documentation of all four International Women's Year Tribunes, held in Mexico City (1975), Copenhagen (1980), Nairobi (1985), Beijing (1995), and the "Beijing +5" conference in 2000.
    </abstract>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
    
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc3767.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>"The Great Court," at the opening ceremony  of the World Conference on the UN Decade  for Women, University of Nairobi, Kenya, 1985.  From "Forum '85 NGO Planning Committee Final Report." </p></daodesc></dao>
       <p>The International Women's Tribune Centre (previously known as the International Women's Year Tribune Project) was established by the NGO Forum Planning Committees to continue the work begun at the 1975 International Women's Year Tribune.  This first Tribune, which resulted from an initiative submitted by Non-Governmental Organizations (NGOs) to the Commission on the Status of Women, was part of the U.N. Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC). (The U.N. had admitted NGOs to consultative status in the late 1940s. The Conference of NGOs in Consultative Status with ECOSOC (CONGO) was originally comprised of 200 member organizations.) CONGO's function was to facilitate consultation with U.N. bodies and to bring together other NGOs with common interests, for exchange of information and action.</p>

	<p>Following the 1975 IWY Tribune, CONGO created the NGO Forum Planning Committees to prepare activities relating to future International Women's Year Tribunes, to be held in 1980, 1985, and 1995.  The Committees' responsibilities included arranging for facilities in host countries, organizing the program, fundraising, and collaborating with the U.N. Secretariat on publicizing the Tribunes and activities of  NGO Forums. The NGO Forums Planning Committees also offered workshops; film screenings; demonstrations; informal meetings in the areas of education, appropriate technology, and health; and other topics of concern to women in the Third World.</p>

	<p>In addition to these activities, the NGO Forum Planning Committees also created the International Women's Tribune Centre.  The IWTC has evolved into a flexible "women's development support resource," the purpose of which is two-fold:  	1) To maintain the momentum generated during the conferences of International Women's Year in 1975, which some termed the "largest consciousness-raising sessions ever held"; and 2) To encourage and assist women and women's projects, particularly in developing countries, in their efforts to achieve the objectives of the International women's Year World Plan of Action.</p>

	<p>IWTC activities include providing resource, information and liason services, as well as technical assistance in the area of materials development to Third World women's groups. The Tribune Centre publishes a bi-monthly newsletter that is distributed gratis to individuals living outside the U.S. as a means of disseminating development-related information pertaining to women, and to encourage dialogue among women around the world.</p>

</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
       <p>The International Women's Tribune Centre Records (1970-96) consist of project files; correspondence with funding agencies and project participants; and board minutes and agendas. This includes records for all four International Women's Year Tribunes, held in Mexico City in 1975, Copenhagen in 1980, Nairobi in 1985, Beijing in 1995, and "Beijing +5" conference in 2000. The IWTC records include the records of the NGO Planning Committees. </p> 
      <p> NOTE: There is no container list online for this finding aid.  You may contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you want one sent to you.</p>
</scopecontent>
 <!-- MRJ: PROOF -->
     <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
      <head>Information on Use</head>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
         <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
          <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
          <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to
use.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
         <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
        </userestrict>
    </descgrp>
      <prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>International Women's Tribune Centre Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>
  <!--  MRJ: PROOF, AND DELETE THIS ACCRUALS SECTION, if there is no accrual info -->
     <accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
        <head>Additions to the Collection</head>
          <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
      </accruals>
</descgrp>

   <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
       <head>Search Terms</head>
          

<!-- HIGHLIGHT EACH SEARCH TERM AND CLICK ON APPROPRIATE SUBJECT CLIPS -->
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">International Women's Tribune Centre--History--Sources</corpname> 
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">International Women's Year Tribune Project</corpname> 
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Once and Future Action Project (OFAN)</corpname> 
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">International Women's Decade, 1976-85--Congresses</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">International Women's Year, 1975</subject>
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">NGO Forum on Women, Beijing '95</corpname> 
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">World Conference of the United Nations Decade for Women: Equality, Development, and Peace (1980: Copenhagen, Denmark)</corpname> 
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the United Nations Decade for Women (1985 :Nairobi, Kenya) </corpname> 
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminism--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Non-governmental organizations--Congresses</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in development--International cooperation--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--International cooperation--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's rights--Congresses</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Developing countries--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
 </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
