<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss538.xml//EN">mnsss538</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Jean Struven Harris Papers, 1973-1993
(ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">January 27, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Harris, Jean (Jean Struven)</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Jean Struven Harris
Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1973-2005 (bulk 1980-1993)</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 184</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">50 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(62.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
           Teacher; Headmistress of Madeira School; Prison reformer.   While incarcerated in the Bedford Hills Correctional Facility, N.Y. (1981-93) for the murder in the 1980 death of Herman Tarnower she worked in the Children's Center, and published three books: Stranger in Two Worlds (1986), They Always Call Us Ladies (1988), and Marking Time (1991) as well as a number of articles and unpublished manuscripts about women in prison. In 1986 she helped establish the Children of Bedford Fund.  The papers primarily date from 1980 and consist of correspondence; clippings; printed material; research material on correctional systems; writings; legal documents; memorabilia; audiotapes; video tapes (of television interviews); and her trial record.
        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
    <p> Jean Struven was born in Chicago, IL, in 1923.  She earned an A.B. from Smith College in 1945
and married James Harris in 1946.  They had two sons, David and James, Jr.  From 1947-50 and 1953-
66 Harris taught at a variety of primary and secondary levels at the Grosse Point (MI) Country Day
School.  In 1965, Harris completed her M.Ed. from [?] and divorced her husband.  She moved to
Chestnut Hill, PA, where she served as director of the Middle School at the Springside School from
1966-71.  In 1966 she met and began an affair with Dr. Herman Tarnower.  In 1971 she became
headmistress of the Thomas  School in Rowayton, CT and in 1976, Headmistress, Madeira School,
McLean, VA.  Harris was convicted of second-degree murder in the 1980 death of Herman Tarnower and
incarcerated in the Bedford Hills Correctional  Facility, N.Y., 1981-93. While in prison, she
worked in the Children's Center, and wrote <title render="italic">Stranger in Two Worlds</title> (1986), <title render="italic">They Always Call Us
Ladies</title> (1988), and <title render="italic">Marking Time</title> (1991) as well as a number of articles and unpublished manuscripts
about women in prison.  In 1986 she helped establish the Children of Bedford Fund, which pays
school tuition for children whose mother's are incarcerated.  After her release from prison Mrs. Harris worked for the Children of Bedford Fund and continued to write.  Jean Harris died on December 23, 2012.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The Jean Harris Papers consist of  correspondence; clippings; printed material; research
material on correctional systems; writings; legal documents; memorabilia; audiotapes; video tapes
(of television interviews); and her trial record.   The vast majority of the materials date from
1980.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance
notice.</item>
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works of Jean Harris
within this collection.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those
individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or
quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy
the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Jean Struven Harris Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton,
Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>Jean Struven Harris donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection b from 1984 to
2005.</p>
</acqinfo>

<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Murder -- New York (State)</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women prisoners -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Bedford Hills Correctional Facility (N.Y.)</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Harris, Jean (Jean Struven)</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Tarnower, Herman</persname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Children of women prisoners -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Law -- United States -- History -- 20th century</subject>


</controlaccess>
<!-- add links where needed -->
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material in <extref href="mnsss541_main.html">Jean Harris Defense Fund and Committee Records</extref>.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead>
