<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss578.xml//EN">mnsss578</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin Papers, 1890-2008</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Megan G. Yeo.</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2015">2015</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Jasmine Jones. 
		<date normal="2015-06-02">2015-06-02</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	  </langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Garvin, Ida Belle Gwynn</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin Papers</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1890-2008</unitdate>
	
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 623</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">1</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">( linear ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">English</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin was a homemaker and homesteader, born in 1869. The Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin Papers is comprised of letters from Ida Gwynn Garvin to her mother, Adaline Gwynn, as well as biographical information and photographs of the Gwynn and Garvin families and letters from Ida Gwynn Garvin's daughters. 
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->

    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>	Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin was born October 4, 1869, in Jefferson Township, Ohio, to farmers Adaline Root and Ira Gwynn. She married farmer Norman S. Garvin and settled first in Richland Township, then Hale Township, Ohio.  The Garvins had seven children: Gwynn (b. 1898), Juanita (b. 1900), Irma (b. 1903), Gage (b. 1906), Daniel (b. 1909), Amer (b. 1913) and Edwin (b. 1914). Ida Garvin seems to have been widowed not long after the birth of her last child, although there is conflicting information about her husband's date of death.</p>

<p>Garvin contracted tuberculosis, and in 1916 spent time in Nob Hill Lodge Sanitarium in Colorado Springs, Colorado, leaving the children in the care of her mother. Her doctors recommended moving to a dry climate, so she conceived the idea of homesteading in Montana, not far from her brother, John Gwynn in Chouteau County.  In late 1916 Garvin signed papers to take over a relinquished property near Loma, Montana. She lived on the property with her children until February 1918, when illness forced her to move in with her brother and sister-in-law in Loma.  From that time, Garvin moved back and forth between Loma and the homestead, depending on her health and on the severity of the weather, perfecting her claim to the property on June 12, 1920. Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin died in the hospital at Fort Benton, Montana, on January 29, 1921.</p>

    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="scope">
	<head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
<p>	The Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin Papers primarily consist of letters from Ida Gwynn Garvin to her mother, Adaline Gwynn.  The letters span the years 1916 (when Garvin was hospitalized for tuberculosis at a sanatorium in Colorado Springs, Colorado), through 1920 (three months before she died), when she and her children attempted homesteading on a claim near Loma, Montana.  The Papers also include some biographical information about and photographs of the Gwynn and Garvin families and a couple of letters by Ida Gwynn Garvin's daughters. </p>

<p>Ida Garvin's letters were part of the research for Marcia Meredith Hensley's book, <title render="italic">Staking Her Claim: Women Homesteading the West</title> (High Plains Press, 2008).</p>

    </scopecontent>

<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->

    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.  </p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to unpublished works in this collection created by Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin.  Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns.  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.  Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>Faith Mullen, great-granddaughter of Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin, donated the Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin Papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2008. </p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Megan Yeo, April 3, 2015.</p> 
    </processinfo>


<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->

    <controlaccess id="subj">
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Montana -- History -- Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Tuberculosis -- Hospitals -- Colorado -- Colorado Springs -- History</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">West (U.S.) -- History -- 1890-1945 -- Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- West (U.S.) - History</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="local">Garvin, Ida Belle Gwynn, 1869-1921</persname> 
	<famname encodinganalog="600" source="local">Garvin family</famname>
	<famname encodinganalog="600" source="local">Gwynn family</famname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="local">Nob Hill Lodge Sanatorium (Colorado Springs, Colo.)</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Frontier and pioneer life -- West (U.S.)</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Social life and conditions</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- West (U.S.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="700" source="local">Gwynn, Adaline Root</persname> 


    </controlaccess>

<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->

<!-- End additional information -->


<!-- Enter Series descriptions -->

<!-- End Series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->

<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Biographical material and photographs of Garvin and Gwynn families <unitdate>circa 1890-2008</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Juanita Garvin to her grandmother, Adaline Gwynn<unitdate> 1921</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Irma (Garvin) Gordon to Juanita (Garvin) Young<unitdate> 1965</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4-10</container>
 <unittitle>Ida Belle Gwynn Garvin to her mother, Adaline Gwynn<unitdate> 1908-20</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>
<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
