<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
   <eadheader audience="internal" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b">
      <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss22.xml//EN">mnsss22</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Portia Willis Fitzgerald Papers, 1868-1966
        </titleproper>
            <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
            <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Amy Hague.</author>
            <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            <date encodinganalog="260$c">2003 </date>
            <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded using Perl scripts and edited in XMetal 2.0. Encoded by Brook Hopkins.
        <date>2003-06-05</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
         </langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2005-09-23">2005-09-23</date>
            <item>mnsss22 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02-5c.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter id="front">
      <titlepage>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb />Smith College
        <lb />
            
         </publisher>
         <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Portia Willis Fitzgerald Papers, 1868-1966
      </titleproper>
         <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
         <num>MS 380
      </num>
         <author encodinganalog="245$c">Amy Hague
      </author>
         <date>1998
      </date>
         
         <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         <p>© 2003  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did id="main">
         <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Fitzgerald, Portia Willis</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Portia Willis Fitzgerald papers</unittitle><unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1868-1966</unitdate>
            <unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1910-1935</unitdate>
         <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 380</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Quantity:">
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(.25 linear ft.)</extent>
         </physdesc>
                  <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
	  </repository>
         <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Woman's club leader, suffragist and lecturer. Much of the collection appears to have been part of a scrapbook. Writings and speeches primarily relate to her father (Colonel and U.S. Representative Benjamin A. Willis), the League of Nations, suffrage, the Institute of Human Relations, and women's clubs. Correspondents include Gertrude Atherton, Carrie Chapman Catt, and Florence G. Tuttle.
      </abstract>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
            <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <bioghist id="bioghist">
         <head>Biographical Note</head>
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc3230.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>Portia Willis Fitzgerald, 1915</p></daodesc></dao>
         <p>"The Prettiest Suffragette in New York State," Portia Willis was born to a well-connected and politically active New York City family, circa 1887.  The distinguished Civil War service of her father, Colonel Benjamin A. Willis, led to his election to the U.S. House of Representatives.  Her mother, Lillie Evelynn Macauley Willis was prominent in the New York City social scene.</p>
         <p>Portia Willis attended the Anne Brown School and took courses at Columbia University and Harvard.  She became active in the women's suffrage movement in the early 1910s as a speaker and writer campaigning for New York State suffrage.  She was an organizer of the New York State Suffrage Association.  Her visible participation in suffrage publicity events, including piloting an airplane that bombarded Long Island with suffrage leaflets, sparked as many references to her beauty as to her cause in the press.  Between 1911 and 1917 she took a very active part in the campaign, conducting a lecture tour through New York State, making speeches for the woman suffrage amendment in Massachusetts in 1914, and in New Jersey and Washington, D.C. the following year.  She was grand marshal for three suffrage parades.  In 1931 New York State placed her name on the suffrage "Honor Rolls" at the State Capitol in Albany.</p>
         <p>In 1925 Willis married Captain L. Rodney Berg, an emigre from Lancashire, England, who worked in real estate.  After her marriage she changed her name to Portia Willis-Berg.  L. Rodney Berg died in 1941.  Her second husband was the Prince of Thurn and Taxis who also pre-deceased her.  In 1958 she married her third husband, Gerald Purcell FitzGerald.</p>
         <p>Portia Willis FitzGerald was involved in many organizations throughout her life.  She was an active pacifist, acting as Grand Marshal for the Women's Peace Parade in 1914, and later working in support of the League of Nations in the Women's Pro-League Council.  She was a founder and board member of the Greater New York Branch of the League of Nations Association and a member of the New York Board of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom.  She was chairman of the Round Table on the United Nations from 1950-53.</p>
         <p>FitzGerald was a founding member of the Women's Roosevelt Memorial Association and was made an honorary member of the Aerial League of America for services to airmen in World War I.  She also devoted much attention to Red Cross work during World War I.  In 1925 she was elected to the National Institute of Social Sciences (for social work).  She was also a member of the Women's City Club and a vice-president of the Woman's Suffrage Study Club.  She served as president of the Little Gardens Club of New York City from 1953 on and was also at one time vice-president of the Women's Farm and Garden Association.</p>
         <p>FitzGerald had been a popular lecturer on public affairs since her involvement in the suffrage movement and was briefly an Assistant in the Oral English Department at Harvard in 1924.  She was also a lecturer on current events at the Barmore School from 1948-50.  In her later years she continued to lecture and was frequently asked to reminisce about her suffrage experiences.  The exact date of her death is unknown.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="scope">
         <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
         <p>The Portia Willis FitzGerald Papers consist of .25 linear feet and are primarily related to her suffrage activism, although quite a few items relate to her family.  Much of the collection appears to have been part of a scrapbook and reflects the selective nature of such a compilation.  This is far from a complete set of papers.  Types of material include correspondence, speeches, writings, photographs, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
         <head>Organization of the Collection</head>
         <p>This collection is organized into four series:</p>
         <list>
            <item>
               <ref target="list-ser1">I. Biographical Material</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="list-ser2">II. Correspondence</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="list-ser3">III. Writings and Speeches</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="list-ser4">IV. Memorabilia and Printed Material</ref>
            </item>
         </list>
      </arrangement>
      <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
         <head>Information on Use</head>
         <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
               <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to unpublished works of Portia Willis Fitzgerald. Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission must be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."
           </p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
               <p>All rights are owned by the Sophia Smith Collection and permission is required for publication beyond "fair use".
            </p>
            </userestrict>
         </descgrp>
         <prefercite id="admin-cite">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
            <p>Portia Willis Fitzgerald Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, MA</p>
         </prefercite>
         <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>History of the Collection</head>
            <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
               <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by FitzGerald's great niece, Kate Earle Funk (Smith '63) in 1998.
            </p>
            </acqinfo>
             <processinfo id="admin-process">
               <p>Processed by Amy Hague, 1998.</p>
            </processinfo>
         </descgrp>
      </descgrp>
      <controlaccess id="subj">
         <head>Search Terms</head>
         
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Societies and clubs--United States--History--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Suffrage--New York (State)--History--Sources</subject>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Atherton, Gertrude Franklin Horn, 1857-1948</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947</persname>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">New York State Woman Suffrage Party--History--Sources</corpname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Seton, Anya</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Tuttle, Florence Guertin</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Willis, Benjamin A.</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <!-- Begin series descriptions -->

<dsc type="analyticover">
  <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
               <unitdate>(1868-1958, n.d.)</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
               <p>This series consists mostly of newspaper clippings about Portia Willis and members of her family, especially her father, Benjamin A. Willis.  The series also includes a program for Fanny Garrison Villard's memorial service.  A small collection of photographs relate primarily to FitzGerald's suffrage career, but there are also later portraits and one photograph of the Astor Family.</p>
            </scopecontent>

 </c01>
  <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
               <unitdate>(1876-1966,n.d.)</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
               <p>Letters from suffrage and other professional associates to Portia Willis FitzGerald make up the bulk of this series.  They are arranged by individual correspondent, among them Gertrude Atherton, Carrie Chapman Catt, and Florence G. Tuttle, followed by a folder of general, more routine incoming correspondence.  There is also a handful of letters to her parents from others.</p>
            </scopecontent>

 </c01>
  <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES
               <unitdate>(1878-1935, n.d.)</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
               <p>Articles and speeches by FitzGerald form the bulk of this series.  They relate to her father, the League of Nations, the Institute of Human Relations, women's clubs, and other topics.  There are also two speeches made by her father in 1878 and 1879.</p>
            </scopecontent>

 </c01>
  <c01 level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES IV. MEMORABILIA AND PRINTED MATERIAL
               <unitdate>(1862-1960, n.d.)</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <scopecontent>
               <p>This series contains miscellaneous programs, certificates, invitations, and suffrage memorabilia and publications.</p>
            </scopecontent>

 </c01>

</dsc>
<!-- End series descriptions -->

<!-- Begin container list -->

<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
         <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle>L. Rodney Berg (first husband): obituary, <unitdate>[1941?]</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Van Rensselaer, Mrs. Cortlandt (aunt): obituary, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Fanny Garrison Villard: memorial service program,<unitdate> 1928</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">4</container>
                  <unittitle>Benjamin A. Willis (father): articles and memorabilia,<unitdate> 1868-78, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">5</container>
                  <unittitle>Benjamin A. Willis (brother): obituary, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Portia Willis FitzGerald</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Articles</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">6</container>
                        <unittitle>
                           <unitdate>1913-58, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">7</container>
                        <unittitle>Miscellaneous fragments,<unitdate> 1915-54, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">8</container>
                        <unittitle>Portraits and suffrage related,<unitdate> 1914-31, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">9</container>
                        <unittitle>The Astor family, Cliveden,<unitdate> 1922</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">10</container>
                  <unittitle>Benjamin A. Willis and Lillie Macauley Willis,<unitdate> 1876-86, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Portia Willis FitzGerald</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Friends and associates</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">11</container>
                        <unittitle>Atherton, Gertrude,<unitdate> 1927</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">12</container>
                        <unittitle>Catt, Carrie Chapman,<unitdate> 1927</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">13</container>
                        <unittitle>Chase, Anya Seton,<unitdate> 1957</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">14</container>
                        <unittitle>Cosgrave, [Louie?],<unitdate> 1925</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">15</container>
                        <unittitle>Laidlaw, [Harriet?],<unitdate> 1915</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">16</container>
                        <unittitle>Simonson, May, <unitdate>1931</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">17</container>
                        <unittitle>Tuttle, Florence G.,<unitdate> 1924</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">18</container>
                     <unittitle>General,<unitdate> 1924-66, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES</unittitle>
            </did>

            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">19</container>
                  <unittitle>Benjamin A. Willis,<unitdate> 1878-79</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">20</container>
                  <unittitle>Portia Willis FitzGerald,<unitdate> 1925-35, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>SERIES IV. MEMORABILIA AND PRINTED MATERIAL</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">21</container>
                  <unittitle>The Woman Voter, <unitdate>Feb 1912 and Jun 1913</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">22</container>
                  <unittitle>Programs,<unitdate> 1913-35</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">23</container>
                  <unittitle>Memorabilia,<unitdate> 1873-1960, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="map-case">Flat File:</container>
                  <unittitle>Benjamin A. Willis, New York State Volunteers certificate,<unitdate> 1862</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="map-case">Flat File:</container>
                  <unittitle>Suffrage poster, "Speaker, Miss Portia H. Willis" (fragment), <unitdate>n.d. </unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>