<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss467.xml//EN">mnsss467</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Eve Hinderer Papers, 1967-2012 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>

     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">June 23, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Hinderer, Eve, 1947-</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Eve Hinderer Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1967-2012 (ongoing)</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 403</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">5 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(2.25 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Feminist; Anarchist; Bisexual; founding member of New York Radical Women in New York City, 1960s. The Eve Hinderer Papers contain journals and diaries, correspondence, email, writings, clipppings and photographs. 
 
                 </abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
     <p>Eve Hinderer was born in New York City, August 25, 1947.  During her first year at City College of New York, she was introduced to socialist and other left-wing groups.  At the same time her life at home with a verbally abusive father had reached a crisis and at the age of 17 in 1965, she became a runaway.  She eventually went to live with her godmother in Daytona Beach, Florida. There she experienced her first bout of mental illness. After three months she returned home and to school, but after about a year she was suffering from panic attacks and anxiety and was ready to enter therapy for the first time. At that time, she had become involved with the New York Federation of Anarchists. "In its' emphasis on personal transformation as the starting point for revolutionary theory and practice, anarchism resolved my conflict between the left's concern for justice and the libertarian emphasis on the individual. I took refuge in the tenets of anarchism..."  She also became active in the nascent women's movement  in the Fall of 1967 and was a founding member of New York Radical Women in New York until the summer of 1968, when she organized a second consciousness raising group with Judith Duffett. While she was traveling around the country that summer, new women continued to join the group including feminist Robin Morgan. By that Fall, a new and much larger group continued to meet at the Southern Christian Leadership Conference office on East 11th street in New York City. Hinderer soon after dropped out of the movement, feeling strongly about the importance of small-group interaction as an organizing tool. In 1971, she joined the emerging gay liberation movement, becoming active in the lesbian separatist community in New York's lower Manhattan. She withdrew three years later, acknowledging her bisexuality.  Hinderer received a B.A. in Fine Arts from Brooklyn College in 1985. She has survived recurring bouts of mental illness. She currently lives in Newburgh, N.Y.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The Eve Hinderer Papers contain journals and diaries (circa 1967-2008), correspondence, email, writings, clippings and photographs. Diary entries are highly self-reflective, and are for the most part daily, including periods of depression and mental instability in Hinderer's life.  Recent diaries (circa 2004- ) are in electronic form (MS Word) and printouts of electronic files. </p>
     </scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>This collection is closed - 
                    <extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/list#contact">Contact the SSC</extref> for more information.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Eve Hinderer Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Eve Hinderer in 2000.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>This collection has not been fully processed.</p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Bisexuality-United States-History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Communists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs--20th century--Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Mental health--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Hinderer, Eve, 1947-</persname> 
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
