<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
   <eadheader audience="internal" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b">
      <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss62.xml//EN">mnsss62</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders Papers, 1914-1997 (bulk 1928-1960)
        </titleproper>
            <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
            <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Margaret Jessup.</author>
            <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            <date encodinganalog="260$c">2003 </date>
            <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded using Perl scripts and edited in XMetal 2.0. Encoded by Brook Hopkins.
        <date>2003-06-06</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2005-09-23">2005-09-23</date>
            <item>mnsss62 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02-5c.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter id="front">
      <titlepage>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb/>Smith College
        <lb/>
            
         </publisher>
         <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders Papers, 1914-1997 (bulk 1928-1960)
      </titleproper>
         <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
         <num>MS 247
      </num>
         <author encodinganalog="245$c">Margaret Jessup
      </author>
         <date>1993
      </date>
         
         <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         <p>© 2003  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did id="main">
         <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Saunders, Mildred Louise (Boie), 1907-</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Mildred Louise Boie Saunders papers</unittitle><unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1914-1997</unitdate>
            <unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk"> 1928-1960</unitdate>
         
         <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 247</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Quantity:">
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">4 boxes</extent>
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1.5 linear ft.)</extent>
         </physdesc>
                  <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
	  </repository>
         <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Poet; editor; professor, English; and Red Cross worker, World War II.  Collection is primarily personal correspondence, including  a lifetime of letters to her twin sister, which read as a personal journal and document her career, romances, family relations, experiences in psychoanalysis, and world events.  Other material includes photographs; writings; a travel diary from a trip to Europe; and reports to the Red Cross from Italy and Egypt during World War II.
      </abstract>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
            <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <bioghist id="bioghist">
         
         <p>Mildred Louise Boie (called Louise) and her twin sister, Maurine Boie, were born in Plainville, Minnesota on May 20, 1907.  Louise attended Mankato Teachers College, then earned her B.S. degree in Education from the University of Minnesota in 1927.  From 1927 to 1929, she worked in the creative department for the Harrison-Guthrie Advertising Agency in Minneapolis, and also edited a magazine for the C. &amp; C. Publishing Company.  In 1930 Louise went to England for a year, where she studied modern English literature at Newnham College, University of Cambridge, and wrote articles for the London Morning Post and the Spectator.  When she returned to the United States she took a position as instructor and head of extension classes in English at the University of Minnesota until 1934, when she received her Masters degree in English from the University.  Her thesis is entitled Louisa May Alcott.  Also in 1934, Louise was awarded the M.P. Sears and F.Z. Gilbert Fellowship in creative work from Radcliffe College and spent the next year studying there.</p>
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc6161.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>Mildred Louise Boie Saunders <lb/>and others on balcony, circa 1940s </p></daodesc></dao> 
         <p>From 1935 to 1937, Louise served as assistant professor of English at Smith College.  She left Smith in 1937 to be associate editor of poetry for the Atlantic Monthly in Boston, under editor Ted Weeks.  She remained there until 1940 when she took a position as publicity head for the American Unitarian Association and Service Committee, organizing humanitarian work in Europe and America, and serving as editor for their publication, the Christian Register.  During this time Louise also edited books for Bacon Press.  Sometime in the late 1930s, while living in Boston, Louise began psychoanalysis with Dr. Leslia Dalrymple.</p>
         <p>Feeling that she needed something more stimulating and rewarding in her life, in 1943 Louise applied for overseas work with the American Red Cross and, until 1946, was stationed at various United States Army bases in France, Italy, and Egypt, where she assisted in civilian relief.  She was awarded the Bronze Star by the United States Army for her service.  While overseas, Louise wrote several articles and short stories about her experiences which were published in various journals, including Ladies Home Journal, Glamour, and Radcliffe Quartery.  In 1946, her book of poems, Better Than Laughter was published by the University of Minnesota Press.</p>
         <p>In 1948, Louise married Lt. Colonel William (Bill) Saunders and moved to Fort Bragg in North Carolina, where Bill was chief engineer.  After a series of health problems, Bill received an honorable discharge and they moved off base into the city of Fayetteville, where he found work as an architect.</p>
         <p>Louise was active in numerous community services in Fayetteville.  She did volunteer work for the United Services Fund, the Red Cross, the Mental Health Association, and served on the board of the County Guidance Center Advisory Council.  During the 1970s and 80s Louise was executive director of the Cumberland County Council on Older Adults.  In 1991, when the Sophia Smith Collection received her papers, Louise was living with Maurine and Weston LaBarre at the Carol Woods Retirement Village in Chapel Hill, North Carolina.</p>
         <p>Although both Louise and her twin, Maurine, were active career women and travelled frequently, usually living in different cities, they always remained extremely close and corresponded regularly, sometimes on a weekly basis.  Maurine Boie received her Masters in Social Work from Bryn Mawr in 1934, and thereafter she alternately taught and practiced social work in New York, Pennsylvania, and North Carolina.  During the late 1930s and early 40s, she was editor-in-chief of the The Family, journal of the Family Welfare Association of America in New York City, and in 1943 she wrote the New York Baby Book which was given to every new mother in the city.</p>
         <p>In 1939, Maurine married Weston LaBarre and they eventually moved to Durham, North Carolina.  There she helped start the Durham Child Guidance Clinic and was founder of the Durham School for Pregnant School Girls.  In 1960, Maurine was appointed assistant professor of Psychiatric Social Work at Duke University, where Weston LaBarre also taught, and in 1971 she returned to psychiatric social work at the Duke University Medical Center.</p>
	<p>Louise's sister, Maurine Boie LeBarre, died on September 16, 1991 in Chapel Hill, North Carolina. Louise Boie Saunders died on November 10, 1997 in Goldsboro, North Carolina.</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="scope">
         
         <p>The Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders Papers consist of 1.5 linear feet (four document boxes) of correspondence, published writings, manuscripts, diaries, photographs, and memorabilia, dating from 1914 to 1978.  The bulk of the material dates from 1928 to 1960.</p>
         <p>Half of the collection (two document boxes) contain Louise's letters to her twin sister, Maurine, dating from 1928 to the 1960s.  The letters serve as Louise's personal journal, in which she shares with her sister intimate reflections on her life, including family relationships, her romances, her experience in psychoanalysis, her observations of world events (especially of World War II), thoughts about her career, her writing, and books she's read.  The letters offer an in-depth look at the daily life of a single, working woman in the 1920s, 30s, and 40s, written by a talented and very thoughtful writer.  The rest of the correspondence (one document box) includes letters to and from other family members, friends, and colleagues of both Louise and Maurine.</p>
         <p>Louise's writings fill half a box and consist of published magazine and newspaper articles, book reviews, and poems, including her book, Better Than Laughter.  The writings also include typescripts of articles, poems, and short stories, dating from 1926 to 1944.  Some of these relate to her work with the Red Cross.  Included with her writings are a travel journal from a 1930 trip to Europe (including photographs) and a few pages of journal entries describing her Red Cross work during World War II.</p>
         <p>The remainder of the collection (half a document box) consists of biographical material relating to Louise and Maurine, newspaper clippings, memorabilia, and photographs.</p>
      </scopecontent>
      <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
         
         <p>The papers are arranged in four series: </p>
         <list>
            <item>
               <ref target="list-ser1">I. Biographical </ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="list-ser2">II. Photographs</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="list-ser3">III. Writings (of Mildred Louise Boie)</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
               <ref target="list-ser4">IV. Correspondence</ref>
            </item>
         </list>
      </arrangement>
      <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
         <head>Information on Use</head>
         <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
               <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any added restrictions.  </p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
               <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the papers of the Mildred Louise and Maurine Saunders. Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission must be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."
           </p>
            </userestrict>
         </descgrp>
         <prefercite id="admin-cite">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
            <p>Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
         </prefercite>
         <descgrp type="admininfo">
            <head>History of the Collection</head>
            <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
               <p>Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders' papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in several installments, from 1991 to 1993, by her sister Maurine's husband, Weston LaBarre.  </p>
            </acqinfo>
             <processinfo id="admin-process">
               <p>Processed by Margaret Jessup, 1993.</p>
            </processinfo>
         </descgrp>
      </descgrp>
      <controlaccess id="subj">
         <head>Search Terms</head>
         
         <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">American Universalist Society--History</corpname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Saunders, Mildred Louise (Boie), 1907-</persname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sisters--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Twins--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1939-1945--War work--Red Cross--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">World War, 1939-1945--Women--Personal narratives, American</subject>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Bates, H.E. (Herbert Ernest), 1905-1974</persname>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">Atlantic Monthly--History</corpname>
         <famname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Boie family</famname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women poets--20th century</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women editors--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women and psychoanalysis--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in the professions--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
         <persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">LaBarre, Maurine Boie, 1907-</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <descgrp id="addinfo" type="add">
         <head>Additional Information</head>
         <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
            <head>Related Material</head>
            <p>The archives of the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis also has some of Louise's published writings and copies of both Louise's and Maurine's masters theses.  The archives at Bryn Mawr College hold some of the papers of Maurine (Boie) LaBarre.</p>
         </relatedmaterial>
      </descgrp>
      <dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
         <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series I. Biographical</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">1</container>
                     <unittitle>Clippings re: M.L.B.S.,<unitdate> 1935-83, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">2</container>
                     <unittitle>Documents: passport,<unitdate> 1942</unitdate>; will, <unitdate>1955</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">3</container>
                     <unittitle>Boie-Stephan family genealogy, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">4</container>
                     <unittitle>Awards,<unitdate> 1963-78, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">5</container>
                     <unittitle>Memorabilia,<unitdate> 1914-73, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">6</container>
                     <unittitle>Red Cross activities: reports,<unitdate> 1944-45, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">7</container>
                  <unittitle>Maurine (Boie) LaBarre: resume and memorabilia,<unitdate> 1929-76, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">8</container>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous clippings,<unitdate> 1939-60, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series II. Photographs</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders</unittitle>
               </did>
		<note><p>[See also Oversize.]</p></note>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">9</container>
                     <unittitle>M.L.B.S. alone,<unitdate> 1942-58, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">1</container>
                     <container type="folder">10</container>
                     <unittitle>M.L.B.S. with others,<unitdate> 1936-58, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Red Cross activities, <unitdate>ca.                    1940s</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">11</container>
                        <unittitle>Egypt</unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">12</container>
                        <unittitle>Italy</unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">1</container>
                        <container type="folder">13</container>
                        <unittitle>General</unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">14</container>
                  <unittitle>Family, friends, miscellaneous,<unitdate> 1949, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">15</container>
                  <unittitle>Album of unidentified people in China, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">16</container>
                  <unittitle>Postcards (blank), <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series III. Writings (Mildred Louise Boie)</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">2</container>
                  <container type="folder">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Travel journal (Europe) with photos,<unitdate> 1930</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">2</container>
                  <container type="folder">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Writings about Red Cross activities, <unitdate>ca. 1944</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">2</container>
                  <container type="folder">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Published articles, book reviews, and poems,<unitdate> 1926-1942, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">2</container>
                  <container type="folder">4</container>
                  <unittitle>
                     <title>Better Than Laughter</title>, poems by Mildred Louise Boie</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Manuscripts</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Articles and stories</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">2</container>
                        <container type="folder">5</container>
                        <unittitle>"An American's Farewell to England," <unitdate>ca. 1931</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">2</container>
                        <container type="folder">6</container>
                        <unittitle>"Do American Men Spoil Their Wives?" <unitdate>ca. 1931</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">2</container>
                        <container type="folder">7</container>
                        <unittitle>"We Keep House for You Boys,"<unitdate> 1944</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">2</container>
                        <container type="folder">8</container>
                        <unittitle>"Homesickness," <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">2</container>
                        <container type="folder">9</container>
                        <unittitle>"Please Communicate At Once," <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">2</container>
                     <container type="folder">10-14</container>
                     <unittitle>Reviews,<unitdate> 1937-40, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">2</container>
                     <container type="folder">15</container>
                     <unittitle>Poems,<unitdate> 1934, 1941, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series IV. Correspondence</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <unittitle>Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders to</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Family</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04 id="list-toj.l.">
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">3</container>
                        <unittitle>Maurine (Boie) LaBarre,<unitdate> 1928-1939</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">4</container>
                        <unittitle>Maurine (Boie) LaBarre,<unitdate> 1940-1960s, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">1</container>
                        <unittitle>Group letters to family,<unitdate> 1936, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">2</container>
                        <unittitle>Edith (Stephan) Boie,<unitdate> 1936-37, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">3</container>
                        <unittitle>Emil Boie,<unitdate> 1943</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">4</container>
                        <unittitle>Isabelle (Boie) Westby, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">5</container>
                        <unittitle>Luther Boie,<unitdate> 1939</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">6</container>
                        <unittitle>John LaBarre,<unitdate> 1946</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">7</container>
                        <unittitle>Weston LaBarre,<unitdate> 1939, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                     <note>
                        <p>
                           <ref target="list-tomaurine">[See also letters to Maurine]</ref>
                        </p>
                     </note>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">5</container>
                     <container type="folder">8</container>
                     <unittitle>Friends and associates,<unitdate> 1945-46</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <unittitle>To Louise (Boie) Saunders from</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Family</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">9</container>
                        <unittitle>Edith (Stephan) Boie,<unitdate> 1925-47, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">10</container>
                        <unittitle>Isabelle (Boie) Westby,<unitdate> 1944-86, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">11</container>
                        <unittitle>Luther ("Toby") and Ruth Boie,<unitdate> 1946, 1986, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">12</container>
                        <unittitle>Maurine (Boie) LaBarre,<unitdate> 1954-86, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Friends and associates</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">13-14</container>
                        <unittitle>George Allen,<unitdate> 1936-38, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">15-17</container>
                        <unittitle>Richard (H.E.) Bates,<unitdate> 1938-39, n.d. </unitdate>[inc. "Every Bullet Has its Billet," mss. by H.E. Bates, <unitdate>ca. 1938</unitdate>]</unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">18</container>
                        <unittitle>Harriet Beale,<unitdate> 1946, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">19</container>
                        <unittitle>Other friends and associates,<unitdate> 1928-90, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">20</container>
                        <unittitle>Professional,<unitdate> 1927-67, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <unittitle>To Maurine (Boie) and Weston LaBarre from</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Family</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">21</container>
                        <unittitle>Edith and Emil Boie,<unitdate> 1928-56, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">22</container>
                        <unittitle>Isabelle (Boie) Westby,<unitdate> 1932, 1936, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">23</container>
                        <unittitle>Luther ("Toby") Boie,<unitdate> 1935, 1944</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">24</container>
                        <unittitle>Ruth Boie,<unitdate> 1955, 1957</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">25</container>
                        <unittitle>Mrs. Artie LaBarre (Weston's mother),<unitdate> 1956</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">26</container>
                        <unittitle>William Saunders,<unitdate> 1960</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">27</container>
                        <unittitle>Other family,<unitdate> 1926, 1946, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02 id="list-tomaurine">
               <did>
                  <unittitle>To Maurine (Boie) and Weston LaBarre from</unittitle>
               </did>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <unittitle>Friends and associates</unittitle>
                  </did>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">28</container>
                        <unittitle>Harriet Beale,<unitdate> 1928-50, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">29</container>
                        <unittitle>O. Spurgeon English,<unitdate> 1940-58</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">30</container>
                        <unittitle>Chauncey Wu,<unitdate> 1932, 1936</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
                  <c04>
                     <did>
                        <container type="box">5</container>
                        <container type="folder">31-32</container>
                        <unittitle>Other friends,<unitdate> 1926-60, n.d.</unitdate>
                        </unittitle>
                     </did>
                  </c04>
               </c03>
               <c03>
                  <did>
                     <container type="box">5</container>
                     <container type="folder">33</container>
                     <unittitle>Professional,<unitdate> 1937-43, n.d.</unitdate>
                     </unittitle>
                  </did>
               </c03>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">5</container>
                  <container type="folder">34</container>
                  <unittitle>To John LaBarre from family,<unitdate> 1946, n.d.</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
               <note>
                  <p>
                     <ref target="list-toj.l.">[See also Louise (Boie) Saunders to J.L.]</ref>
                  </p>
               </note>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01 id="list-serOV" level="series">
            <did>
               <unittitle>Series V. Oversize Material</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
		<container type="map-case">Flat file drawer 35</container>
                  <unittitle>Portrait of Mildred Louise (Boie) Saunders, watercolor on board <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
               </did>
	    </c02>
	</c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
