<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss491.xml//EN">mnsss491</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Choice USA Records, 1980s-
2005 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd
Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith
Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2009">2009</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 12.0. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">July 26, 2010</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Choice USA (Washington,
 D.C.)</persname>
        </origination>
        <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Choice USA
 Records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1980s-2005
 (ongoing)</unitdate>
       <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 575</unitid>
   <physdesc label="Quantity:">
           <extent encodinganalog="300$a">4 boxes</extent>
           <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(4.75 linear ft.) </extent>
   </physdesc>

   <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
   </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
             <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
             <address>
                <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
                <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
             </address>
          </repository>
           <!-- MRJ Edit as needed-->
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Reproductive rights advocacy group. Records contain correspondence, publications,
publicity materials, press releases and clippings, photographs, website images, reports, polls,
financial information, and Board of Directors minutes, and other materials.  They document the
organization's history and work for the preservation of a woman's right to choose by way of media
campaigns, voter registration initiatives, educational outreach to young adults, and endorsing pro-
choice candidates for political office.

        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

   </did>

    <!--  Add paragraph marks to text -->
   <bioghist id="bioghist">
          <head>Historical Note</head>
        <p>Choice USA was founded in 1992 by Gloria Steinem as Voters for Choice and serves to
   mobilize and provide ongoing support to the upcoming generation of leaders who promote and
   protect reproductive choice. The organization's first projects analyzed the activities of the
   religious right in elections and promoted electoral participation by women, young people, and
   people of color. In 1996, responding to signs that young people's support for reproductive
   choice had declined compared to previous generations and that young supporters of choice were
   disconnected from the pro-choice movement, Choice USA created the Next Generation Campaign which
   focused its work exclusively on teenagers and young people. National in scope, Choice USA's
   programs address the pressing need for pro-choice messages, programs, and strategies tailored to
   engage young people, whose experiences differ markedly (socially and politically) from the
   generation of reproductive rights activists who fought to see Roe v. Wade passed in 1973.  In
   2001, Choice USA laid the groundwork for transitioning to become an exclusively youth-led and
   youth-focused reproductive rights organization, creating programs that incorporate the lessons
   learned from research (and validated by field experience) to regain young people's support.
   Choice USA programs reach young people in every region of the country. Gloria Steinem currently
   serves as the President of the Board of Directors.  Crystal Plati is Executive Director.</p> 

<p>For more information, see
<extref href="http://www.choiceusa.org/">Choice USA Web site</extref>.</p>

   </bioghist>
   <!--  Add paragraph marks to text -->
  <scopecontent id="scope">
        <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
       <p>Records contain correspondence, publications, publicity materials, press releases and
  clippings, photographs, website images, reports, polls, financial information, and Board of
  Directors minutes, and other materials.  They document the organization's history and work for
  the preservation of a woman's right to choose by way of media campaigns, voter registration
  initiatives, educational outreach to young adults, and endorsing pro-choice candidates for
  political office.</p>
         <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
  Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

  </scopecontent>
   <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                      <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the
  Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                      <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
  difficult to use.</p>
                       <p> Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</p>
  </accessrestrict>

  <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
               <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
  </userestrict>
  <prefercite id="admin-cite">
          <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this
  collection:</p>
            <p>Choice USA Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton,
  Mass.</p>
  </prefercite>

  <accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
                 <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be
  reflected in this record.</p>
  </accruals>
  <!-- MRJ:  Edit donor info as necessary -->
  <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
            <p>The Choice USA Records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by
  the organization in 2007.</p>
  </acqinfo>
  <!-- Edit Processing date if necessary- year only -->
  <processinfo id="admin-process">
            <p>Accessioned by Burd Schlessinger, 2007 </p>
  </processinfo>
  <!-- Encode Subject terms -->
  <controlaccess id="subj">
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abortion  --  Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abortion -- Political aspects -- History -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abortion -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Birth control -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reproductive health -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reproductive rights -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in politics -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
      	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Steinem, Gloria</persname> 
      	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Choice USA (Washington, D.C.) -- History -- Sources</corpname> 
      	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Voters for Choice (Washington, D.C.) -- History -- Sources</corpname> 

  </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->