<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss419.xml//EN">mnsss419</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Carrie Eliza Meares Papers, 1932-1982 (bulk 1947-1963)</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Maida Goodwin.</author>
		<sponsor>Processing of the Carrie Eliza Meares Papers was made possible by the generous support of the National Historical Publications and Records Commission</sponsor> 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2009">2009</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Annie-Sage Whitehurst. 
		<date normal="2009-06-03">2009-06-03</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Meares, Carrie Eliza</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Carrie Eliza Meares papers</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1932-1982</unitdate>
	<unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1947-1963</unitdate>
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 610</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1.5 linear ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
	 YWCA worker. The Carrie Eliza Meares Papers are primarily related to her professional and public life.  Types of materials include correspondence, memorabilia, press releases, reports, journal and newspaper articles,  and subject files.  The bulk of the papersfocus on Meares' work in South  Africa for the World YWCA, 1950-53; in  Ethiopia for the YWCA of the U.S.A., 1960-61; and on the August 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom.   The papers include general background reference on South Africa, Ethiopia, and race relations, as well as correspondence, reports, financial records, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia from Meares' work.  In addition to official reports and correspondence, the files contain some personal correspondence with reflections on Meares' experiences in Africa.
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	
	<p>Carrie Eliza Meares was born January 28, 1899, in Fountain Inn, South Carolina.  She earned an A.B. in education from Winthrop College in Rock Hill, South Carolina in 1919.  After graduation, Meares spent two years teaching in the primary grades in the Rombert, South Carolina public schools, 1919-21. </p> 

<p>She went to New York City to study for a diploma in religious education at Biblical Seminary, 1921-23, then joined the staff of the YWCA at the Mississippi State College for Women.  She taught Bible at the College, 1923-25.  She returned to New York to attend Teachers College at Columbia University, 1925-26, earning an M.A. in religious education in 1926.  
</p>
<p>In 1926 Meares joined the national YWCA staff, working as a Student Secretary in the central region, 1926-28, and southern region, 1926-34.  Meares returned again to New York City to pursue a BS in library science at Pratt Institute.  She then served seven years as Librarian Consultant at Teachers College; and did additional graduate work in education at Columbia (1934-35), at Pratt Institute of Library Science, Brooklyn (1935-36), and Columbia University School of Library Science.  During this time she also worked half time as a Personnel Secretary and then a volunteer for the National Student Council of the YWCA.</p>

<p>From 1944 to 1948, Meares was Secretary for personnel standards and practices in the  Leadership Services Division of the YWCA of the U.S.A., working with community YWCAs to establish fair policies and procedures for their professional staff members.
</p>
<p>Meares joined the staff of the World YWCA in 1950, going to South  Africa to strengthen YWCAs in Durban and Port Elizabeth, extending the work of the YWCA among non-European groups, and promoting consolidation between European and non-European groups.  She also carried out exploratory service in Uganda and Kenya.
</p>
<p>On returning to the U.S., Meares became Executive Director first of the Baltimore YWCA, circa 1953-55, and then Rochester, circa 1955-60.  She returned to Africa circa 1960, under the auspices of the YWCA of the U.S.A.'s International Division as an Adult Education Specialist in Ethiopia.  </p>

<p>Meares served as National Director of Church Women United's "Assignment:  Race, 1961-64" program, a three-year project in race relations.  Meares retired from the YWCA in the summer of 1964.</p>

<p>Carrie Eliza Meares died April 14, 1982, at Foulkeways in Gwynedd, Pennsylvania.</p>

    </bioghist>

    <scopecontent id="scope">
	
	<p>The Carrie Eliza Meares Papers consist of .5 linear ft. and are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1932 to 1982.  Types of materials include correspondence, memorabilia, press releases, reports, journal and newspaper articles,  and subject files. </p> 


<p>The bulk of the papers date from 1947 to 1963 and focus on Meares' work in South  Africa for the World YWCA, 1950-53; in  Ethiopia for the YWCA of the U.S.A., 1960-61; and on the August 1963 March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom.</p>

<p>The Papers include general background reference on South Africa, Ethiopia, and race relations, as well as correspondence, reports, financial records, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia from Meares' work.  In addition to official reports and correspondence, the files contain some personal correspondence with reflections on Meares' experiences in Africa.</p>

    </scopecontent>


<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.  </p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."   Copyright ownership of Carrie Eliza Meares' writings is unknown.  Copyright to materials authored by persons other than Carrie Eliza Meares may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Carrie Eliza Meares Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>The Carrie Eliza Meares Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the Records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. in 2002.  The YWCA received them from Meares' longtime housemate Mildred Roe in 1985.</p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Maida Goodwin, 2009</p> 
    </processinfo>

<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
		<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Meares, Carrie Eliza, 1899-1982</persname>
   	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. -- History</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Young Women's Christian Associations -- Ethiopia</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Young Women's Christian Associations -- South Africa</subject>
</controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->

<!-- End additional information -->
    <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
	<p>Associated material located in the
	<extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss292_main.html">YWCA USA Records, Sophia Smith Collection</extref>.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>

<!-- Insert container list here:-->
<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>General<unitdate> 1933-82</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>General<unitdate> 1932-60</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>International Division, Adult Education Specialist, Ethiopia</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3-4</container>
 <unittitle>General<unitdate> 1960-61</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Reference materials<unitdate> 1957-75, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <unittitle>World Young Women's Christian Association</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>General<unitdate> 1951, 1961</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Secretary, South Africa</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">7-12</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence and reports<unitdate> 1947-53, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Financial<unitdate>1949-53,undated </unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>Reference materials<unitdate> 1932, 1950-51, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Subject files: Race</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Reference material<unitdate> 1939-70, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom<unitdate>Aug 1963</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
