<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss547.xml//EN">mnsss547</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Old Lesbians Organizing for Change Records, 1987-2010
(ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">January 27, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
            <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Old Lesbians Organizing for
Change</corpname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Old Lesbians Organizing for Change records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1987-2010 (ongoing)</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 671</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">21 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(25.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Lesbian activists. Extensive documentation of all OLOC gatherings to date (1987-2004),
including photographs, and videotapes of panel discussions and keynote speeches. Administrative
files, newsletters and other publications, and educational and public relations materials are also
included, as is a history of the organization.

        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>The book <title render="italic">Look Me in the Eye: Old Women, Aging and Ageism</title> by Barbara Macdonald and Cynthia Rich
(1983), which exposed the harsh realities of ageism on old women, was the inspiration for the
founding of Old Lesbians Organizing for Change.  In April 1987, the First West Coast Conference by
and for Old Lesbians in Southern California was held at the California State University Dominguez
Campus in Carson, California. It was so successful that in August 1989, Old Lesbians in Northern
California sponsored The Second West Coast Conference. Out of the larger group of Old Lesbians
attending these two events came a smaller group of sixteen that wished to concentrate their efforts
on challenging ageism. This group founded The Old Lesbian Organizing Committee, which was later
renamed Old Lesbians Organizing for Change. Participation was strictly limited to lesbians sixty
years of age and older, although OLOC has always welcomed the support of younger lesbians,
encouraging them to work against ageism while respecting the need for separate space for Old
Lesbians. To minimize travel expenses for committee members, most meetings during the first two
years were held in California. A concerted effort was then made to expand the geographic
representation by moving the meetings around the country; frequency of meetings was later changed
from quarterly to twice a year.</p>

<p>OLOC quickly established a newsletter to reach Old Lesbians around the country and began enrolling
subscribers. Committee members focused early efforts on development of educational materials on
ageism, using the familiar and effective format of consciousness raising sessions. These materials
were pooled and published in <title render="italic">The Facilitator's Handbook: Confronting Ageism: Consciousness Raising
for Lesbians 60 and Over</title> (early 1990s).  Much of OLOC's early work was done within both the women's
and LGBT communities, since ageism was as entrenched in those communities as it was in society at
large. Often at its own expense, OLOC provided speakers and presentations to dozens of workshops
and conferences, challenging the status quo and demanding to be a part of the process. OLOC felt
strongly that younger people couldn't effectively speak for Old Lesbians and insisted that Old
Lesbians be allowed to represent themselves. OLOC was a strong and highly visible part of the
National Lesbian Conference in Atlanta in 1991 as well as the March on Washington in 1993. By 1992,
OLOC sought and gained non-profit status, incorporating in the state of Texas, and in 1994 also
achieved tax-exempt status. In 1996, OLOC held its first National Gathering, bringing together Old
Lesbians from coast to coast, at the University of Minnesota in Minneapolis. Hundreds of Old
Lesbians gathered in San Francisco, California in 1999. In 2002, OLOC held it's third Gathering,
again in Minnesota. Old Lesbians at the Gatherings expressed a strong desire for more frequent
opportunities to get together, so the schedule was switched from once every three years to every
other year. In 2004, the fourth National OLOC Gathering was held in Houston, Texas and in 2006, the
group convened in Durham, North Carolina. The 2008 Gathering, held in Los Angeles, California, will
be followed by future Gatherings on each even-numbered year.</p>

<p>In addition to a quarterly newsletter, <title render="italic">The OLOC Reporter</title>, and biennial Gatherings, OLOC confronts
ageism wherever it is found. OLOC has also been associated with the Old Lesbian Oral Herstory
Project, which gathers the unique stories of lesbians who are seventy  years of age and older. OLOC
operates both as a national organization and through local chapters that have formed across the
country. </p>
<p>[source: 
<extref href="http://http//www.oloc.org/index.php">OLOC Website</extref>]</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>THe Records contain extensive documentation of all OLOC gatherings to date (1987-2004), including photographs, and
videotapes of panel discussions and keynote speeches. Administrative files, newsletters and other
publications, and educational and public relations materials are also included, as is a history of
the organization.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of
research copies.</item>
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                         <item>Portions of collection are stored offsite; researchers must give 48
hours advance notice.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to unpublished works by OLOC within this
collection.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their
heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair
use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all
copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Old Lesbians Organizing for Change Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The OLOC Records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 2011</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
           <p>Accessioned by  Burd Schlessinger, 2011 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Ageism -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian communities -- United States -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians -- United States -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians activists -- United States -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Older lesbians -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Older people -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Older women -- United States -- Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Old Lesbians Organizing for Change</corpname> 

</controlaccess>
<!-- add links where needed -->
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>See also the <extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss557_main.html">Old Lesbians Oral History Project</extref></p>
      </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead>
