<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss475.xml//EN">mnsss475</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Carol Leonard Papers, 1966-2008</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Margaret Jessup. 
		<date normal="2008-12-10">2008-12-10</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Leonard, Carol</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Carol Leonard papers</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1966-2010</unitdate>
	
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 206</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">11 boxes</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(4.75 linear ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		Midwife. The Carol Leonard Papers document the general practice of midwifery, the legal status of lay midwifery in the State of New Hampshire, and Leonard's profession as a midwife.  Types of materials include correspondence, primarily from Leonard's clients expressing gratittude and describing their experiences and feelings following childbirth; photographs; documentation of her travel to Russia in 1990 to help improve maternity care there; records of Leonard's work towards the legalization and regulation of lay midwifery in New Hampshire; general information about the practice and legal status of midwifery in New Hampshire, the U.S. and other countries; materials pertaining to the Midwives Alliance of North America; and Carol Leonard's writings including her book <title render="italic">Lady's Hands, Lions Heart: Memoirs of a Midwife</title>.  
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc4693.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>Governor Hugh Gallen signing  New Hampshire  midwifery legislation, with group of women  including Carol Leonard looking on, 15 August 1981</p></daodesc></dao>
	<p>Carol Leonard was born in Bangor, Maine on June 10, 1950. She received a B.S. in biology from New England College in Henniker, New Hampshire in 1974. She trained as a midwife from 1975 to 1977 with Dr. Francis Brown and has been a practicing midwife since 1978. In 1979 she co-founded the Concord (New Hampshire) Midwifery Service, where she practiced until 1987. In 2000, she founded the Longmeadow Farm Midwifery Service and Birthing Home at her farm in Hopkinton, New Hampshire, one of only two midwife-owned and operated, free-standing birth centers in the state.  Leonard was a board member of the New Hampshire Feminist Health Center, where she trained and was a well-woman health care provider, as well. She was the first midwife certified to practice in New Hampshire (1985) and a charter member of the Midwives Alliance of North America (MANA) (1982). Through the years she held numerous positions within MANA and was elected president of the organization in 1986. In 1984 Leonard received the Bronze Medal for Bravery from the Australian government for saving a man's life, and in 1990 she went to the former Soviet Union to study birthing practices. This trip was videotaped and featured on ABC's 20/20 in April 1991.  Leonard is on the faculty of Birthwise Midwifery School in Bridgton, Maine, a nationally accredited program.  She is the author of <title render="italic">Lady's Hands, Lions Heart: Memoirs of a Midwife</title> (2008), co-author, with Elizabeth Davis, of <title render="italic">Women's Wheel of Life: Thirteen Archetypes of Woman at Her Fullest Power</title> (1996), and published a two-part series on menopause titled <title render="italic">Women of the Thirteenth Moon: The Baby Boomer's Survival Guide to Menopause</title>. </p>
    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="scope">
	
	<p>The Carol Leonard Papers consist of 3 linear ft., and date from 1966 to 2008.  They offer a glimpse into the general practice of midwifery, the legal status of lay midwifery in the State of New Hampshire, and Leonard's profession as a midwife.  Types of materials include correspondence, clippings, articles, photographs, case files, surveys, legal documents, and writings.  They document the general practice of midwifery, the legal status of lay midwifery in the State of New Hampshire, and Leonard's profession as a midwife.  Types of materials include  correspondence, primarily from Leonard's clients expressing gratittude and describing their experiences and feelings following childbirth; clippings and articles about her; documentation of her travel to Russia in 1990 to observe childbirth practices and to help improve maternity care there. There are also records of Leonard's work with the New Hampshire Division of Public Health in formalizing the legalization and regulation of lay midwifery in that state; general information about the practice and legal status of midwifery in New Hampshire, the U.S. and other countries; materials pertaining to Leonard's involvement in several midwifery practices, as well as correspondence and printed materials pertaining to the early years of the Midwives Alliance of North America.  Materials pertaining to Carol Leonard's writings include a pre-publication copy of her book <title render="italic">Lady's Hands, Lions Heart: Memoirs of a Midwife</title>.  There are also photographs of Leonard, her clients, family and friends.</p>
    </scopecontent>

    <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	
	<p>This collection is organized into four series:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser3">SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser4">SERIES IV. WRITINGS</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-serOV">OVERSIZE MATERIALS</ref>
		</item>
	</list>
    </arrangement>

<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, although researchers must sign the "Access Agreement Form" before viewing them. Certain photographs are closed, and new accessions are closed until processed. </p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the papers, with the exception of Leonard's book, <title render="italic">Lady's Hands, Lions Heart: Memoirs of a Midwife</title>, to which she has retained rights. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  Copyright to materials authored by persons other than Carol Leonard (including Elizabeth Davis, co-author of <title render="italic">Women's Wheel of Life: Thirteen Archetypes of Woman at Her Fullest Power</title>) may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. </p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Carol Leonard Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <accruals id="admin-accruals">
	<p>This is a continuing collection to which materials will be added from time to time.</p>
    </accruals>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>Carol Leonard began donating her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1991.  </p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Burd Schlessinger, 2008</p> 
    </processinfo>

<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
		
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Childbirth -- History -- United States --20th century --Sources</subject>

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Midwifery -- United States --20th century --Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Midwives -- New Hampshire -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Leonard, Carol</persname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Midwives' Alliance of North America</corpname> 
	    </controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->
    <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
	<p>Related materials can be found in
	<extref href="mnsss102_main.html">Midwives Alliance of North America Records</extref></p>
    </relatedmaterial>

<!-- End additional information -->


<!-- Enter Series descriptions -->
<dsc type="analyticover">
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS <unitdate>(1966-2008)</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>.25 linear ft.</extent>
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series contains legal documents, including the contract stating the terms between Leonard and potential clients.  It also includes photographs of Leonard alone, and with clients, family and friends; and clippings and articles about her, including documentation of her travel to Russia in 1990 to observe childbirth practices and to help improve maternity care there. Restricted photographs are filed separately.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>

 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE <unitdate>(1976-92)</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>.5 linear ft.</extent>
	</physdesc>
	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>The correspondence, primarily from Leonard's clients, includes letters of gratitude and thanks.  Numerous letters describe the women's experiences and feelings following childbirth; several also contain discussion of payment for Leonard's services.  There is some personal correspondence from friends and colleagues, and a small amount of business correspondence not related to clients.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES <unitdate>(1976-92)</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>1 linear ft.</extent>
	</physdesc>	</did>
	<scopecontent>
		<p>This series primarily documents Leonard's work with the New Hampshire Division of Public Health in formalizing the legalization and regulation of lay midwifery in that state.  There is general information about midwifery as a medical specialty, the practice and legal status of midwifery in other countries, applications for license to practice midwifery in New Hampshire, and documentation of the lay midwifery certification and examination process.  The series also includes materials pertaining to Leonard's involvement in several midwifery practices, as well as correspondence and printed materials pertaining to the early years of the Midwives Alliance of North America.  Also of interest is documentation of investigations into several cases of infant and maternal mortality (involving midwives other than Carol Leonard).</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>

 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES IV. WRITINGS <unitdate>(1988-2008)</unitdate></unittitle>
	<physdesc>
		<extent>.25 linear ft.</extent>
	</physdesc>
	</did>

	<scopecontent>
		<p>Materials pertaining to Carol Leonard's writings include a pre-publication copy of her book <title render="italic">Lady's Hands, Lions Heart: Memoirs of a Midwife</title>, correspondence pertaining to an early proposal for the book, a diary entry, and a dream recall.</p>
	</scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>
<!-- End Series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->
<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Resumes, and internet printouts<unitdate>1985, 2008, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Articles, clippings, travel documents, basal temperature charts, calendars, and business cards<unitdate>1978-84, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
	<note><p> [see also Oversize Materials]</p>
	</note>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Legal documents<unitdate>1977-78, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Financial information: checkbooks, bills, and receipts<unitdate>1978-85</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Soviet training mission: clippings, correspondence, and articles<unitdate>1990-91</unitdate></unittitle>
	<note><p>[see also Oversize Materials]
</p>
	</note> 
</did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">6-7</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs<unitdate>circa 1966-94, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>General</unittitle>
	<note><p>[see also SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES: Midwives Alliance of North America]
</p>
	</note>
  </did>
<c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">8-10</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1976-77, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">1-7</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1978-92, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Seattle Midwifery School<unitdate>1983-85</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Third-party<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Midwives Alliance of North America</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">1-2</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence<unitdate>1983-86, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Fliers, brochures, notes, mailing list, and printed materials<unitdate>1984-91, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>State of New Hampshire Lay Midwifery</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Certification and regulation</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">4-5</container>
 <unittitle>General information: articles, statistics, forms, and correspondence and memoranda<unitdate>1978-85, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Scope of Practice<unitdate>2003</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Applications to practice<unitdate>1985</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Written examinations<unitdate>1985, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Advisory Committee</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">1-4</container>
 <unittitle>Case histories of infant or maternal mortality<unitdate>1985-86</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Client files<unitdate>1978-86, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Concord Midwifery Service: policies and procedures, fliers, and forms<unitdate>1983, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Longmeadow Farm Midwifery Service and Birthing Home: correspondence, brochure, and internet printout<unitdate>1999, 2008</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>New Hampshire Childbirth Education Association: newsletters<unitdate>1977</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>New Hampshire Midwives Association: proposed regulations and flier<unitdate>1982, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>New Hampshire Women's Health Services: pregnancy surveys and names of Board of Directors<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Conferences and workshops</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Presentations by Carol Leonard</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>International Confederation of Midwives: "Delivery Over an Intact Perineum": correspondence, forms, articles, and notes<unitdate>1987</unitdate></unittitle>
 	<note><p>[see also Oversize Materials]
</p>
	</note>
</did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Other<unitdate>1984-92, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>General information about other conferences and workshops<unitdate>1976-79, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Forms, and handouts<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Product information<unitdate>1980, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">3-5</container>
 <unittitle>Childbirth and midwifery, general information about: articles and clippings<unitdate>circa 1974-80s</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Spirituality: articles, and fliers<unitdate>1985-87, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous documents<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES IV. WRITINGS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Lady's Hands, Lions Heart: Memoirs of a Midwife</title></unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Desktop publishing copy, publicity, and internet printouts<unitdate>1999, 2008</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>"Midwife": correspondence, and contract<unitdate>1988 </unitdate>(probably re: early version of Lady's Hands, Lions Heart)</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Diary entry and dream recall<unitdate>1988, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Notes about midwifery<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">1-2</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs of women giving birth<unitdate>1977-80, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
	<accessrestrict>
		<p>[CLOSED]</p>
	</accessrestrict>
</c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-serOV" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>OVERSIZE MATERIALS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>Calendars, clippings, correspondence, and writings<unitdate>1977-91, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>

 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-serBK" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>BOOKS ON SHELF</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Carol Leonard, <title render="italic">Bad Beaver Tales: Love and Life on a New Sustainable 				Homestead in Down  East Maine, Volume I - Camp Kwitchabitchin</title> <unitdate>2012</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
