<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">


  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss569.xml//EN">mnsss569</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Safe Passage Records, 1971-2000 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 14.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">September 30, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Safe Passage (Northampton, Mass.)</corpname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Safe Passage records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1971-2000 (ongoing)</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 351</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">7 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(8 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Women's shelter and community service organization. Safe Passage (formerly Necessities/Necesidades) was founded in Northampton, Massachusetts in 1978 as a women's collective to provide shelter and assistance to battered women and their children and to empower women with self-help techniques for ending abusive relationships. In addition the organization educates the community about violence against women through public programs. Records include internal documents such as  executive director's files; financial records; and correspondence, 1978-1992. Public records include material documenting the history of the organization; publicity and fundraising material; material related to other women's organizations; and pamphlets, articles and other printed material that relate to the subject of battered women. [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>
</did>


<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Safe Passage (formerly Necessities/Necesidades) was founded in Northampton, Massachusetts  in
1978 as a women's collective intended  "to empower women by providing them with self-help
techniques that allow them to end abusive relationships."  In addition to this work, the
organization also educates the community about violence against women through public programs and
publications and by training volunteers. Perhaps most important, it provides shelter and assistance
to battered women and their children.  In 1995 the organization abandoned its collective framework
in favor of a more hierarchical organizing structure that included  two co-directors and an
expanded board.  In 1998 they adopted a single director model.  In 2000, Necessities/Necesidades
changed its name to Safe Passage.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>The Safe Passage (formerly Necessities/Necesidades) records include both internal and public
material. Internal records consist of:  executive director's files; financial records;
correspondence, and personal records, 1978-1992. Public records  include material that documents
the history of the organization; publicity and fundraising material; material related to other
women's organizations, including Necessities predecessors HLRIPP and HERA; and pamphlets, articles
and other printed material that relate to the subject of battered women.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>
 

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>Partially restricted access - contact the Sophia Smith Collection for more information.</item>
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>


 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works created by Safe
Passage in this collection.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those
individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or
quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy
the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Safe Passage Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>

<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>Safe Passage began donating their records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1984. Periodic additions to the collection are expected.</p>
</acqinfo>


<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abused women -- Services for -- Massachusetts</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Collectivism -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists -- Northampton (Mass.)</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's shelters -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Family violence -- Massachusetts</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Massachusetts</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Massachusetts Coalition of Battered Women's Service Groups -- History -- Sources</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Safe Passage (Northampton, Mass.) -- History</corpname> 
</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
