<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
   <eadheader audience="internal" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b">
      <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss125.xml//EN">mnsss125</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Florence Ellinwood Allen Papers, 1920-1966
        </titleproper>
            <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
            <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by mnsss.</author>
            <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            <date encodinganalog="260$c">2003 </date>
            <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded using Perl scripts and edited in XMetal 2.0. Encoded by Brook Hopkins.
        <date>2003-07-01</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2005-09-23">2005-09-23</date>
            <item>mnsss125 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02-5c.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter id="front">
      <titlepage>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection Smith College
         
            </publisher>
         <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Florence Ellinwood Allen Papers, 1920-1966
      </titleproper>
         <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
         <num>MS 2
      </num>
         <date>2002
      </date>
         
         <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         <p>©  2003  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did id="main-overview">
         <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Allen, Florence Ellinwood, 1884-1966</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Florence Ellinwood Allen papers</unittitle><unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1920-1966</unitdate>
         
         <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 2</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Quantity:">
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">2 boxes		  </extent>
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(.75 linear ft.)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            </repository>
         <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Lawyer, judge, suffragist, and pacifist. Allen's papers reflect her career as the first woman judge of a state supreme court and the first woman appointed as a federal judge, as well as her work in the Ohio suffrage and peace movements. Also included are the writings of Florence's mother, Corinne Tuckerman Allen, who was a member of the first class admitted to Smith College. Tuckerman Allen advocated sexual morality, monogamy and family relationships and organized for the Congress of Mothers.</abstract>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
            <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <bioghist id="bioghist">
         
         <p>Florence Ellinwood Allen was born on March 23, 1884 in Salt Lake City.  Her mother, Corinne Tuckerman, was a member of the first class admitted to Smith College.  Her father, Clarence Emir Allen, was a professor of Latin and Greek at Western Reserve University and placed a strong emphasis on education.  Florence took an interest in books from a young age, and her father once said, "If Florence were a boy, I'd make a lawyer out of her."  A gifted pianist, Allen moved to Berlin after high school to study music and work as a music critic.  She returned to the United States and attended the University of Chicago.  In 1913, she received an L.L.B. from New York University Law School.

    </p>
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc6268.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>Florence Ellinwood Allen, Judge United States  Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, 1940</p></daodesc></dao> 
         <p>Allen started her own legal practice in Cleveland, Ohio and was active in the women's suffrage movement.  She was the attorney for the Cleveland Woman Suffrage Party and became the first woman to argue before a supreme court, winning a municipal suffrage case in Ohio.  She was also active in the Peace Movement in the 1920s.  In 1920, the first year women were constitutionally guaranteed the right to vote, she was elected as judge of the Court of Common Pleas, becoming the first woman in history to be elected to a judicial office.  In 1922, she was elected to the Ohio Supreme Court, making her the first woman to serve as a judge of the highest court of a state.  She served as an Ohio Supreme Court Judge for almost twelve years and in 1934, President Roosevelt appointed her to the Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit.  No woman had previously been appointed to the United States Court of Appeals.

    </p>
         <p>Judge Allen was a popular lecturer and published several books, including Patris, The Treaty as an Instrument of Legislation, and This Constitution of Ours.  She was an outspoken opponent of war and wrote extensively on the topic.  She was also interested in international law and was a strong advocate for the International Court.  She received numerous honors and awards in her lifetime, including honorary degrees from twenty-five colleges and universities, the National Achievement Award in 1938, the Order of the Coif in 1955 by George Washington University, and a citation for advancing the status of women in the legal profession from the National Association of Women Lawyers.  In 1959, a portrait of Judge Allen was given to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit in honor of her contribution to the law.  Judge Allen died at the age of eighty-two in her home in Cleveland, Ohio on September 12, 1966.
    </p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="scope">
         
         <p>The Florence Ellinwood Allen papers consist of .75 linear feet of biographical material, awards, articles, addresses, correspondence, and photographs.  The collection also includes writings of her mother Corinne Tuckerman Allen, one of the first students admitted to Smith College (1874) and organizer of the Congress of Mothers (1916), about her work for sexual morality, monogamy, family relationships in Utah, and the Congress of Mothers. Additionally, there are several speeches and articles written by Florence Allen on topics ranging from the status of women in the legal profession to international law and human rights.  There are two books written by Allen: Patris and The Treaty as an Instrument of Legislation.    </p>
      </scopecontent>

            <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
               <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
          </p>
            </accessrestrict>
            <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
               <p>The copyright owner of this collection is unknown. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.
          </p>
            </userestrict>

         <prefercite id="admin-cite">
            <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
            <p>"Florence Ellinwood Allen Papers", Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
         </prefercite>

             <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
               <p>Florence Ellinwood Allen donated this material to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1962 to 1966.
          </p>
            </acqinfo>
             <processinfo id="admin-process">
               <p>Finding aid revised in 2002 by Brook Hopkins, intern. </p>
            </processinfo>

      <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
         
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Allen, Florence Ellinwood, 1884-1966</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">
                  Allen, Corinne Tuckerman, 1865-1931
                  </persname>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">National Congress of Mothers--History--Sources</corpname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women judges--United States
                  </subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women lawyers--United States
                  </subject>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources
                  </subject>
         <name>Women and peace--History--20th century--Sources</name>
      </controlaccess>

         <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
            <head>Related Material</head>
            <p>A larger collection of Florence Allen's Papers are located at
            <extref href="http://www.wrhs.org">Western Reserve Historical Society Library</extref>, Ohio.  Additional papers of Corinne Tuckerman Allen are housed at the
            <extref href="http://www.radcliffe.edu/schlesinger_library.aspx">Schlesinger Library</extref> at Harvard University and in the
            <extref href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/archives/">Smith College Archives</extref>. </p>
         </relatedmaterial>

      <dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">1</container>
               <unittitle>Contents</unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">2</container>
               <unittitle>Allen, Corinne Tuckerman (mother of F.E. Allen): writings and correspondence<unitdate> 1856-1931 </unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>Biography</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">3</container>
                  <unittitle>Articles about F.E. Allen</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">4</container>
                  <unittitle>Obituary<unitdate> 1966</unitdate>
                  </unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">1</container>
                  <container type="folder">5</container>
                  <unittitle>Clippings about F.E. Allen</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">6</container>
               <unittitle>Correspondence: Janet Wilson (to and from)<unitdate> 1956</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">7</container>
               <unittitle>Honors</unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">8</container>
               <unittitle>Photographs (12)</unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">9</container>
               <unittitle>Retirement: clippings</unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <container type="box">1</container>
               <container type="folder">10</container>
               <unittitle>Speeches and articles<unitdate> 1925-1960</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
         </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>Books</unittitle>
            </did>
	     <c02>
               <did>
	         <container type="box">1</container>
	         <unittitle>Allen, Florence Ellinwood. <title>Patris</title>  (Cleveland, 1908) <unitdate>1908</unitdate>
               </unittitle>
            </did>
	     </c02>
	     <c02>
            	<did>
		  <container type="box">1</container>
		  <unittitle>Allen, Florence Ellinwood. <title>The Treaty as an Instrument of Legislation</title> (New York, 1952)<unitdate> 1952</unitdate>
		  </unittitle>
            	 </did>
           </c02>
	 </c01>
         <c01>
            <did>
               <unittitle>Oversize Materials</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c02>
               <did>
                  <container type="box">2</container>
                  <unittitle>Framed photographic portrait of Florence Ellinwood Allen</unittitle>
               </did>
            </c02>
         </c01>
      </dsc>
   </archdesc>
</ead>
