<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">


  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss518.xml//EN">mnsss518</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Tucker Pamella Farley Papers, 1969-2010</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2012">2012</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">February 20, 2012</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Farley, Tucker Pamella</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Tucker Pamella Farley
Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1969-2010</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 676</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">3 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(2.25 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <!-- MRJ Edit as needed-->
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Author; Labor organizer; Lesbian activist; Professor, English; Professor, Women's
Studies. The papers contain materials from her academic career and study groups. Most material is related to Marxist Feminist Group 1 (MF 1) which include an extensive amount of discussion notes, minutes, planning materials, and publications. The group's topics ranged significantly over the years, and have included socialism, homophobia, racism, and postmodernism.  Some records also exist of her participation in early women's studies courses, research, and conferences. The collection contains draft and published writings by Farley on the subjects of women in literature, women's self-narratives, and the history of women's studies.

         </abstract>
       
</did>

 <!--  Add paragraph marks to text -->
<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
     <p>Tucker Pamella Farley is an activist and academic who helped create a space for women's studies in the university. She has been active in a variety of social justice causes. Farley earned her bachelor's degree from Oberlin College in 1961, and as a graduate student at Pennsylvania State University in the late 1960s, she became involved in Leftist activist efforts aimed at radicalizing the university. She organized for academic labor unions, and she participated in the Radical Caucus of the Modern Language Association and the New University Conference, among other groups. She was also involved in the women's liberation movement and the emergent field of women's studies. Farley completed her Ph.D. in 1973.</p> 

<p>Hired by Brooklyn College of the City University of New York in 1970 to teach women's studies and American literature, she was instrumental in the development of the school's Women's Studies Program and Women's Center. She was a founder of the New York Women's Labor Project, where she created and taught women's studies course for trade union women. A self- described "founding mother" of the National Women's Studies Association (NWSA), Farley spearheaded the creation of NWSA's Lesbian Caucus. At the same time, she engaged in small-scale activist and intellectual networking through participation in a variety of study groups on radical and feminist issues. This included Marxist-Feminist Group 1 (MF 1), which has been active since 1973. Organized in the northeastern United States, MF 1 combined elements of the consciousness raising group with academic inquiry into issues of radicalism and feminism. Members have included academics, policy makers, and political activist. The group continues to meet two to three times a year. Tucker Farley maintained an active publishing and teaching career through the 2000s. She earned emerita status in 2005.</p>
</bioghist>
 <!--  Add paragraph marks to text -->
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The Tucker Pamella Farley papers contain materials from her academic career and study groups. Most material is related to Marxist Feminist Group 1 (MF 1). Farley maintained a personal set of the organization's records, which include an extensive amount of discussion notes and minutes, planning materials, and publications. The group's topics ranged significantly over the years, and have included socialism, homophobia, racism, and postmodernism. Farley's contributions to these discussions included the subjects of lesbian feminism and women in literature, among others. Most documentation of MF 1 consists of discussion notes and presentation papers; the collection also contains audiocassettes of a 2010 session. Farley created item level inventories of most of the MF1 documents in this accession. These lists can be found appended to the box list. The remainder of the papers relate to other aspects of Farley's career. A small amount of printed material and correspondence documents her association with labor organizing, feminist organizing, lesbian issues, and direct action campaigns in the academy in the early 1970s. Some records also exist of her participation in early women's studies courses, research, and conferences. The collection contains draft and published writings by Farley on the subjects of women in literature, women's self-narratives, and the history of women's studies.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
       
</scopecontent>
 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	   <list type="simple">
    			<item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult
to use.</item>
                     <item>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.</item>
                     <item>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>


<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works of Tucker Pamella Farley in her papers. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Tucker Pamella Farley Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton,
Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>

<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>Tucker Pamella Farley began donating her papers to the SSC in 2011. Periodic additions to the collection are expected.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by  Amanda Izzo, April 2010 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminism -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminism and education -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminist theory -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Gay rights -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian activists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian feminism -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians -- Education (Higher) -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Labor movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Marxist criticism -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Communism -- Study and teaching -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Radicalism -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sex discrimination in education -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Socialism -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Education (Higher) -- United States -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Societies and clubs -- United States -- History -- 20th century</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women college teachers -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women radicals -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's studies -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in the labor movement -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Brooklyn College -- Faculty</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Farley, Tucker Pamella</persname> 

</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->