<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss426.xml//EN">mnsss426</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Winnifred Crane Wygal Papers, 1918-1972 (bulk 1932-1958)</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Maida Goodwin.</author>
		<sponsor>Processing of the Winnifred Crane Wygal Papers was made possible by the generous support of the National Historical Publications and Records Commission</sponsor> 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2009">2009</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Annie-Sage Whitehurst. 
		<date normal="2009-06-03">2009-06-03</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	  </langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Wygal, Winnifred</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Winnifred Wygal papers</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1918-1972</unitdate>
	<unitdate encodinganalog="245$g" type="bulk">1932-1958</unitdate>
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 617</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">4 boxes</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1.75 linear ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		YWCA worker. The Winnifred Crane Wygal Papers are primarily related to her professional and public life and include biographical materials, correspondence, memorabilia, notebooks, administrative planning files, subject files, and writings. The bulk of the papers date from 1932 to 1958 and focus on Wygal's work planning religious services, writing religious program materials, and as a speaker and discussion leader for the YWCA and for other religious groups.  Wygal's notebooks (1932-58) document her part in wide variety of conferences, councils, meetings, worship services, courses, seminars, discussion groups in the YWCA and other national, international, and local organizations.  They also include notes on lectures and conferences she attended and books and articles she read.  The main subject of Wygal's writings, most published by the YWCA's Womans Press,  is the development of meaningful worship services, and relevance of religion in twentieth-century life.
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	<head>Biographical Note</head>
<p>Winnifred Crane Wygal was born August 25, 1884 in  Springfield, Missouri, to  Frank and Katie A. Bigelow Wygal.  Frank Wygal was a wagon maker at the Springfield Wagon Works. 
Both parents read widely and encouraged their daughters to do likewise.  Frank Wygal's Christian socialist beliefs fostered a strong commitment to social justice in the young Winnifred.  In an autobiographical manuscript, Wygal wrote of her childhood:   "I was wanted and loved and cherished.  Life was exciting and good almost at once."  </p>

<p>After graduating from Springfield High School, "Windy" Wygal attended Drury College (now Drury University) in Springfield, where she first joined the Young Women's Christian Association.  After receiving her B.A. in 1906, Wygal taught high school English and Latin in Missouri from 1906 to 1911.  Wygal attended the YWCA's National Training School in New York City and did graduate coursework at Columbia University in 1911-12.  Drury awarded her  an M.A. in 1912.  A life-long student, Wygal also did post-graduate work at Union Theological Seminary and the University of Chicago Divinity School, as well as "special reading" with Canon Streeter at Oxford University and with H.B. Sharman of the Pendle Hill Quaker Center for Graduate Study.</p>

<p>In 1913 Wygal took a job at the YWCA at the University of Nevada, Reno.  In 1917 or early 1918 she joined the War Work Council staff of the national YWCA.  She supervised five Hostess Houses where servicemen could meet with family and friends, and three recreational service centers at Camp Funston at Fort Riley near Manhattan, Kansas.  From there, Wygal transferred to the YWCA's North Central region field staff in 1919 or 1920, as a Student Secretary.  She moved to the National Student Council staff (the college and university student department of the YWCA) in 1922, where she remained until 1935, working on program and personnel and serving several years as acting executive, associate executive, and finally, executive of the Council.  Much of Wygal's work in the Student YWCA centered on helping young women to distinguish between "the prohibitions imposed by culture" and "the universal imperatives."</p>  

<p>In 1935 Wygal transferred to the Laboratory Division where she developed religious resources for use in YWCA programs.  In May of 1935 Wygal was co-chair with Gregory Vlastos, of the Fletcher Farm Seminar on Religion, a ten-day seminar led by Reinhold Niebuhr, Henry Nelson Wieman, and Paul Tillich.  Wygal attended the Conference of the Church on Life and Work at Oxford University in 1937 and she wrote preparatory materials for the World Christian Youth Conference in Amsterdam in 1939.  A 1940 staff reorganization moved Wygal's work to the Division of Community YWCAs.  Wygal retired from the YWCA in 1944.</p>

<p>For many years after retirement, Wygal did extensive free-lance speaking and discussion leading to young people's groups in churches and YWCAs.  She was the author of many works relating to personal and group worship and the first woman to be a deacon at Riverside Church in New York City.</p>

<p>In a meditation written for Wygal's memorial service in 1972, YWCA General Secretary Edith Lerrigo described Wygal with the words "deep," "ardent," "committed," "flaming," "impatient," and "dedicated."</p>

<p>Winnifred Wygal died of a heart attack in New York City on September 8, 1972.  She was buried in San Antonio, Texas.</p>

    </bioghist>
    <scopecontent id="scope">
	<head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
<p>	The Winnifred Crane Wygal Papers consist of 1.75 linear ft. and are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1918 to 1972.  Types of materials include biographical materials, correspondence, memorabilia, notebooks, administrative planning files, subject files, and writings.  </p>

<p>The bulk of the papers date from 1932 to 1958 and focus on Wygal's  work planning religious services, writing religious program materials, and as a speaker and discussion leader for the YWCA and for other religious groups.</p>   

<p>Wygal's notebooks (1932-58) document her part in wide variety of conferences, councils, meetings, worship services, courses, seminars, and discussion groups in the YWCA and other national, international, and local organizations.  They also include notes on lectures and conferences she attended and books and articles she read.</p>  
 
<p>The main subject of Wygal's writings, most published by the YWCA's Womans Press,  is the development of meaningful worship services, and relevance of religion in twentieth-century life.</p>

    </scopecontent>


<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>Copyright ownership of Winnifred Wygal's writings is unknown.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Winnifred Crane Wygal Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass."</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>The Winnifred Crane Wygal Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the Records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. in 2002.  The YWCA received them from Winnifred Wygal in 1969 and from her estate in 1972.</p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Processed by Maida Goodwin, 2009</p> 
    </processinfo>

<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
		<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Wygal, Winnifred, b. 1884</persname>
    		<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. -- History</subject> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Young women -- Religious life -- United States -- History</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women and religion -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>

</controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->

<!-- End additional information -->
    <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
	<p>Related materials in the Sophia Smith Collection are in the
	<extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss292_main.html">YWCA USA Records, Sophia Smith Collection</extref>.  

</p>
    </relatedmaterial>
    <separatedmaterial id="add-separated">
	<p>Additional papers of Winnifred Wygal are housed at the
	<extref href="http://www.radcliffe.edu/schlesinger_library.aspx">Schlesinger Library, Harvard University</extref>.</p>
    </separatedmaterial>

<!-- Insert container list here:-->
<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Biographical materials and memorabilia</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>General<unitdate> 1961-72, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Favorite poems<unitdate> 1918, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>80th birthday celebration<unitdate> 1964</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Subject file on miscellaneous religious topics<unitdate> 1965, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Notebooks</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5-6</container>
 <unittitle> <unitdate>1932-38</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">1-8</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1942-1958</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">1-2</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1954-1958</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1929-71, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Typescript of letter re visit to Gandhi's ashram at Ahmedabad, India with Ruth ?<unitdate>5 Feb 1928</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle>Professional activities</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Fletcher Farm Seminar on Religion<unitdate> 1935</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>YWCA of the U.S.A.<unitdate> 1936, 1948, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Speaking engagements<unitdate> 1950-53</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Workshop, Church World Service Center, New Windsor, Maryland<unitdate> 1958</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Worship services for an unidentified Convention in Toronto<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Writings</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Articles<unitdate> 1936-55, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Autobiography: typescript fragments<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Book reviews<unitdate> 1945-52</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Study guides<unitdate> 1947, 1950</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">14-15</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous typescripts and fragments<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>"A Christman Service:" typescript<unitdate> 1936</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">The Good Life-A Discipline</title> , The Womans Press<unitdate> 1936, 1941</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">How to Plan Informal Worship</title> , Association Press<unitdate> 1957</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">Jesus-A Brief Study</title> , The Womans Press<unitdate> 1936</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">Our Religious Vocabulary: A Glossary of Terms in Current Use</title> , The Womans Press<unitdate> 1939</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">Principles of Religious Practice in the Community Association Program</title> , The Womans Press<unitdate> 1938</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>"The Question: Meditations on Meaning, Maturity and Faith," typescript<unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">Questions and Answers About You</title> , by Tirzah Anderson and Winnifred Wygal, The Woman's Press<unitdate> 1945</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">Reflections of the Spirit: Resources for Personal and Group Worship</title> , The Woman's Press<unitdate> 1948</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">Stop, Think and Do!</title>  by Elizabeth Palmer, Janet Fowler Nelson, and Winnifred Wygal, The Womans Press<unitdate> 1941</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">The Struggle for the Union at YWCA</title> , AFSCME Local<unitdate> 1707 </unitdate>Community and Social Agency Employees Union, n.d.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">The Superb Adventure: Acquiring a Theory of Living</title> , The Womans Press<unitdate> 1934</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic"/> We Plan Our Own Worship Services, The Womans Press (1940), and revised edition (1945)<unitdate> 1940, 1945 </unitdate> </unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>	<title render="italic">We the Peoples of the Ecumenical Church</title>, Woman's Division of Christian Service, Board of Missions and Church Extension, The Methodist Church<unitdate> 1949</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
