<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">


  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss560.xml//EN">mnsss560</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Black Women's Health Imperative Records, 1983-2006
(ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 14.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">September 30, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
<!-- Edit Orig label:
corpname encodinganalog="110"
famname encodinganalog="100 3"
Del Orig for Subject Colls and OH colls  -->
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Black Women's Health Imperative</corpname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Black Women's Health Imperative Records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1983-2006 (ongoing)</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 487</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">11 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(11 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Women of color, reproductive rights, and women's health advocacy organization. The records consist of materials pertaining to the administration and the public outreach work of the BWHI, including board of directors files reports, correspondence, conference materials, photograph albums, memorabilia, and audiovisual materials. There is a large amount of promotional and educational materials produced by BWNHP including pamphlets, posters, brochures, fact sheets, newsletters, self-help manuals, and videos. There is also a small amount of material pertaining to Byllye Avery as founder of BWHI.  [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>


<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Historical Note</head>
     <p>The Black Women's Health Imperative, originally called the Black Women's Health Project
(BWHP), then the National Black Women's Health Project (NBWHP), was established by Byllye Avery in
1981 as a program of the National Women's Health Network in Atlanta, GA. At the first National
Conference on Black Women's Health Issues, held at Spelman College in 1983, the BWHP became an
independent national organization.  Its purpose was to develop and disseminate self-help
methodologies, including "group psychosocial therapy techniques..to empower Black women to attain
healthy living and overall physical, mental and spiritual wellness."  In 1984, having been
incorporated and renamed the National Black Women's Health Project, the organization purchased a
national headquarters in Atlanta, affectionately known as The Mother House.  One of the NBWHP's
first initiatives was to begin holding quarterly task force meetings to gather information about
and to develop a cohesive perspective on black women's health issues.  Another primary facet of the
organization's work has consistently involved networking and collaborating with black women in
other countries on health issues (Africa, South America, the West Indies, as well as the United
Nations Fourth World Conference on Women in Beijing, China and the Beijing + 5 NGO Host Committee).
 The organization has produced and published numerous films, videotapes and books pertaining to
Black women's health issues.</p> 

<p>Key projects, some of them ongoing, include implementation and
promotion of a national fitness program, Walking for Wellness (1992); the Domestic Violence
Initiative (1995); development and implementation of substance abuse education and prevention
programs on eight "historically black" college and university campuses (1996); REACH 2010, a study
of intervention strategies to reduce cardiovascular risk among Black church women in New Orleans,
LA (2000); development of the Black Women's Wellness Study, a weight management pilot program
undertaken in partnership with the University of Pennsylvania (2001); <title render="italic">Because I am a Queen</title>, a
national television campaign and online smoking prevention and cessation program directed to Black
women (2002); and Take Your Loved One to the Doctor Day, a national multimedia campaign to promote
gynecological visits, also directed specifically to Black women, undertaken in partnership with the
USDHHS (2002).  In 2003, the organization was instrumental in convening the National Colloquium on
Black Women's Health, "to generate a national sense of urgency to address the unequal burden of
health issues borne by Black women."  In 2003, the organization changed its name to the Black
Women's Health Imperative.</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The records consist of materials pertaining to the administration and the public outreach work of the BWHI, including board of directors files reports, correspondence, conference materials, photograph albums, memorabilia, and audiovisual materials. There is a large amount of promotional and educational materials produced by BWNHP including pamphlets, posters, brochures, fact sheets, newsletters, self-help manuals, and videos.   There is also a small amount of material pertaining to Byllye Avery as founder of BWHI.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>
 

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
                         <item>Original audiovisual materials and master copies are closed. Research copies are available.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>


 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to most of the unpublished works created 
by the BWHI  in this collection.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those
individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or
quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy
the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Black Women's Health Imperative Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<altformavail id="admin-altform">
     <head>Additional Formats</head>
		<p>Original VHS videos have been digitized and are 
		<extref href="https://media.smith.edu/departments/ssc/bwhi/bwhi_video.html">available for viewing online</extref> (Smith campus only).</p>
</altformavail>
<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>

<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Black Women's Health Imperative began donating their records to the Sophia Smith
Collection in 2003.   Periodic additions to the collection are expected.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by  Burd Schlessinger, 2003 </p>
</processinfo>

<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American women -- Health and hygiene -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American women -- Medical care -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American women -- Mental health</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American women -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American women health reformers -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Health care reform -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Health education of women -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Public health --  United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reproductive health -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reproductive rights -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Health and hygiene -- Africa -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Health and hygiene -- Social aspects -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's health services -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">National Black Women's Health Project</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Black Women's Health Imperative</corpname> 
<!-- Encode with Added Entry clips -->
      	<persname encodinganalog="700" source="lcnaf">Avery, Byllye, 1937-</persname> 
</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated material can be found in the 
          <extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss205_main.html">Loretta Ross Papers</extref>; the Byllye Avery Papers; and the <extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss291_main.html">Voices of Feminism Oral History Project</extref> (Loretta Ross and Toure).</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->