<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">


  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss558.xml//EN">mnsss558</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Alan Guttmacher Institute Records, 1960-2013 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 14.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">September 30, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Alan Guttmacher Institute</corpname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Alan Guttmacher Institute
Records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1960-2013 (ongoing)</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 720</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">20 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(20 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>, <language langcode="spa">Spanish</language>, <language langcode="por">Portuguese</language>

</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Birth control advocacy organization; Birth control research organization. Records
include reports, data, publications, administrative and financial records, some correspondence.
They document especially well the efforts of a fact-finding organization determined to disseminate
as widely as possible the data it collects so as to help shape policy to increase access to
reproductive health services, and to "to ensure the highest standard of sexual and reproductive
health for all people worldwide."  [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>


<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Historical Note</head>
     <p>Founded in 1968 and first known as the Center for Family Planning Program Development, the
organization was initially part of the Planned Parenthood Federation of America (PPFA).  The Center
had as its champion Alan F. Guttmacher, the prestigious obstetrician/gynecologist/educator who
served as PPFA president for more than ten years until his death in 1974.  By 1977, the Center was
renamed the Alan Guttmacher Institute (AGI) in Dr. Guttmacher's honor and incorporated as an
independent non-profit organization with its own Board of Directors, distinct from PPFA.  But its
mission and goals remain the same since its founding.  As stated on their Web site, "The Guttmacher
Institute advances sexual and reproductive health and rights through an interrelated program of
research, policy analysis and public education designed to generate new ideas, encourage
enlightened public debate and promote sound policy and program development. The Institute's
overarching goal is to ensure the highest standard of sexual and reproductive health for all people
worldwide."  To that end, AGI maintains an impressive Web site, making widely available the facts
and figures they so carefully collect. [source: 
<extref href="http://www.guttmacher.org/about/mission.html">Guttmacher website</extref>]</p>
</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>Records include reports, data, publications, administrative and financial records, some
correspondence.  They document especially well the efforts of a fact-finding organization
determined to disseminate as widely as possible the data it collects so as to help shape policy to
increase access to reproductive health services, and to "ensure the highest standard of sexual
and reproductive health for all people worldwide."</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
        
</scopecontent>
 

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>Partially restricted access - contact the Sophia Smith Collection
for more information.</item>
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>


 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works created by the
Alan Guttmacher Institute in this collection.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be
owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish
reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to
identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Alan Guttmacher Institute Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>

<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The Alan Guttmacher Institute began donating their records to the Sophia Smith
Collection in 2013.  Periodic additions to the collection are expected.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by Kathleen Banks Nutter, 2014 </p>
</processinfo>

<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abortion -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Birth control -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Birth control -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Birth control -- Research -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reproductive rights -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Dryfoos, Joy G.</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Guttmacher, Alan Frank, 1898-1974</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Jaffee, Frederick S.</persname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Planned Parenthood Federation of America -- History -- Sources</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Center for Family Planning Program Development -- History -- Sources</corpname> 
</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Associated materials can be found in the Joy Dryfoos Papers and in the Planned
Parenthood Federation of America Records.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->