<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss435.xml//EN">mnsss435</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Cary Herz Papers, 1950s-2008</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Burd Schlessinger.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2012-02-23">February 23, 2012</date>
            <item>Finding aid content updated to reflect recent additions to collection.</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Herz, Cary</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Cary Herz papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1950s-2008</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 574</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">33 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(26 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Photographer. Photographic prints, slides, and contact sheets documenting events of political, social and economic significance in the U.S.,
circa 1970s to the early 2000s.  Topics include musicians and musical events, theater performances, political gatherings and demonstrations (including anti-Vietnam War), rape and sexual violence, religion and women in the ministry, homelessness, the ERA, women in sports, the rights of flight attendants, the National Organization for Women, and women artists.  Copies of Herz's published books are also in the collection, with related reviews and some original photographs.</abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc4859.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>International Women's Day Demonstration, photo by Cary Herz, n.d.</p></daodesc></dao>

 	<p>Photographer Cary Herz was born June 15, 1947  in New York City to Fred and Gertrud Herz.  After graduating from the Bronx High School of Science in 1965, she earned a BA from the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1970.  She worked as a freelance photographer in New York City from 1972-77, documenting the women's movement and women's sports for <title render="italic">Ms.</title> Magazine and other publications.  From 1977-84, she was a staff photographer for the <title render="italic">Newark Star-Ledger</title> covering the New York City metropolitan area on news, features, sports, personalities, fashion, and commerical assignments.  She moved to Albuquerque, New Mexico, in 1984 where she  worked as a news editor and videographer for KOAT-TV.  In 1987 she established her own business, Cary Herz Photography, doing freelance photojournalism, and editorial, corporate, and location photography.  She also worked as a New Mexico photo correspondent for <title render="italic">The New York Times</title> beginning in 1985.  Her photographs have appeared in <title render="italic">Time</title>, <title render="italic">Newsweek</title>, <title render="italic">PC World</title>, <title render="italic">People</title>, <title render="italic">Ms</title>, <title render="italic">Garden Design</title>, and on the Discovery Channel.   Her images have been published in many books including <title render="italic">Stones of Remembrance: The Historic Jewish Cemetery in Las Vega</title>s, New Mexico (1990); <title render="italic">Street Gangs in America</title> (1993); <title render="italic">The Pilgrimage to Chimayo: Contemporary Portrait of a Living Tradition</title> (1999); and her own book, <title render="italic">New Mexico's Crypto-Jews: Image and Memory</title> (2007).  In the spring of 2001, her work was exhibited at the Smithsonian Institution in Game Face: What Does a Woman Athlete Look Like.  In 2007 Herz received the <title render="italic">New Mexico Press Women</title>'s Woman of Achievement Award. She died of ovarian cancer in 2008.</p>


</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The collection includes photographic prints, slides, and contact sheets by Carry Herz, documenting events of political, social and economic significance in the U.S.,  circa 1970s to the early 2000s.   There is an emphasis on women and women's issues.   Topics include musicians and musical events, theater performances, political gatherings and demonstrations (including anti- Vietnam War), rape and sexual violence, religion and women in the ministry, homelessness, the ERA, women in sports, the rights of flight attendants, the National Organization for Women, and women artists.  Copies of Herz's published books are also in the collection, with related reviews and some original photographs. </p>

       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>Partially restricted access - contact the Sophia Smith Collection for more information.</item>
                         <item>Portions of collection are stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</item>
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works in this collection created by Cary Herz.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Cary Herz Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers  were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Cary Herz in 2007.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by Burd Schlessinger, 2007-2009. </p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Demonstrations--United States--Photographs</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Equal rights amendments--United States--Photographs</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">National Organization for Women--Photographs</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists--United States--Photographs</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Photojournalists</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Photographs</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women photographers--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women musicians--Photographs</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sports for women--United States--History--20th century</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Herz, Cary</persname> 
</controlaccess>


    <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
	<p>The <extref href="http://econtent.unm.edu/cdm4/indexpg.php">Palace of the Governors New Mexico Museum of History Photo
Archives</extref> houses a substantial collection of New Mexico images by Cary Herz.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>


</archdesc>
</ead>
