<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
   <eadheader audience="internal" findaidstatus="unverified-full-draft" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b">
      <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss109.xml//EN">mnsss109</eadid>
      <filedesc>
         <titlestmt>
            <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Frances Rich Papers, 1912-1980</titleproper>
            <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
            <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Susan Boone.</author>
            <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         </titlestmt>
         <publicationstmt>
            <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
            <address>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            <date encodinganalog="260$c">2003 </date>
            <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
         </publicationstmt>
      </filedesc>
      <profiledesc>
         <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded using Perl scripts and edited in XMetal 2.0. Encoded by Laura Cutter.
        <date>2003-06-12</date>
         </creation>
         <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
      </profiledesc>
      <revisiondesc>
         <change>
            <date normal="2005-09-23">2005-09-23</date>
            <item>mnsss109 converted from EAD 1.0 to 2002 by v1to02-5c.xsl (sy2003-10-15).</item>
         </change>
      </revisiondesc>
   </eadheader>
   <frontmatter id="front">
      <titlepage>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection Smith College
         
            </publisher>
         <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Frances Rich Papers, 1912-1980

      </titleproper>
         <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
         <num>MS 129

      </num>
         <date>Revised 2004

      </date>
         
         <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
         <p>©  2003  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
      </titlepage>
   </frontmatter>
   <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
      <did id="main">
         <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Rich, Frances</persname>
         </origination>
         <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Frances Rich papers</unittitle><unitdate encodinganalog="245$f" type="inclusive">1912-1980</unitdate>
         
         <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 129</unitid>
         <physdesc label="Quantity:">
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">5 boxes</extent>
            <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(2.75 linear ft.)</extent>
         </physdesc>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            </repository>
         <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Sculptor; Director, Smith College Public Relations; and Officer, United States Naval Reserve, World War II. Focuses primarily on her career as a sculptor, with a small amount of material on her work (as student and staff) at Smith College and in U.S. Navy.  Material includes correspondence, biographical articles, research files, clippings, exhibit catalogs (sculptures of notable people), posters, scrapbooks, and photographs.

      </abstract>
         <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
            <language langcode="eng">English.</language>
         </langmaterial>
      </did>
      <bioghist id="bioghist">
         
 
         <p>Irene Frances Luther Rich was born in Spokane, Washington, on 8 January 1910. She was named after her mother, Irene Frances Luther (film actress Irene Rich), but used Frances Rich to avoid confusion. She was educated in Swiss schools and at the School for Girls in Santa Barbara, California. She received a B.A. from Smith College in 1931 with a major in English Literature. </p>

<p>In the years following her graduation, Rich appeared in a number of Hollywood films and on stage. In 1933 she met sculptor, Malvina Hoffman, and studied with her in Paris for two years. When she returned to the U.S. Rich did intensive work at the Boston Museum School and established her own studio in New York City. Between 1937 and 1940 she was a resident student at Cranbrook Academy of Art in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, where she met sculptor Carl Milles, with whom she worked for the next eighteen years. </p>

<p>When the United States entered World War II, Rich began work as a mechanical draftsman at Lockheed Aircraft in Burbank, California. In 1942 she joined the Women's Reserve of the U.S. Navy as a Junior Grade Lieutenant, graduating in the first class of women at the Officer's Training School at Smith College.  She was posted to Washington, D.C. and became the National Director of Publicity for "V" Mail and traveling speaker for the Director of the WAVES. When she was discharged at the end of the war, Rich held the rank of Lt. Commander and received a citation for outstanding service from the Chief of Naval Personnel. </p>

<p> Following the war she did graduate work at Scripps College working with sculptor Albert Stewart, and at Columbia University. In 1947 she became the first Director of Public Relations at Smith College, a post she held until 1950 when she resigned to return to her art work. Rich has been featured in many publications and has exhibited in major art centers. Her works include portrait busts, wall and door panels, plaques and medallions, drawings, and statues. Subjects of her portrait busts include Alice Stone Blackwell, Lotte Lehmann, Margaret Sanger, Diego Rivera, and Katharine Hepburn. She also sculpted the Army-Navy Nurse Monument in Arlington National Cemetery in Washington, D.C. Much of her work is religious in nature and includes statues of St. Francis of Assisi, St. Joseph, Christ of the Sacred Heart, Our Lady of Combermere, St. Catherine of Siena, and various Madonnas. Rich established studios in California, and Payson, Arizona.</p>

<p> Frances Rich died at her home in Payson, Arizona, on October 14, 2007</p>
      </bioghist>
      <scopecontent id="scope">
         
         <p>The Frances Rich Papers focus primarily on her professional career as a sculptor, but include a small amount of material about her work as Public Relations Director at Smith College and her service in the U.S. Navy during World War II. The Papers are arranged  in three series:</p>

   <list>
	<item>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS </item>

	<item>SERIES II. ARTWORK</item>

	<item>SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS</item>
   </list>

<p>Types of material include correspondence, articles and clippings, memorabilia, photographs, exhibit catalogs, posters, and scrapbooks. Photographs are located in both SERIES II and III.
</p>
      </scopecontent>

    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restriction.  Copyright to materials created by Frances Rich is owned by her estate.  Copyright to materials created by persons other than Frances Rich may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns.  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.  </p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Frances Rich Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>Frances Rich donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1981 to 1996. Priscilla Cunningham donated her letters from Rich in 2002.  Additional materials were donated by Anthony Lame, son of Rich's college roommate, Mary Perkins Lame, in 2013.  </p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>This finding aid was revised by Susan Boone in 2004.</p> 
    </processinfo>

    <separatedmaterial id="add-separated">
	<p>Additional papers are housed at Cranbrook Academy of Art (Bloomfield Hills, Michigan), Getty Department of Humanities (Santa Monica, California), and Smith College Archives.  In addition there nine of Rich's works of art located on the Smith College Campus (see Appendix I for locations).  In 1982 Rich donated to the Sophia Smith Collection ten World War II WAVES recruitment posters.  These are not part of the Frances Rich Papers and are located in the Sophia Smith Collection flat files.</p>
    </separatedmaterial>


      <controlaccess id="subj">
         <head>Search Terms</head>
         
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Blackwell, Alice Stone, 1857-1950</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Hepburn, Katharine, 1907-2003</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Lehmann, Lotte</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Rich, Frances</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Rivera, Diego, 1886-1957</persname>
         <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966</persname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sculptors--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
         <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf">Smith College--Students--History--Sources</corpname>
         <geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">United States. Naval Reserve. Women's Reserve--History--Sources</geogname>
         <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women sculptors--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
      </controlaccess>


    <odd id="odd-app1">
	<head>Appendix I</head>
	<p>The following works of Frances Rich are located at Smith College:</p>
<table>

  <tgroup cols="2">  
     <colspec colname="1" colnum="1" colwidth="50"/> 
     <colspec colname="2" colnum="2" colwidth="50"/> 
  <thead>
    <row>
      <entry colname="1">Location</entry> 
      <entry colname="2">Work</entry> 
      <entry colname="3">Description</entry> 
    </row>
  </thead>

  <tbody>
  <row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Museum</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Bust: Laura Scales</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Museum</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Bust: Diego Rivera</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
  </row>  
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Museum</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Bust: Virgil Thompson</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
  </row>  
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Museum</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Panel for bronze door of the Lew Wentz Mausoleaum, Ponca City, Oklahoma</entry>
    <entry colname="3">depicting the sports of baseball, basketball, and football</entry>
</row>
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Museum</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Panel for bronze door of the Lew Wentz Mausoleaum, Ponca City, Oklahoma</entry>
    <entry colname="3">depicting the animals and their young</entry>
</row>
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Museum</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Study for St. Francis</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
</row>
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Museum</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Bas Relief for St. Peters Episcopal Church</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
</row>
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Library</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Bust: Herbert Davis</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
</row>
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Smith College Library</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Bust: Margaret Sanger</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
</row>
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Center for the Performing Arts</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Bust: Katharine Hepburn as Cleopatra</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
</row>
<row>
    <entry colname="1">Behind the President's House</entry>
    <entry colname="2">Statue: St. Francis of Assisi</entry>
    <entry colname="3"/>
</row>
  </tbody>
  </tgroup>
</table>

    </odd>

    <odd id="odd-app2">
	<head>Appendix II</head>
	<p>Alphabetical list of works by Frances Rich</p>
   <list>
	<item>Alice Stone Blackwell, 1958-59</item>
	<item>Army/Navy Nurse, Arlington National Cemetery, 1937</item>
	<item>Birds in Flight, 1980</item>
	<item>Carl Milles, 1971</item>
	<item>Ch. King Eric v. Konigbach ("Little King"), 1946</item>
	<item>Christ crucified, 1954</item>
	<item>Christ of the Sacred Heart, 1972</item>
	<item>Converse Colt, 1935</item>
	<item>Crucifix, 1954</item>
	<item>Diego Rivera, 1941</item>
	<item>Earl Wild, 1976</item>
	<item>Etruscan Rhythm, 1951</item>
	<item>Everett Kimball, 1931</item>
	<item>Harboe Nude, 1968</item>
	<item>Healer, 1969</item>
	<item>Jane and Little Billie, 1940</item>
	<item>Katharine Hepburn, 1958, 1961 </item>
	<item>Laura Scales, 1936</item>
	<item>Lew Wentz Mausoleum door, 1954</item>
	<item>Little Emily, 1972</item>
	<item>Look I'm Dancing, 1962</item>
	<item>Lotte Lehmann, 1952</item>
	<item>Madonna and Child, 1964</item>
	<item>Madonna and Child, 1970</item>
	<item>Margaret Sanger, 1956-57</item>
	<item>Mother and Child (fountain figure), 1951</item>
	<item>Mother and Child (seated), 1951</item>
	<item>Mother and Child, 1956</item>
	<item>Mother and Child, 1958</item>
	<item>Mother and Child, 1958</item>
	<item>Mother and Child, 1968	</item>
	<item>Negress, 1936</item>
	<item>Our Lady of Combermere, 1960</item>
	<item>Pelican, 1957</item>
	<item>Pieta, 1953</item>
	<item>Purdue University panel, 1939</item>
	<item>Purification, 1958</item>
	<item>Questing Madonna, 1954</item>
	<item>Roadrunner, 1972</item>
	<item>Seated Female Figure, 1958</item>
	<item>Spirit of the Grape, 1976-77</item>
	<item>St. Catherine of Sienna, 1968</item>
	<item>St. Francis, 1951-71</item>		
	<item>St. Joseph, 1956</item>
	<item>Taille Libre, 1936</item>
	<item>Vanity, 1961</item>
	<item>Virgil Thomson, 1961</item>
	<item>Wailing Woman, 1951</item>
	<item>Woman With Flower Pot, 1958</item>
   </list>
    </odd>



<dsc type="analyticover">
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS <unitdate>(1928-1970)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.5 linear feet</extent></physdesc>
	</did>
<scopecontent><p>This series contains three subseries: <title render="bold">Miscellaneous</title>, <title render="bold">Smith College</title>, and <title render="bold">U. S. Navy</title>. The <title render="bold">Miscellaneous </title>material consists of clippings and articles (1931-77), an interview done by Mayne Ober Park for the Boston Globe in 1940, and two scrapbooks (1952-59)  consisting primarily of clippings. In addition there is a small amount of correspondence. It consists of fourteen  letters Rich wrote to Priscilla Cunningham (1979 -88), one letter from Irene Rich to Frances Snow (1931), two letters written to Frances Rich, and three third party letters about the possibility of granting Rich a Smith College Medal.</p>

<p>The <title render="bold">Smith College</title> subseries contains printed material and memorabilia about Rich as a student, alumna, and as Director of Public Relations (1947-50). The latter also contains correspondence regarding the publication of <title render="italic">This Is Smith College</title> (1949).</p>

<p>The <title render="bold">U.S. Navy</title> material includes correspondence and printed material related to Rich's service with the U. S. Navy Reserve (1942-48, 1980) and her training, particularly officer training at Smith College. There is also correspondence related to an oral history of Admiral Nimitz and the WAVES (1969-70). </p>

<p>Photographs from these two subseries are located in SERIES III. 
</p></scopecontent>
</c01>
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES II. ARTWORK <unitdate>(1931-1980)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.75 linear feet</extent></physdesc>
	</did>
<scopecontent><p>This series is organized into two subseries:  <title render="bold">Works </title>and <title render="bold">Exhibitions</title>. <title render="bold">Works </title>consists mostly of photographs of Rich's work, but also contains some related correspondence and printed material. It is arranged by date.  (See Appendix II for an alphabetical list of these works.)  Statues of the Army-Navy Nurses  in Arlington National Cemetery, St Francis of Assisi,  Our Lady of Combermere, St. Catherine of Siena, and the Spirit of the Grape;  portrait busts of Lotte Lehmann, Diego Rivera, Margaret Sanger, and Katharine Hepburn; and drawings and photographs used for her work are represented in this subseries.   Two copies of <title render="italic">The Sculpture of Frances Rich</title> by Merle Armitage (1974) are also included.</p>

<p>The <title render="bold">Exhibitions </title>subseries includes photographs, correspondence, exhibit catalogs, articles and printed material. There is significant documentation of exhibitions at the Palm Springs Desert Museum (1969 and 1977) including two copies of <title render="italic">The Sculpture of Frances Rich: Frances Rich Retrospective Exhibition</title>, 7th February - 2nd March, 1969. 
</p></scopecontent>
</c01>
 
<c01 level="series">
	<did>
		<unittitle>SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS <unitdate>(1963-1988)</unitdate></unittitle>
<physdesc><extent>.25 linear feet</extent></physdesc>
	</did>
<scopecontent><p>This series contains approximately seventy-five  photographs, the bulk of which are photographs of Frances Rich alone (1914-77), with her mother Irene Rich, and with others. The latter include Laura Scales, Lottie Lehmann, Elissa Landi, Eugene Ormandy, John Ford, Diego Rivera, and Benjamin Wright. There are also photographs of Diego Rivera's fresco of Rich.  In addition there are Smith College photographs from Rich's student years (1928-31), her tenure as Smith College  Director of Public Relations (1947-50), and  from her service with the U.S. Navy.  Many of these are of her WAVES training at Smith College. There are also two photographs of Lotte Lehman, two of Irene Rich, and finally photographs of Rich's two California  studio/homes: Hope and Shumway ranches (1941-68). </p></scopecontent>
</c01>
</dsc>




<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Clippings, articles, and memorabilia,<unitdate> 1931-77, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Interview by Mayme Ober Park,<unitdate> 1940</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3-4</container>
 <unittitle>Scrapbooks,<unitdate> 1952-64</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>To Priscilla Cunningham,<unitdate> 1979-88</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous,<unitdate> 1931-58, 1977</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Smith College</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Student</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Scrapbook,<unitdate> 1931</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Articles,<unitdate> 1928-31, 1975-79</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Director of Public Relations</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Articles and printed material,<unitdate> 1947-50, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">This Is Smith College</title>: correspondence,<unitdate> 1949</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>U.S. Navy</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Clippings and articles,<unitdate> 1942-48, 1980, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Oral history of Admiral Nimitz and the WAVES: correspondence,<unitdate> 1969-70</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. ARTWORK</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Works</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">1-4</container>
 <unittitle>General,<unitdate> 1931-77, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Laura Scales,<unitdate> 1936</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Army/Navy Nurse, Arlington National Cemetery,<unitdate> 1937</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Diego Rivera,<unitdate> 1941</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>St. Francis of Assisi</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs,<unitdate> 1951-71</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Clippings, articles, and printed materials,<unitdate> 1952-66</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Lotte Lehmann,<unitdate> 1952</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Questing Madonna,<unitdate> 1954</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>St. Joseph,<unitdate> 1956</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Margaret Sanger,<unitdate> 1956-57</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>Pelican,<unitdate> 1957</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Seated female figure,<unitdate> 1958</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>Alice Stone Blackwell,<unitdate> 1958-59</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">17</container>
 <unittitle>Katharine Hepburn,<unitdate> 1958, 1961</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">18</container>
 <unittitle>Our Lady of Combermere,<unitdate> 1960</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">19</container>
 <unittitle>St. Catherine of Sienna,<unitdate> 1968</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">20</container>
 <unittitle>Roadrunner,<unitdate> 1972</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">21</container>
 <unittitle>Spirit of the Grape,<unitdate> 1976-77</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Birds in Flight,<unitdate> 1980</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs containing more than one work or unidentified works,<unitdate> 1977-78, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Drawings,<unitdate> 1944-46, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">The Sculpture of Frances Rich</title> by Merle Armitage,<unitdate> 1974 </unitdate>(two copies, both autographed)</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle>Exhibitions</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>California Palace of the Legion of Honor,<unitdate> 1955</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle>Palm Springs Desert Museum</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Frances Rich Retrospective Exhibition,<unitdate> 1969</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Frances Rich Sculpture Show,<unitdate> 1977</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous,<unitdate> 1963-75</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Catalogs,<unitdate> 1952-73</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle>Rich, Frances</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Alone,<unitdate> 1914-77</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>With others,<unitdate> 1937-72, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>With Irene Rich, <unitdate>circa 1912-46, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <unittitle>Smith College</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Student,<unitdate> 1928-31</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Director of Public Relations,<unitdate> 1947-50</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>U.S. Navy,<unitdate> 1941-47, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Lehmann, Lotte,<unitdate> 1953</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Rich, Irene, <unitdate>circa 1941</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c01>
 <c01>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Studios: Hope and Shumway Ranches,<unitdate> 1941-68, undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES IV. OVERSIZE MATERIALS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <unittitle>Sculpture of Margaret Sanger's head, and clipping, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Spirit of the Grape <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Birds in Flight, <unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Jane, Frances, and Irene Rich,<unitdate> 1927</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Frances and Irene Rich, <unitdate>circa 1942</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Vice Admiral Morris Denfeldt,<unitdate>undated</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Certificate from the American Bicentennial Research Institute,<unitdate> 1974</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Shumway Ranch, Palm Desert, California</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Plans for studio and caretakers cottage</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Bureau of Land Management map</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Posters</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>St. Francis of Asissi</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Spirit of the Grape</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Seated Woman with Child</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="map-case">Flat File dwr 33</container>
 <unittitle>Harboe Nude</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

   </archdesc>
</ead>
