<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss245.html">mnsss245</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Annette Hoyt Flanders Papers, 1923-1991</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
        <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
       </titlestmt>
       <publicationstmt>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
         <address>
           <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
         </address>
         <date calendar="gregorian" era="ce">© 2005</date>
         <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by
 Margaret Jessup and Jennifer Smar.
           <date>2006-04-07</date>
 <!-- CHANGE TO TODAY'S DATE IF NECESSARY -->
     </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter id="front">
    <titlepage>
      <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb />Smith College<lb /></publisher>
   <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Annette Hoyt Flanders Papers, 1923-1991</titleproper>
   <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
   <num>MS 501</num>
   <date encodinganalog="260$c">2005</date>
   
     <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon
 Foundation.</sponsor>
       <p>© 2005  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
   </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
 <did id="main">
 	<head>Collection Overview</head>
 <origination label="Creator:">
     <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Flanders, Annette Hoyt, 1887-1946</persname>
 </origination>
   <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Annette Hoyt Flanders Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1923-1991</unitdate>
 <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 501</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">11 boxes</extent>
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(5.75 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
    <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>

  </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            </repository>
 <!-- MRJ: EDIT ABSTRACT  -->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Landscape architect. Collection consists of files compiled by Patricia L. Filzen in preparation for writing her M.A. thesis on landscape architecture (1988, University of Wisconsin-Madison).  While the files pertain primarily to Annette Hoyt Flanders, there are materials about other practitioners in the field, as well.  Glass slides of Flanders' work are also included.
    </abstract>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
    <head>Biographical Note</head>
<dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc1589.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>Astor Doorway painted by <lb /> Annette Hoyt Flanders, n.d.</p></daodesc></dao> 
       <p>Annette Hoyt Flanders was born in Milwaukee, WI, the daughter of Frank M. Hoyt, a
prominent attorney, and Hettie Pamelia Hoyt.  She received her early education from tutors
and at private schools.  She majored in botany at Smith College, earning her B.S. in 1918,
and received her M.A. in landscape architecture from the University of Illinois.  She
studied civil engineering at Marquette University, as well as design, architecture and the
history of architecture at the Sorbonne.  She served with the American Red Cross in France
in 1918 and 1919.  Upon her return, she joined the landscape architecture firm of Vitale,
Brinckerhoff, and Geiffert in New York, where she was responsible for design and for
supervising planting.  She opened her own office in 1922.  The scope of her practice was
extensive, and included private estates, real estate subdivisions, the grounds of industrial
plants, recreational developments, and exhibit gardens throughout the United States.
Flanders became a member of the American Society of Landscape Architects in 1923, and was
elected a Fellow in 1942.  In 1932, she was awarded the Medal of Honor in Landscape
Architecture of the Architectural League of New York.  She relocated her office to Milwaukee
in 1943.  Flanders lectured extensively to horticultural and botanical societies, schools,
and garden and women's clubs, and also appeared often on radio talk shows.  She wrote
extensively for numerous publications, including <title render="italic">House and Garden</title>, <title render="italic">Country Life in America</title>,
and <title render="italic">House Beautiful</title>.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
       <p>This collection consists of files compiled by Patricia L. Filzen in preparation for
writing her M.A. thesis on landscape architecture (1988, University of Wisconsin-Madison).
While the files pertain primarily to Annette Hoyt Flanders, there are materials about other
practitioners in the field, as well.  Glass slides of Flanders' work are also included.</p>
            <p> NOTE: The container list for this collection is available in the Sophia Smith Collection.  Please contact us to request a copy.</p>

</scopecontent>

     <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
      <head>Information on Use</head>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
         <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
          <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection.</p>
          <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to
use.</p>
<p>Partially restricted access - contact the Sophia Smith Collection for more information.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
         <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
        </userestrict>
    </descgrp>
      <prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Annette Hoyt Flanders Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
Northampton, Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>
     <accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
        <head>Additions to the Collection</head>
          <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
      </accruals>
</descgrp>

   <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
       <head>Search Terms</head>
<!-- HIGHLIGHT EACH SEARCH TERM AND CLICK ON APPROPRIATE SUBJECT CLIPS -->
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Flanders, Annette Hoyt, 1887-1946</persname> 
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Landscape architecture-United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Landscape design-United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Landscape gardening-United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women landscape architects--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Gardens-United States--Design--20th century</subject>

 </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead><!-- END OF FILE -->