<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">


  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss564.xml//EN">mnsss564</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Swanee Hunt Papers, 1968-2013 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 14.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">September 30, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Hunt, Swanee</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Swanee Hunt papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1968-2013 (ongoing)</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 721</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">99 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(155 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>, <language langcode="ger">German</language>

</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Ambassador; Clergy member; Composer; Feminist; Foundation executive; Marriage counselor; Philanthropist; Political activist; Professor; Photographer; Reproductive health advocate; Rancher. The papers well document Ambassador Hunt's service as the American Ambassador in
Austria during a most volatile period and her efforts to provide programming to assist, especially women, in the aftermath of the break up of the Soviet Union and during the Bosnian War.  Materials include correspondence, speeches, conference programs, internal memos, daily schedules, and newspaper articles.  Also well represented within the papers are the activities of the Hunt Alternatives Fund including correspondence, financial records and annual reports.  Monthly reports, as well as income and expenses, document the family property in Colorado, the Columbine Ranch, over
several years.          [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>


<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Swanee Grace Hunt was born May 1, 1950 in Dallas, Texas, the youngest of four children born to the oil tycoon H.L. Hunt and Ruth Ray.  However, not until her father's first wife died did Swanee Hunt's parents marry in 1957 and it was only then that she and her siblings moved into the Hunt mansion, built to resemble its namesake, Mount Vernon.  This unusual early childhood and her mother's profoundly fundamentalist faith had a lasting impact on Swanee Hunt's world view.  While she had hoped to attend college in the east, her ultra-conservative father refused so Swanee Hunt began college in her hometown at Southern Methodist University.  At the age of twenty, she married Mark Meeks, a seminary student, and moved to Fort Worth where she graduated from Texas Christian University in 1972 with a degree in philosophy.  A year later, the couple moved to Heidelberg,Germany where Meeks served as pastor for an English-speaking Baptist church.  Although she was able to complete a master's degree in counseling, this was a difficult time for Hunt who was unhappy in her marriage and unsure what direction she should take in life.  In 1977, the couple returned to the US, settling in Denver where Hunt entered the Iliff School of Theology where she earned a Master's degree in Religion (1979) and a doctorate in Theology (1986).  Despite ongoing marital problems, Swanee Hunt gave birth to daughter Lillian in 1982; however, the marriage soon ended.  In 1985 she married Charles Ansbacher, a symphonic conductor and divorced father of a teenage son, Henry.  In 1987,  amidst a growing number of professional responsibilities, Swanee gave birth to Theodore Ansbacher-Hunt.</p>

<p>After her father's death in 1974, Swanee Hunt had a sizable personal fortune at her disposal and throughout the 1970s, she weighed various options of how she could put some of her wealth to good use, creating positive and sustainable social change at the grassroots level.   She had long been concerned about mental health issues, education and women's empowerment. Thus, in 1981, the Hunt Alternatives Fund was founded in Denver.  According to their Web site, "Hunt Alternatives brings daring goals, distinctive perspectives, innovative practices, and extraordinary talent to some of the world's most complex and injurious challenges...and  has contributed more than $100 million to social change through a blend of grantmaking and operating programs."  In 1986, Hunt was a co-founder of the Women's Fund of Colorado which she also led for its first six years.  More recently, in 2006, with her sister, Helen LaKelly Hunt, Swanee Hunt created Women Moving Millions, an organization designed to encourage women to give large gifts to support programing directed to empower other women, nationally and globally.  In honor of her late husband, Charles Ansbacher, who died in 2010, she founded the Free for All Concert Fund which provides free arts programming in the city of Boston. </p> <p>As her philanthropy focused more and more on issues of public policy, Hunt was increasingly drawn into the world of politics.  In 1992, she vigorously campaigned and generously donated to Bill Clinton's 1992 presidential bid.  Winning the White House, Clinton first appointed Hunt to his transition team and then named her Ambassador to Austria.  She served at the height of the Bosnian War and urged that the US government step up its efforts to secure peace in this embattled region, a message not always well received back home.  Nonetheless, Hunt did what she could and directed much of her efforts at women in the affected areas, organizing conferences designed to promote East- West learning, such as "Bosnian Women Stepping into Politics" (1999) and "Vital Voices: Women in Democracy" (1997) at which then First Lady Hillary Clinton gave the keynote address.  But by 1997, Hunt was ready for a change and the opportunity to do so came when the Kennedy School of Government at Harvard University offered her the task of establishing the Women and Public Policy Program. Since stepping down as Director of the Program in 2008, she has continued on at the Kennedy School as the Eleanor Roosevelt Lecturer in Public Policy.   Since then, Hunt founded and directs the Institute for Inclusive Security, in which "Women are an essential tool to prevent violence, stop war, and restore communities after deadly conflicts."  In addition, she focuses on demanding an end to commercial sex around the globe as well as  her "Political Parity campaign which works to elect more women to higher office as such "improves policy outcomes and lifts public trust."  Most recently, she has been active in Iran and Rwanda, spearheading efforts there to improve the lives of women and girls.</p>  <p>A talented classical composer and photographer, Swanee Hunt is also the author of three books: <title render="italic">Worlds Apart: Bosnian Lessons for Global Security</title> (2011); her memoir, <title render="italic">Half-Life of a Zealot</title> (2006); and, <title render="italic">This Was Not Our War: Bosnian Women Reclaiming the Peace</title> (2004).  She has also published dozens of articles in newspapers and journals, both in the US and in Europe, serves on multiple boards and foundations, and has received several honorary degrees and awards, including induction into the National Women's Hall of Fame in 2007.</p> <p>[source: 
<extref href="http://www.swaneehunt.com/policy-areas/">Swanee Hunt's website</extref>]</p>

</bioghist>

<scopecontent id="scope">
      
     <p>The papers well document Ambassador Hunt's service as the American Ambassador in Austria during a most volatile period and her efforts to provide programming to assist, especially women, in the aftermath of the break up of the Soviet Union and during the Bosnian War.  Materials include correspondence, speeches, conference programs, internal memos, daily schedules, and newspaper articles.  Also well represented within the papers are the activities of the Hunt Alternatives Fund including correspondence, financial records and annual reports.  Monthly reports, as well as income and expenses, document the family property in Colorado, the Columbine Ranch, over several years. Finally, also included are some personal papers including manuscript drafts, correspondence, speeches, photographs, and both undergraduate and graduate school papers and notes.</p> 
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>
 

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
                         <item>Partially restricted access - contact the Sophia Smith Collection for more information.</item>
                         <item>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>


 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works in this
collection created by Swanee Hunt. Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those
individuals or their assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations
beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy all
copyright holders.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Swanee Hunt Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>

<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>Swanee Hunt began donating her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2013</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by Kathleen Banks Nutter, May 2014</p>
</processinfo>

<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Ambassadors -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Austria -- Politics and government</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Authors -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Bosnia and Hercegovina -- Politics and government -- 1992-</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Clergy -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Colorado -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Composers -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminism -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">International relations -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Mental health services -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Philanthropists -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Political activists -- United States -- Biography</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Photographers -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Poverty -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reproductive health -- Developing countries</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Reproductive health -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">United States -- Foreign relations -- 1993-2001</geogname> 
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Vienna (Austria) -- Description and travel</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women ambassadors -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women and peace</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in development</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Political activity -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Youth -- Services for -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Yugoslav War, 1991-1995 -- Atrocities</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Yugoslav War, 1991-1995 -- Women -- Bosnia and Hercegovina</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Yugoslav War, 1991-1995 -- Protest movements</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Clinton, Bill, 1946-</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Clinton, Hillary Rodman</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Ansbacher, Charles</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Hunt, Swanee</persname>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">John F. Kennedy School of Government. Women and Public Policy Program</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">The Institute for Inclusive Security</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Women Waging Peace (organization)</corpname>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh"> Hunt Alternatives Fund</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Women Moving Millions</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Women's Foundation of Colorado</persname> 

</controlaccess>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
          <p>Additional papers of Swanee Hunt are at the Denver Public Library</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
