<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss553.xml//EN">mnsss553</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Silvia Tennenbaum Papers, 1944-2012</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2014">2014</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">January 27, 2014</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>

        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Tennenbaum, Silvia</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Silvia Tennenbaum
Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1944-2012</unitdate>
      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 499</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">7 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(7 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Author. Born in Frankfurt, Germany, her family fled Nazi Germany in 1936 and eventually emigrated to America. She married Rabbi Lloyd Tennenbaum in 1951 (divorced 1986). Her first novel Rachel the Rabbi's Wife (1978) portrays her own life experiences.  She also the author of the novel Yesterday's Streets (1981), about life amongst upper-middle class Jews in Frankfurt, Germany in the early twentieth century. Her papers include almost seventy years of personal journals beginning in 1944 with descriptions of her travels in Europe, Israel, Germany, Russia, and the U.S. There are also notes for her novels.
        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>

</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Biographical Note</head>
     <p>Silvia Pfeiffer Tennenbaum was born in Frankfurt, Germany, the daughter of Lotti Clara Stern
and Erich Pfeiffer-Belli.  Her parents divorced in 1930 and in 1934, her mother married William
Steinberg, a conductor who would lead several symphonies, including the Pittsburgh Symphony
Orchestra (1952-1976).  The Steinberg family fled Nazi Germany in 1936 and young Silvia spent the
next two years living in Basel, Switzerland with her Aunt, Getrude Ritz-Stern.  In 1938, reunited
with her mother, stepfather and stepbrother, she emigrated to America where the family settled in
New Rochelle, New York. Silvia Pfeiffer graduated from New Rochelle High School in 1946; she then
attended Barnard College, earning a BA with honors in Art History in 1950. She started graduate
school at Columbia University but left in 1951 upon her marriage to Lloyd Tennenbaum, a rabbi.  The
Tennenbaums lived the next seven years in Lynchburg, Virginia--it was during these years that
Silvia Tennenbaum gave birth to three sons and started her writing career.  Twenty years later, she
would parlay that experience into her first book, <title render="italic">Rachel the Rabbi's Wife</title> (1978).  After a brief
stint in Plainfield, New Jersey, Lloyd Tennenbaum was appointed rabbi to two congregations on Long
Island's North Shore and the family settled in Huntington, New York where Silvia Tennenbaum began
writing in earnest.  In 1981, after thirty years of marriage, the Tennenbaums separated and were
divorced in 1986.  By then, Silvia Tennenbaum had returned to graduate school at Columbia
University and completed her MA in art history in 1983.   An avid traveller and prolific diarist,
she is also the author of <title render="italic">Yesterday's Streets</title> (1981), a fictionalized account of life amongst
upper-middle class Jews in Frankfurt, Germany from the start of the twentieth century to the Nazi
take-over.  In 2012, the city that Silvia Tennenbaum had fled from as a young child to escape the
Holocaust decades earlier named <title render="italic">Yesterday's Streets</title> as their "Book of the Year."</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
     <p>The Pspers consist of almost 70 years of Tennenbaum's personal journals beginning in 1944.
They include descriptions of her travels in  Europe, Israel, Germany, Russia, and the U.S..  There
are also notes for her novels.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	       <list type="simple">
                         <item>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance
notice.</item>
                         <item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be
difficult to use.</item>
                         <item>Researchers must sign an Access Agreement Form before using this
collection, agreeing to protect the confidentiality of living persons.</item>
                     </list></p>
</accessrestrict>

 <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works of Silvia
Tennenbaum within this collection.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those
individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or
quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy
the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Silvia Tennenbaum Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>

<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this
record.</p>
</accruals>
<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>Silvia Tennenbaum began donating her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2012.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
           <p>Accessioned by  Kathleen Banks Nutter, 2013 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Holocaust survivors -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Marriage -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Divorce -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Jewish women -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Jews -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">New York (State) -- Long Island</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women rabbis -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Motherhood -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Authors, American -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Travel writers -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Tennenbaum, Silvia</persname> 

</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>