<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss499.xml//EN">mnsss499</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Agnes Lauga Papers, 1940-1989</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2010">2010</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 12.0. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">July 26, 2010</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
         <origination label="Creator:">
            <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Lauga, Agnes</persname>
        </origination>
        <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Agnes Lauga papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1940-1989</unitdate>
       <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 577</unitid>
   <physdesc label="Quantity:">
           <extent encodinganalog="300$a">2 boxes</extent>
           <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(2.5 linear ft.) </extent>
   </physdesc>

   <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
        <language langcode="eng">English</language>
   French
   </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
             <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
             <address>
                <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
                <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
             </address>
          </repository>
          
           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Social worker; Social work administrator and educator. The papers include
correspondence, photographs, memorabilia, writings by Lauga and others, teaching materials, and other documents related to
Lauga's teaching and administrative work at the Albert Einstein School of Medicine and her involvement in the Alumnae Association of the Smith College School for Social Work.  

        [NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
Collection if you would like one sent to you.]
         </abstract>
        
   </did>

   <bioghist id="bioghist">
          
       <p> Agnes Louise Cosgrove Thénaud Lauga was born  February 6, 1911 to Elizabeth and John
   Cosgrove in Providence, RI.  She earned her Bachelor's degree from Pembroke College, Brown
   University (1932), her Master's degree from Brown University (1937);  and her MSW from the Smith
   College School for Social Work in 1944.  From 1944 to 1947, she worked at Family Service in
   Cincinnati, Ohio, and went on to work at the Central Clinic of the University of Cincinnati
   School of Medicine, from 1947 to 1955.  She was recruited as Director of Psychiatric Social Work
   at the Albert Einstein College of Medicine, where she worked from 1955 to 1970, to forge the
   college's newly-established psychiatric social service program; she then served as Associate
   Director and Acting Director of Social Work.  Lauga also held faculty appointments at the
   University of Cincinnati and Yeshiva University.  As an alumna, she was deeply involved in the
   Smith College School for Social Work, serving on its Governance Board, on search committees, and
   in key positions in the Alumnae Association, including President and Chair of the Annual Fund.
   Lauga wrote extensively, taught at workshops and institutes, and served on panels of major
   professional associations.  In 1985, She received the Smith College School for Social Work's Day-
   Garrett Award.  Agnes married Franc Thénaud in 1937.  He died while serving as a translator at
   the Nuremberg Trials.  She later married Henri Lauga and they lived in New York.  She died in
   2007.</p>
   </bioghist>
   
  <scopecontent id="scope">
        
       <p>The Agnes Lauga Papers include correspondence, writings by Lauga and others, teaching materials, and
  other documents related to Lauga's teaching and administrative work at the Albert Einstein School
  of Medicine and her involvement in the Alumnae Association of the Smith College School for Social
  Work.  Photographs, awards, and memorabilia are also included.</p>
         <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith
  Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>

  </scopecontent>
   <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                      <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the  Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                      <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be  difficult to use.</p>
                       <p>  Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</p>
  </accessrestrict>


  <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
               <p>The material in this collection may be protected by copyright. It is the  responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights  for permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Permission must  also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
  </userestrict>
  <prefercite id="admin-cite">
          <head>Preferred Citation</head>
            <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this  collection:</p>
            <p>Agnes Lauga Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton,  Mass.</p>
  </prefercite>


  
  <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
            <p>The Agnes Lauga Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection  Clara Genetos in 2007.</p>
  </acqinfo>
  
  <processinfo id="admin-process">
            <p>Accessioned by Burd Schlessinger, 2007 </p>
  </processinfo>
  
  <controlaccess id="subj">
      <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Social work education--United States--History--Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Social work--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
      	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Social workers--United States--History--Sources</subject>
      	
      	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Lauga, Agnes</persname> 

  </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
