<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss275.html">mnsss275</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Clara Morris Papers, 1874-1901</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
        <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
       </titlestmt>
       <publicationstmt>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
         <address>
           <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
         </address>
         <date calendar="gregorian" era="ce">© 2005</date>
         <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by
 Margaret Jessup and Jennifer Smar.
         <date>2006-04-07</date>
 <!-- CHANGE TO TODAY'S DATE IF NECESSARY -->
     </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter id="front">
    <titlepage>
      <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection Smith College </publisher>
   <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Clara Morris Papers, 1874-1901</titleproper>
   <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
   <num>MS 106</num>

   <date encodinganalog="260$c">2005</date>
   
     <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon
 Foundation.</sponsor>
       <p>© 2005  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
   </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
 <did id="main">
 	<head>Collection Overview</head>
 <origination label="Creator:">
     <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Morris, Clara, 1848-1925</persname>
 </origination>
   <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Clara Morris papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1874-1901</unitdate>
 <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 106</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">1 box</extent>
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(.5 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
    <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>

  </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
            </repository>
 <!-- MRJ: EDIT ABSTRACT  -->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Actress; Journalist. Includes original manuscripts for <title render="italic">Life on the Stage: My Personal Experiences and Recollections</title> (1901), and several short stories; memorabilia; photographs; and 2 letters.     </abstract>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
    

       <p>Actress Clara Morris was born in Toronto, probably 17 Mar 1847, the eldest child of a bigamous marriage. When she was three her father, whose name was La Montagne, was exposed as a bigamist and her mother moved with Clara to Cleveland, where they adopted Clara's grandmother's name, Morisson. Young Clara received only scanty schooling. In circa 1860 she became a ballet girl in the resident company of the Cleveland Academy of Music, shortening her name to Morris at that time. After nine years of training with that company she played a leading lady at Wood's Theatre in Cincinnati in 1869. She then appeared in Halifax, Nova Scotia for a summer and with Joseph Jefferson in Louisville before going to New York City in 1870. She made her New York debut in September in "Man and Wife," directed by Augustin Daly at his Fifth Avenue Theatre. The role had come to her by chance, but she made such an impression in it that Daly starred her in a series of highly emotional roles over the next three years in such plays as "No Name," "Delmonico's," "L'Article 47," "Alixe," "Jezebel," and "Madeline Morel." She left Daly in 1873 and in November of that year starred under A.M. Palmer's management in "The Wicked World" at the Union Square Theatre.</p>
<p>
Over the next few years Morris had great successes in "Camille" in 1874, "The New Leah" in 1875, "Miss Multon" (an American version of a French version of "East Lynne"), her most popular role, in 1876, "Jane Eyre" in 1877, and "The New Magdalen" in 1882. She also toured extensively, especially in the 1880s, and everywhere mesmerized audiences with her emotional power. Although neither a great beauty nor a great artist, nor trained in elocution or stagecraft, she had an instinctive genius for portraying the impassioned and often suffering heroines of French melodrama. </p>

<p>The passing of the vogue for that sort of theatre, together with her uncertain health, brought her career to a close in the 1890s. In retirement in Riverdale, New York, she contributed articles on acting to various magazines, wrote a daily newspaper column for ten years, and published numerous books, including <title render="italic">A Silent Singer</title>, 1899; <title render="italic">Little Jim Crow and Other Stories for Children</title>, 1900; <title render="italic">Life on the Stage: My Personal Experiences and Recollections</title>, 1901; <title render="italic">Stage Confidences</title>, 1902; <title render="italic">A Pasteboard Crown</title>, 1902; <title render="italic">The Trouble Woman, 1904</title>; <title render="italic">The Life of a Star</title>, 1906; <title render="italic">Left in Charge</title>, 1907; <title render="italic">New East Lynne</title>, 1908; <title render="italic">A Strange Surprise</title>, 1910; and <title render="italic">Dressing-Room Receptions</title>, 1911. In 1904 she returned to the stage in a revival of "The Two Orphans," and she later appeared in vaudeville. She died in New Canaan, Connecticut, on November 20, 1925.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
       <p>This small collection contains three volumes of original manuscripts for her memoir <title render="italic">Life on the Stage: My Personal Experiences and Recollections</title> (published 1901), with unpublished passages on John Wilkes Booth; plus manuscripts for several short stories, dated 1900.  Also included are theatre programs dating from 1874 to 1888, photographs, two letters, and an obituary.</p>
            <p> NOTE: The container list for this collection is available in the Sophia Smith Collection.  Please contact us to request a copy.</p>

</scopecontent>

     <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
      <head>Information on Use</head>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
         <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
          <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection.</p>
          <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to
use.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
         <p>Copyright to unpublished materials may be  owned by the creator, or their heirs
or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of
all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also
be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
        </userestrict>
    </descgrp>
      <prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Clara Morris Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton,
Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>
</descgrp>

   <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
       <head>Search Terms</head>
<!-- HIGHLIGHT EACH SEARCH TERM AND CLICK ON APPROPRIATE SUBJECT CLIPS -->
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Actresses--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women in the theater--United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women journalists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Booth, John Wilkes, 1838-1865</persname> 
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Morris, Clara, 1848-1925</persname> 

 </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
