<ead>
  <eadheader langencoding="iso639-2b" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601"
repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924" audience="internal" id="head"
relatedencoding="MARC21">


  <eadid publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss515.xml//EN" countrycode="us"
mainagencycode="mnsss">mnsss515</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Center for the Advancement of Women Records, 1993-
2010</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2012">2012</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 13.0.
Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="yyyy-mm-dd">February 20, 2012</date>
    </creation>
    <langusage>Finding aid written in
        <language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English.</language>
      </langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
<!-- Edit main entry label for Organizations, Subject Colls and OH colls  -->
        <origination label="Creator:">
     <corpname  encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Center for the Advancement of Women</corpname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Center for the Advancement of Women Records</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:">1993-2010</unitdate>
      <unitid label="Collection Number:" encodinganalog="099" countrycode="us"
repositorycode="mnsss">MS 667</unitid>
<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">55 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(55 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial label="Language of Material:" encodinganalog="546">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
           <!-- MRJ Edit as needed-->
           <abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">
            Women's advocacy group. The records document the daily activities of a feminist non-prift research and advocacy group.  Major topics covered: women's rights, women's health, reproductive rights, women of color, affirmative action, and domestic violence.
         </abstract>
       
</did>

 <!--  Add paragraph marks to text -->
<bioghist id="bioghist">
       <head>Historical Note</head>
     <p>Co-founded and led by Faye Wattleton, the CFAW was "a not-for-profit institution dedicated to research-based education and advocacy for women.  An independent, non-partisan organization founded in 1995," and known as the Center for Gender Equality until 2002, its mission was "to conduct national opinion research among women to measure experiences in their daily lives. This research presents a profile of women that [was hopefully] used to educate opinion leaders, policy makers and the general public."  One of the significant research projects undertaken by the CFAW beginning in the late 1990s and lasting several years was "Progress and Perils: A New Agenda for Women," "a two-part landmark survey of over 3,300 American women" that measured their various opinions re: various topics such as domestic abuse, sexual assault, affirmative action, and abortion rights, in which responses were tabulated so as to reflect any differences based on race.  Other research projects included the Domestic Violence Report (an outgrowth to the "Progress and Perils" results), a National Security Report in response to 9/11, the Women on Religion Survey, and the Women in Science, Engineering and Technology Report.  Throughout its fifteen years, the CFAW depended on donors, large and small, to do its work and, after years of financial struggle, the organization closed down.</p>
     <p>[source: CFAW's former Web site,  <extref href="http://www.advancewomen.org">http://www.advancewomen.org</extref> (retrieved 9/15/10)]</p>
</bioghist>
 <!--  Add paragraph marks to text -->
<scopecontent id="scope">
      <head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
       <p> The records document the daily activities of a feminist advocacy organization.  Major topics covered: women's rights, women's health, reproductive rights, women of color, affirmative action, and domestic violence. Types of materials include research files, reports, minutes, general office files, correspondence, emails, calendars, publications, mailings, biographical information, audiovisual materials, photographs, funding, and financial records. Of particular interest are the foundation files which document the ways in which organizations such as the CFAW had to present themselves so as to receive much-needed funds.  Also well documented is the way in which the CFAW, primarily through the person of Faye Wattleton, made good use of various media outlets, from television appearances to Web blogs.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
       
</scopecontent>
 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
		<p>The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
	  	 <list type="simple">
    		<item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
    		<item>Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.</item>
    		<item>Collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.</item>
		</list>
</p>
</accessrestrict>


<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works in this collection created by the Center for the Advancement of Women.  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>
<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Center for the Advancement of Women Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>



<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The records were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by CFAW board members Janit Greenwood and Grada Fischer in 2010.</p>
</acqinfo>

<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Accessioned by  Kathleen Banks Nutter, August 2011 </p>
</processinfo>
<!-- Encode Subject terms -->
<controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abortion -- Law and legislation -- United States -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Abortion -- Moral and ethical aspects -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">African American women -- Social conditions -- History -- 20th century</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Birth control -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Domestic violence -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Feminists -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Hispanic American women -- Social conditions -- History -- 20th century</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Nonprofit organizations -- Management</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Pro-choice movement -- United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sex discrimination against women -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- Violence against -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women -- United States -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's Health -- United States</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Wattleton, Faye</persname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Center for the Advancement of Women (New York, N.Y.)</corpname> 
</controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->

