<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss235.xml//EN">mnsss235</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Edith Roelker Curtis Papers, 1916-1989</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Amanda Izzo.</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2011">2011</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Wendy Essery. 
		<date normal="2011-10-21">2011-10-21</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	  </langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Curtis, Edith Roelker</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Edith Roelker Curtis papers</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1916-1989</unitdate>
	
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 39</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">26 boxes</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(16 Linear Ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College </addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		Author, Poet, Biographer, Diarist. Papers include correspondence, photographs, line-a-day diaries; scrapbooks, financial records, and material relating to her literary career, including published and unpublished manuscripts, poetry, stories, articles, publicity, reviews, fan mail, research material, and forty-two volumes of diaries. Curtis' introspections give a perspective on a life's journey that included a troubled marriage and complex family life; a struggle to make a career as a writer; and day-to-day observations of New England life, from Boston elite society to small town New Hampshire.
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	
	<p>The author Edith Goddard Roelker was born on July 29, 1893 to William and Eleanor (Jenckes) Roelker. The family's roots in Rhode Island stretched back to the colonial era, and Edith grew up in a privileged environment on an East Greenwich homestead and a city residence in Providence. With the marriage strained by Eleanor's alcoholism, the Roelkers divorced in 1901. Edith attended school in Providence and lived for a time with an aunt in Cincinnati. She subsequently attended the elite Miss Porter's School in Farmington, Connecticut between 1909 and 1912 but left before receiving a degree. She made her society debut in 1912. Two years later, she married Charles Pelham Curtis, Jr., a Harvard Law student and member of a similarly distinguished Boston family. Charles became a partner at the Choate, Hall, and Stuart firm, and the couple lived in Boston's Back Bay neighborhood until they moved to Norfolk, Massachusetts in 1924. Their first child, Sarah (called Sally), was born in 1915, followed by Anita (1917), Charles (1919), William (1923), and Richard (1924). During the First World War, Edith volunteered for the Red Cross. She was active in Boston club life, becoming a member of the Nucleus, Chilton Club, and Boston Sewing Circle (a predecessor to the Junior League), among others. The groups functioned as hubs of high society, but they also sponsored cultural events and volunteer activities. Edith maintained an interest in literary and social clubs throughout her life. </p>

<p>Edith Curtis' literary ambitions were awakened after the birth of her third child, and she undertook coursework in composition and English literature at Radcliffe College. In the 1920s, she would become a steady diarist, writing daily ruminations on travels and home life, reflecting on the progress of her writing career, and exploring writing projects. Her personal papers contain an extensive run of diaries, primarily spanning from 1926 to 1977. With brief newspaper articles, Curtis entered the professional realm of publishing in the 1920s. Inspired by the celebration of the Boston tercentennial, she released a full-length book, <title render="italic">Anne Hutchinson: A Biography</title>, with the Washburn and Thomas publishing house in 1930. As her writing career developed, her marriage foundered. Charles' extramarital affairs prompted a separation in 1934 when Edith discovered in a gossip column that her husband had registered at a New York hotel with his mistress. Charles obtained a divorce in Reno, Nevada in 1936 and soon married Frances Prentice. Given the prominent standing of the family, the divorce caused scandal in Boston social circles. Edith's continuing discontent with her ex-husband led her to obstruct contact between Charles and the children, complicating family relationships. While maintaining an active social life and overseeing a large household, Edith continued to write as her children grew up and left the home. Short works appeared in magazines and newspapers throughout the 1930s. A second historical biography, <title render="italic">Lady Sarah Lennox, An Irrepressible Stuart</title>, was published by Putnam in 1946 and was also released in London and Brazil. This extensively researched narration of the life of the notorious royal consort was reportedly enjoyed by the British royal family and Winston Churchill. A facsimile reprint of this book was issued in 2007.</p>

<p>Moving to Dublin, New Hampshire in the mid-1950s, where she would remain until her death in 1977, Edith became an avid gardener and bird-watcher while still publishing historical sketches, book reviews, and travel essays. Her most noted book, <title render="italic">A Season in Utopia, The Story of Brook Farm</title>, was published in 1961 and reprinted in 1971. Her history of the Massachusetts Transcendentalist commune was widely reviewed, and it won the National League of American Pen Women's 1962 prize for the best work of non-fiction. Curtis later assisted greatly in the successful effort to designate the endangered site of Brook Farm in West Roxbury a national historical landmark. </p>

<p>Curtis' histories interwove a narrative style with considerable scholarly research, providing transcriptions of primary documents and detailing the context of historical dramas. In the 1960s, Edith became an increasingly prolific writer of fiction and verse, exploring more personal and contemporary topics. A novella about Gilded Age Rhode Island, <title render="italic">Love's Random Dart</title>, came out in 1962, and the full-length novel, <title render="italic">Mexican Romance</title>, was published in 1969. At the same time, Curtis spent many years researching and writing a biography of Josiah Tattnall, a naval officer who became a commander in the Confederate Navy during the Civil War. Though she was not able to complete this book project, she distributed her research and writings to the National Archives and the Sophia Smith Collection in hopes that the work would be completed. She died in Dublin, New Hampshire on February 1, 1977 at the age of 83.</p>

<p>[NOTE: This biographical note also appears in a <extref href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edith_Roelker_Curtis">Wikipedia article</extref> and the text is available for modification and reuse under the terms of the 
<extref href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Text_of_Creative_Commons_Attribution-ShareAlike_3.0_Unported_License">Creative Commons Attribution-Sharealike 3.0 Unported License</extref> and the 
<extref href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Text_of_the_GNU_Free_Documentation_License">GNU Free Documentation License</extref>].</p>

    </bioghist>

    <scopecontent id="scope">
	
	<p>The Edith Roelker Curtis Papers document Curtis' literary output, family history and personal reflections. The collection of diaries, which were annotated by Curtis' granddaughter, Edith Byron, covers many years, beginning again in the mid-1920 and extending until the end of her life in 1977. There is also lesser amount of family correspondence and photographs. Curtis' introspections give a perspective on a life's journey that included a troubled marriage and complex family life; a struggle to make a career as a writer; and day-to-day observations of New England life, from Boston elite society to small town New Hampshire. The collection contains a large amount of material related to Curtis' writings, both published and unpublished. It includes research, correspondence with publishers, drafts, fan mail, reviews, and publications, which ranged from books that were well-received by scholarly audiences to pulp pieces in confessional magazines. In addition to books and articles, the collection contains unpublished poems and stories in which she took up themes of romance, interpersonal drama, and the pastoral alongside the travel narratives and historical vignettes that made up a large amount of her published work. Of interest is research and draft material from an unfinished biography of Josiah Tattnall, whose extensive naval career has not otherwise received scholarly attention.</p> 
    </scopecontent>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	
	<p>This collection has not been fully processed and is arranged in four accessions as received from the donor between 1962 and 2011:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">ACCESSION 1 (no accession number)</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">ACCESSION 2 (no accession number)</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser3">ACCESSION 3 (No. 03S-77)</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser4">ACCESSION 4 (No. 11S-25)</ref>
		</item>
	</list>
    </arrangement>
<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.  Please note that this collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>Copyright to unpublished works by Edith Roelker Curtis is owned by the Sophia Smith Collection. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use."  Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>"Edith Roelker Curtis Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass."</p>
    </prefercite>
    <accruals id="admin-accruals">
	<p>Periodic additions to this collection are expected. The collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
    </accruals>
    <acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
	<p>Edith Roelker Curtis donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection beginning in 1962.  Additions to the papers have been given by various family members.  Some materials were transferred from the Georgia Historical Society.</p> 
    </acqinfo>
    <processinfo id="admin-process">
	<p>Finding aid written by Amanda Izzo, May 2011.</p> 
    </processinfo>

<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Biographers -- United States -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Diaries -- Women authors</genreform> 
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Naval operations</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Authors, American -- 20th century -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Brook Farm Phalanx (West Roxbury, Boston, Mass.) -- History -- Sources</corpname> 
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Massachusetts  --  History  --  20th century  --  Sources</geogname> 
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Naval operations</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Poets, American -- 20th century -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Family -- New England -- History -- 20th Century -- Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">New England -- Description and travel -- Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Poets, American -- 20th century -- Biography -- Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women authors -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Hutchinson, Anne, 1591-1643</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Lennox, Sarah, Lady, 1745-1826</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Tattnall, Josiah, 1795-1871</persname> 
    </controlaccess>
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->
    <relatedmaterial id="add-related">
	<p>Related materials can be found in the Curtis-Iselin Family Papers.</p>
    </relatedmaterial>

<!-- End additional information -->


<!-- Enter Series descriptions -->

<!-- End Series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->

<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>ACCESSION 1 (no accession number)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box"/>
 <unittitle>Biographical</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Contents list</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence, Sophia Smith Collection</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Biography</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Literary clubs and societies, awards</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Clippings</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs of Edith Roelker Curtis (ERC)</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Date books <unitdate>  1964-74</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs of family and friends</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Large photos of ERC, slides, and travel postcards</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Law firm: Ropes, Gray, Boyden, Perkins</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Financial papers</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Son's report cards</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Family correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence with publishers</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Paperback project</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Re: Gregg Thompson</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle>Publications: <title render="italic">Anne Hutchinson </title> (1930)<title render="italic"> and Lady Sarah Lennox</title> (1946) </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Reviews and correspondence from Sophie Drinker</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Richard Hale</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>John Murray</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Putnam's Sons (publishers) and miscellaneous</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Ropes, Gray, Best, Coolidge, and Rugg (law firm)</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">6-7</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence re: <title render="italic">Lady Sarah Lennox</title>, miscellaneous</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Illustrations</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Reviews</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Fan mail</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <unittitle>Printer plates for <title render="italic">Lady Sarah Lennox</title></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <unittitle>Early draft and proofs, <title render="italic">Lady Sarah Lennox</title></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <unittitle>Publications: <title render="italic">Love's Random Dart </title> (1960)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Proofs</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Reviews and fan mail</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <unittitle>Publications: <title render="italic">A Season in Utopia</title> (1961)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Notes and research material</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Research material, Charles Fourier</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Material written by Arthur Eugene Bestor, Jr.</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Brook Farm Letters</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Photostat of letter to R.H. Dana, Sr., from George Ripley<unitdate> 1845</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence re: Brook Farm</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Article</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>Manuscript</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Reviews</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Fan mail</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>Publications: general</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Mexican Romance</title> (1969): reviews and fan mail</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Book reviews by Curtis, dated</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Book reviews, undated</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Poetry by Curtis, dated</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Poetry, undated</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <unittitle>Articles: includes fan mail, typescripts, and publications</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>"Visit Historic Homes" <unitdate>1939</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>"Yucatan Revisited" <unitdate>1947</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>"My Husband Had Another Wife"</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>"Border Crossing" <unitdate>1958</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>"The Comeback" <unitdate>1958</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>"I Remember Too" <unitdate>1959</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>"Sundays at Potowam" <unitdate>1959</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>"Mr. Hawthorne Arrives" <unitdate>1961</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>"The Palace that Will Shirley Built" <unitdate>1963</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>"Adventures of a Tyro Herb Grower" <unitdate>1966</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>"Bellamy's Utopia" <unitdate>1969</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>Housing Association of Boston correspondence and miscellany re: housing article</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Highlights in the Life of Amy Lowell</title> (play)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">17</container>
 <unittitle>Notes and drafts</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">18</container>
 <unittitle>Typescript</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">19</container>
 <unittitle>Programs and scripts</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">20</container>
 <unittitle>Fan mail</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">21</container>
 <unittitle>Plays, miscellaneous</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <unittitle>Unpublished, undated articles by topic</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Divorce</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Red Cross</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Travel</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <unittitle>Unpublished, undated articles by title</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <unittitle>A-I</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <unittitle>J-The I</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">12</container>
 <unittitle>The J-Z</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">12</container>
 <unittitle>Untitled</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">12</container>
 <unittitle>Publications: <title render="italic">The Tattnalls of Savannah</title></unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">13</container>
 <unittitle>Note cards</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">13</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Notes and typescripts</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">13</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">William Howard Allen</title> by Harold Cook, typescript</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">13</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence to Harold Cook</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">13</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Cook's notes and letters</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">13</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Other correspondence re: Tattnall sources</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">14</container>
 <unittitle>Note cards</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">14</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Lecture notes and course material, <title render="italic">How to Write for Money</title></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">14</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Suggestions for Writers of Informal Essays by M. Tanner</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">14</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Six Lessons in Fiction Writing by Anne Hamilton</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">14</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Patterns for Newspaper Writing</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">14</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Notes on Confess for Cash by Pauline Smith</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">14</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Description of New Hampshire profiles</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">15</container>
 <unittitle>2 Scrapbooks of art postcards</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">15</container>
 <unittitle>Gershwin sheet music</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">15</container>
 <unittitle>Photograph</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">15</container>
 <unittitle>Fashion drawings</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">15</container>
 <unittitle>Framed poem, oversize</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>ACCESSION 2 (no accession number)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Magazines with Curtis' articles: "True Experience" (1954); "Town and Country" (1947); and "Rhode Island History" (1947)</unittitle>
<unitdate>1947, 1954</unitdate>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Dublin, N.H. real estate records<unitdate> 1947</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Identification cards and records</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Improvements, Dublin house</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Writings, notebook</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Scrapbooks: writings and correspondence by Curtis</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Scrapbook: miscellaneous clippings (not about Curtis)</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Business and income taxes</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Divorce agreement</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Insurance and financial papers</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Financial ledgers [16]</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Xerox of "Civil War at Sea"</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Research related to the Shirley-Eustis House</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Radcliffe seminar papers<unitdate> 1970s?</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle>Josiah Tattnall project</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle>Writing notes, outlines, research materials, correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle>Manuscript, drafts and final</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <unittitle>Research material</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <unittitle>Manuscripts, drafts and final</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>ACCESSION 3 (No. 03S-77)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Biographical information by Edith Byron</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Diaries</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1916, 1926-27, 1930-38</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1939-42, 1951-59</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1960-73</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <unittitle><unitdate>1974-77</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <unittitle>Poetry typescripts, notes, and correspondence <unitdate>  1970s</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>ACCESSION 4 (No. 11S-25)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Published volumes and periodicals</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Anne Hutchinson</title> <unitdate>1930</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Lady Sarah Lennox</title> <unitdate>1946</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">A Season in Utopia: The Story of Brook Farm</title> <unitdate>1961</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle><title render="italic">Mexican Romance</title> <unitdate>1969</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>"A Season in Utopia," in <title render="italic">American Heritage</title> <unitdate>1959</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>"Blood Is Thicker than Water," in <title render="italic">American Neptune</title> <unitdate>1967</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>"Border Crossing," in <title render="italic">General Magazine and Historical Chronicle</title>, University of Pennsylvania <unitdate>1958</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>Manuscript, "Never Back Step" or "Aladino's Folly" [4 folders] <unitdate>circa 1965 </unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
