<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss323.html">mnsss323</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Association of Collegiate Alumnae Records, 1882-1917?</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
        <sponsor>Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</sponsor>
       </titlestmt>
       <publicationstmt>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
         <address>
           <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
         </address>
         <date calendar="gregorian" era="ce">© 2005</date>
         <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by
 Margaret Jessup and Jennifer Smar.
           <date>2006-04-07</date>
 <!-- CHANGE TO TODAY'S DATE IF NECESSARY -->
     </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter id="front">
    <titlepage>
      <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb/>Smith College<lb/></publisher>
   <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Association of Collegiate Alumnae Records, 1882-1917?</titleproper>
   <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
   <num>MS 325</num>

   <date encodinganalog="260$c">2005</date>
   
     <sponsor id="encoding_sponsor">Encoding funded by the Andrew W. Mellon
 Foundation.</sponsor>
       <p>© 2005  Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
   </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
 <did id="main">
 	<head>Collection Overview</head>
 <origination label="Creator:">
     <corpname encodinganalog="110" source="lcnaf">Association of Collegiate Alumnae
 (U.S.)</corpname>
 </origination>
   <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Association of Collegiate Alumnae records</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1882-1917?</unitdate>
 <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 325</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">3 boxes</extent>
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(1.75 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
  <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>
    </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
 <!-- MRJ: EDIT ABSTRACT  -->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Collegiate association. The records contain reports, correspondence, announcements, publications, registers, and a scrapbook on topics relating to the education of women in the late 19th century, medical education of women, athletics for women; wages of working women, and school lunch programs.
    </abstract>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
    
       <p>In 1882 Marion Talbot, Alice Freeman (Palmer), Alice Hayes, Ellen Swallow Richards, and thirteen other women met in Boston to establish the Association of Collegiate Alumnae, uniting college graduates for "practical educational work."  Members of the first generation of college-educated women, they had struggled for an education only to find that society had no place for them and no interest in utilizing their abilities.  Through the new organization (ACA), they hoped to promote and raise standards for women's higher education.  To distinguish themselves from normal-school and academy graduates, they limited membership to alumnae of specified, carefully selected four-year colleges and universities.  Additionally, they expected the ACA to help end the social isolation often faced by women college graduates when they returned home.  Women in other regions responded enthusiastically and set up ACA branches across the country.  Founded in 1901, the Southern Association of College Women served a similar community.  In 1921 the ACA and the SACW merged, forming the American Association of University Women.  Although the ACA, the SACW, and later the AAUW were committed to equal access to education, they avoided identification as explicitly feminist organizations.  Until the 1970s, AAUW leaders rejected controversial and potentially divisive issues like suffrage and the Equal Rights Amendment.</p>

     <p>During its first fifty years, the ACA studied a variety of issues related to women's education. Its members addressed the status of women within the academy by lobbying for women to serve as college trustees, fought discrimination on coeducational campuses, and argued for inclusion in the curriculum of home economics courses designed to make homemaking more professional and scientific.  Additionally, the ACA provided fellowships for undergraduate, graduate, and postdoctoral study, and encouraged women's careers, particularly in the social sciences.  Activities of regional branches and local groups of the ACA varied a good deal.  The internationalism of the war years carried over into the 1920s, when the AAUW joined similar organizations from eight other countries to promote women's education around the world and to create an international community of college women through the International Federation of College Women.</p>

</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
       <p>The records of the Association of Collegiate Alumnae (1882-1917?) contain 1.75 linear feet of material, including announcements, registers, the "A.C.A. Journal" (1918), a scrapbook, and committee, financial, and branch reports.  The records contain correspondence (1906-08) relating to living wage of college women and accompanying investigations, including letters to Ellen Richards, 1842-1911, and to internationalist and pacifist Fannie Fern Andrews, 1867-1950. Pamphlets of special interest concern the medical education of women, college entrance requirements, history of the A.C.A., Domestic Reform League, comparative statistics on colleges (1904), university extension programs, alumnae gifts, athletics for women (1897), wages of working women (1896), school lunch programs (1898), and a bibliography on higher education of women (1897).</p>

            <p> NOTE: The container list for this collection is available in the Sophia Smith Collection.  Please contact us to request a copy.</p>

</scopecontent>

     <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
      <head>Information on Use</head>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
         <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
          <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection.</p>

        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
         <p>Copyright to unpublished materials may be  owned by the creator, or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
        </userestrict>
    </descgrp>
      <prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Association of Collegiate Alumnae Records, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith
College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>
</descgrp>

   <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
       <head>Search Terms</head>
<!-- HIGHLIGHT EACH SEARCH TERM AND CLICK ON APPROPRIATE SUBJECT CLIPS -->
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women college graduates--United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Education--United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Employment--United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Association of Collegiate Alumnae (U.S.)--History--Sources</corpname> 
    <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">American Association of University Women--History--Sources</corpname> 

 </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
