<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
 <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
     <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss584.xml//EN">mnsss584</eadid>
	<filedesc>
	  <titlestmt>
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Alison Bechdel Papers, 1984-2013</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by .</author>
		 
	  </titlestmt>
	  <publicationstmt>
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
		<date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2015">2015</date>
	  </publicationstmt>
	</filedesc>
	<profiledesc>
	  <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Jasmine Jones. 
		<date normal="2015-11-02">2015-11-02</date>
	  </creation>
	  <langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	  </langusage>
	</profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
	<origination label="Creator:">
		<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Bechdel, Alison, 1960-</persname>
	</origination>
	<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Alison Bechdel Papers</unittitle>
	<unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1984-2013</unitdate>
	
	<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">633</unitid>
	
	<physdesc label="Quantity:">
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">36 boxes</extent>
		<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(26.75 linear ft.)</extent>
	</physdesc>
	<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:"><language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
	<repository label="Location:">
		<corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
		<address>
		  <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
		  <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
		</address>
	</repository>
	<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
		This collection is comprised of materials related to works created by Alison Bechdel. It includes business correspondence, character and topic development files, manuscript edits, press interviews, reviews, press releases, and a broad range of texts, sketches, and notes that formed the basis for Bechdel's work from the mid-1980s through the early 2000s.
	</abstract>
    </did>


<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
    <bioghist id="bioghist">
	<head>Biographical Note</head>
	<p>Alison Bechdel was born in Lock Haven, Pennsylvania to Bruce Allen Bechdel--high school English teacher, antiques dealer, and funeral director--and Helen Fontana Bechdel--high school English teacher and amateur actress. Her family also owned and operated a funeral home, dubbed the Fun Home by Bechdel and her two brothers.</p>

<p>Bechdel earned her A.A. in 1979 from Simon's Rock Early College (now Simon's Rock of Bard College) and her B.A. from Oberlin College in 1981. She applied to many art schools but was rejected. She worked in various publishing industry office jobs in New York City from 1981 to 1985, and as a production writer for Equal Time in Minneapolis, MN from 1986 to 1990.  According to the autobiographical <title render="italic">The Indelible Alison Bechdel</title>, she began "Dykes to Watch Out For" (DTWOF) as a single drawing labeled: "Marianne, dissatisfied with the morning brew: Dykes to Watch Out For, plate no. 27." An acquaintance recommended she send her work to <title render="italic">Womannews </title>newspaper, which began publishing the strip regularly beginning with the July-August 1983 issue. After a year, other outlets began running the strip, and it was syndicated in 1985.</p> 

<p>In 1988, Bechdel began a short-lived, page-length strip about the staff of a queer newspaper, titled <title render="italic">Servants to the Cause</title>, for <title render="italic">The Advocate</title> newspaper. The success of DTWOF allowed Bechdel to quit her day job in 1990 to work on the strip full-time. Bechdel has written and drawn autobiographical strips, has done illustrations for magazines and websites, and has written numerous books, including <title render="italic">Dykes to Watch Out For</title> (1986), <title render="italic">More Dykes to Watch Out For</title> (1988),<title render="italic"> New Improved! Dykes to Watch Out For</title> (1990), <title render="italic">Unnatural Dykes to Watch Out For</title> (1995), <title render="italic">Hot, Throbbing Dykes to Watch Out For</title> (1997), <title render="italic">The Indelible Alison Bechdel: Confessions, Comix and Miscellaneous Dykes to Watch Out For</title> (1998), <title render="italic">Dykes and Sundry Other Carbon-based Life-Forms to Watch Out For</title> (2003), <title render="italic">Invasion of the Dykes to Watch Out For</title> (2005), <title render="italic">Fun Home: A Family Tragicomic</title> (2006), and <title render="italic">The Essential Dykes to Watch Out For</title> (2008). Four of Bechdel's books have won Lamba Literary Awards for humor, and <title render="italic">The Indelible Alison Bechdel</title> won a Lambda Literary Award in the biography/autobiography category. In February 2004, Bechdel married her partner since 1992, Amy Rubin, in a civil ceremony in San Francisco; they separated in 2006.</p>
    </bioghist>



<!-- End collection level metadata -->


<!-- Enter administrative information -->
    <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
	<p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection with the following caveats:
   <list>
	<item>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</item>
	<item>Partially restricted access - contact the Sophia Smith Collection for more information.</item>
   </list></p>
    </accessrestrict>
    <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
	<p>The material in this collection may be protected by copyright. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights for permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Permission must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
    </userestrict>
    <prefercite id="admin-cite">
	<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
	<p>Alison Bechdel Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
    </prefercite>
    <accruals id="admin-accruals">
	<p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this finding aid.</p>
    </accruals>


<!-- End administrative information -->


<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->
    <controlaccess id="subj">
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Cartoonists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian artists--United States</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbianism in art</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbianism--United States--Caricatures and cartoons</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbian feminism--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Lesbians--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">American wit and humor, Pictorial</subject>
    </controlaccess>	
<!-- end controlled access terms -->


<!-- Enter additional information -->

<!-- End additional information -->


<!-- Enter Series descriptions -->

<!-- End Series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here:-->

<!-- End container list -->

  </archdesc>
</ead>
