<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss393.html">mnsss393</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Anna Steese Richardson Papers, 1905-1949</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       </titlestmt>
       <publicationstmt>
         <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
         <address>
           <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
         </address>
         <date calendar="gregorian" era="ce">© 2006</date>
         <p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
     <creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by
 Margaret Jessup.
          <date>2006-12-01</date>
     </creation>
      <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter id="front">
    <titlepage>
      <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb/>Smith College<lb/></publisher>
   <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Anna Steese Richardson Papers, 1905-1949</titleproper>
   <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
   <num>MS 545</num>
   <date encodinganalog="260$c">2006</date>
   

       <p>© 2006 Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
   </titlepage>
 </frontmatter>
 <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
 <did id="main">
 	<head>Collection Overview</head>
 <origination label="Creator:">
     <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Richardson, Anna Steese Sausser, 1865-</persname>
 </origination>
   <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Anna Steese Richardson papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1905-1949</unitdate>
 <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 545</unitid>
  <physdesc label="Quantity:">
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">9 boxes</extent>
          <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(9 linear ft.) </extent>
  </physdesc>
    <langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
      <language langcode="eng">English</language>

  </langmaterial>
         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>
 <!-- MRJ: EDIT ABSTRACT  -->
      <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">Journalist; Editor; Playwright. Collection includes books and pamphlets by Richardson, biographical material, and a small amount of correspondence. Scrapbooks contain newspaper and magazine articles collected by Richardson on suffrage, women's rights, courtship, marriage, divorce, etiquette, citizenship, civic affairs, consumerism, politics, child-rearing, changing cultural and social mores, and women's clubs. Two scrapbooks focus on the theater and contain clippings about plays by Richardson. 
NOTE: There is no container list online for this finding aid.  You may contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you want one sent to you.
    </abstract>
</did>
<bioghist id="bioghist">
    
       <p>Anna Steese Richardson was born in Ohio, and raised by her aunts and grandmothers in Philadelphia after the early death of her mother. Around 1883, after acquiring a Normal School diploma, she took a teaching job in Colorado. She married William Richardson, with whom she had three children; they later divorced.  Richardson ran their household in Council Bluffs, Iowa, and also reported news for the local daily newspaper.  In 1900, Richardson and her family moved to New York where she began writing feature articles for the women's page of the New York World. Richardson went on to write for many newspapers and magazines, often covering theatre.  She reported on and helped to shape the evolving themes of the twentieth century, particularly as related to women.</p>

	<p>An activist at heart, Richardson founded the Better Babies Bureau to which can be traced much of modern health work for mothers and infants. Richardson worked as a war correspondent  for the Companion, McClure's, and the Pictorial Review during World War I in France.  She later founded the Good Citizenship Bureau for the purpose of educating women in civic responsibility.</p>  

	<p>Best known as an editor and columnist of the Woman's Home Companion beginning in 1903, Richardson's career also included newspaper reporting, journalism, and play-writing. She achieved Broadway success with "Big Hearted Herbert," co-authored by Sophie Kerr in 1933, which was made into a movie. In 1936 Richardson, as Associate Editor of the Woman's Home Companion and Director of the Good Citizenship Bureau, was awarded an honorary degree of Master of Science in Business Administration by Bryant College in Providence, Rhode Island. The same year she also received the Advertising &amp; Selling Silver Medal for "distinguished exposition of advertising as a social force," and was one of twenty-four women honored at the Career Women's Dinner. Richardson died at her home in New York City.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
       <p>Scrapbooks containing articles by Richardson concerning women's issues, clipped from newspapers and magazines.  Topics include suffrage and women's rights; courtship, marriage, and divorce; etiquette; citizenship and civic affairs; consumerism; politics; child- rearing; changing cultural and social mores; and women's clubs. Two scrapbooks about the theater are included, one of which contains clippings about Big Hearted Herbert, a play co- authored by Richardson. There are also books and pamphlets by Richardson, biographical information, and a small amount of correspondence.</p>
      <p> NOTE: There is no container list online for this finding aid.  You may contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you want one sent to you.</p>
</scopecontent>
 
     <descgrp id="admin" type="admininfo">
      <head>Information on Use</head>
      <descgrp type="admininfo">
         <head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
         <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
          <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia
Smith Collection.</p>
          <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to
use.</p>
        </accessrestrict>
        <userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
        <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
        </userestrict>
    </descgrp>
      <prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Anna Steese Richardson Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College,
Northampton, Mass.</p>
      </prefercite>
</descgrp>

   <controlaccess id="subj-subheads">
       <head>Search Terms</head>
<!-- HIGHLIGHT EACH SEARCH TERM AND CLICK ON APPROPRIATE SUBJECT CLIPS -->
    <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Richardson, Anna Steese Sausser, 1865-</persname> 
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Child rearing--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Citizenship-History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Consumer education--United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Courtship--United States--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Etiquette for women--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Marriage--United States--History</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Suffragists--United States--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Theater--United States--History--Sources</subject>
    <subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Societies and clubs--United States--History--20th century</subject>
 </controlaccess>

</archdesc>
</ead>
<!-- END OF FILE -->
