<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="MARC21" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">

  <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" publicid="-//us::mnsss//TEXT us::mnsss::mnsss451.xml//EN">mnsss451</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Miriam Meyers Ritvo Papers, 1958-2003 (ongoing)</titleproper>
        <subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
       <author encodinganalog="245$c">Finding aid prepared by Amy Hague.</author>
     </titlestmt>
     <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection</publisher>
        <address>
          <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
          <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
        </address>
         <date encodinganalog="260$c" normal="2008">2008</date>
         <p>Sophia Smith Collection. All rights reserved.</p>
       </publicationstmt>
     </filedesc>
     <profiledesc>
<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid exported into EAD from InMagic DB/Textworks 7.01. Encoded by Margaret Jessup.
         <date normal="2008-06-17">June 17, 2008</date>
    </creation>

    <langusage>Finding aid written in English.</langusage>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>

  <archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did id="main">
       <head>Collection Overview</head>
        <origination label="Creator:">
           <persname encodinganalog="100" source="lcnaf">Ritvo, Miriam Meyers, 1916-</persname>
       </origination>
       <unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Miriam Meyers Ritvo papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:" type="inclusive">1958-2003 (ongoing)</unitdate>

      <unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 296</unitid>

<physdesc label="Quantity:">
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">26 boxes</extent>
        <extent encodinganalog="300$a">(32.5 linear ft.) </extent>
</physdesc>

<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
     <language langcode="eng">English</language>
</langmaterial>
        <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

           <abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
            Professor, education; Dean, Lesley College; Sociologist; Director, Management Development for the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. The papers consist of Ritvo's writings and teaching materials (syllabi, class exercises, etc.). Research files cover the contemporary women's movement and organizational sociology, as well as women in employment, management training, and women in higher education. </abstract>
</did>

<bioghist id="bioghist">
       
     <p>Miriam Myers was born in Lawrence, MA, 1916.  She received an A.B. from Smith College in 1937.  In 1940, she married Meyer Ritvo.  The couple had two sons, Roger and James.  After earning an M.S. in education from Boston University in 1952, Ritvo did postgraduate work at Harvard Medical School where she directed two studies:  Psychiatric Concepts in Group Dynamics and Psychoanalytic Concepts and Social Psychiatry.  She was an assistant professor of behavioral science at Boston University, 1956-1970, and Dean of students and professor of education at Lesley College, 1970-?.  A pioneer in the fields of organizational development and women's studies curricula at the college level, Ritvo is the author (with Adelma Mooth) of Developing Supervisory Skills, 1966; Diagnosing the Professional Climate of Schools (with others), 1973; Developing the Supervisory Skills of the Nurse, 1974. She has contributed to many professional journals.</p>
</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
      
    <p>The Miriam Meyers Ritvo Papers consist of Ritvo's writings and teaching and training materials (syllabi, class exercises, etc.) and related correspondence, memoranda, reports and the like pertaining to Ritvo's work as a consultant to various organizations and corporations. The subject files cover the contemporary women's movement and organizational sociology, as well as women in employment, management training, and women in higher education.  Ritvo advocates the team approach to workplace cooperation and cohesiveness, which crosses over into her work in conflict resolution and pacifism, notably with Greek Cypriots; a relatively small number of documents about her work in Greece is included here.</p>
       <p>[NOTE: The contents list for this collection is not online.  Contact the Sophia Smith Collection if you would like one sent to you.]</p>
</scopecontent>

 <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506" id="admin-access">
                    <p>The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.</p>
                    <p>This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.</p>
</accessrestrict>

<userestrict encodinganalog="540" id="admin-use">
             <p>The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to the unpublished works by the creator of this collection.  Copyright to materials created by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights.</p>
</userestrict>

<prefercite id="admin-cite">
        <head>Preferred Citation</head>
          <p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
          <p>Miriam Meyers Ritvo Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
</prefercite>
<accruals encodinganalog="584" id="admin-accruals">
               <p>Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.</p>
</accruals>


<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
          <p>The papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection by Miriam Meyers Ritvo in 1994.</p>
</acqinfo>
<processinfo id="admin-process">
          <p>Processed by Amy Hague, 1995. </p> 
</processinfo>
<controlaccess id="subj">

	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Civil service--Massachusetts--History--Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Lesley College--History--Sources</corpname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Organizational change--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Ritvo, Miriam Meyers, 1916-</persname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Education (Higher)--Massachusetts--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's studies--United States--Curricula</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Employment--Massachusetts--20th century</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's studies--History--20th century</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women's studies--History--20th century--Sources</subject>
</controlaccess>
</archdesc>
</ead>
