<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">
  <eadheader audience="internal" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" id="head" langencoding="iso639-2" repositoryencoding="iso15511" scriptencoding="iso15924">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="mnsss" url="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss406.html">mnsss406</eadid>

	<filedesc>
		<titlestmt>
			<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Alice Morgan Wright Papers, 1873-1994</titleproper>
			<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle>
			<author encodinganalog="245$c">Indus Chadha</author>
		</titlestmt>
		<publicationstmt>
			<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College</publisher>
			<address>
				<addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
			</address>
			<date encodinganalog="260$c">2007</date>
			<p>Smith College. All rights reserved.</p>
		</publicationstmt>
</filedesc>
<profiledesc>
	<creation encodinganalog="500">Finding aid encoded in NoteTab Pro. Encoded by Margaret Jessup. 
		<date>2007-05-03</date>
	</creation>
	<langusage>Finding aid written in
		<language encodinganalog="546" langcode="eng" scriptcode="latn">English</language>
	</langusage>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>

  <frontmatter id="front"> 
	 <titlepage> 
		<publisher encodinganalog="260$b">Sophia Smith Collection<lb />Smith College</publisher> 
		<titleproper encodinganalog="245$a">Alice Morgan Wright Papers, 1873-1994</titleproper>
		<subtitle>Finding Aid</subtitle> 
		<num>MS 176</num> 
		<author encodinganalog="245$c">Indus Chadha</author> 
		<date encodinganalog="260$c">2007</date> 
				 
		<p>© 2007 Smith College. All rights reserved.</p> 
	 </titlepage> 
  </frontmatter> 

<archdesc level="collection" relatedencoding="MARC21">
<did id="main">
	<head>Collection Overview</head>
		<origination label="Creator:">
			<persname encodinganalog="100 1" source="lcnaf">Wright, Alice Morgan</persname>
		</origination>
		<unittitle encodinganalog="245$a" label="Title:">Alice Morgan Wright Papers</unittitle><unitdate label="Dates:">1873-1994</unitdate>
		<unitid countrycode="us" encodinganalog="099" label="Collection Number:" repositorycode="mnsss">MS 176</unitid>
		
		<physdesc label="Quantity:">
			<extent encodinganalog="300$a">11 boxes</extent>
			<extent encodinganalog="300$a">(4 linear ft.)</extent>
		</physdesc>
		<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language of Material:">
			<language langcode="eng">English</language>
		</langmaterial>

         <repository label="Location:">
            <corpname>Sophia Smith Collection</corpname>
            <address>
               <addressline>Smith College</addressline>
               <addressline>Northampton, MA</addressline>
            </address>
         </repository>

		<abstract encodinganalog="520$a" label="Abstract:">
			Sculptor, Suffragist, Animal welfare advocate. Papers include biographical material, correspondence, writings, postcards, scrapbooks, artwork and photographs of her work as a sculptor; subject files, and memorabilia. Wright's career as a sculptor and her activism are well-documented; personal material is more fragmentary. Topics include art, women's suffrage, women's rights, women companions, birth control, world peace, and animal welfare.  Notable correspondents include Florence E. Allen, Emily Greene Balch, Mary Ellen Chase, Helen Keller, Stella Newsome, Ada Comstock Notestein, Emmeline Pankhurst, Alice Paul, Emmeline Pethink-Lawrence, Adlai S. Stevenson, Elisabeth Telling, Mary E. Woolley, Edith J. Goode (Wright's lifelong partner), and her mother, Emma Morgan Wright.
		</abstract>
</did>

<!-- Enter collection level metadata -->
<bioghist id="bioghist">
<head>Biographical Note</head>
 <dao actuate="onLoad" altrender="right" href="http://www.smith.edu/libraries/libs/ssc/eadfiles/ssc2196.jpg" linktype="simple" show="embed">
<daodesc><p>Alice Morgan Wright and friend, n.d.</p></daodesc></dao>
<p>Alice Morgan Wright, sculptor, suffragist, and animal welfare advocate, the daughter of Henry Romeyn Wright, a prosperous wholesale grocer, and Emma Jane Morgan, was born on October 10, 1881, in Albany, New York. She attended the St. Agnes School in Albany (now the Doane Stuart School) and then graduated from Smith College in 1904.</p>


<p>Wright worked for the Collegiate Equal Suffrage League and began studying sculpture at the Art Student League in New York City. In 1909 the League awarded her both the Gutzon Borglum and the Augustus Saint-Gaudens prizes for her outstanding art work. She went on to study art at the Académie des Beaux-Arts and at the Académie Colarossi in Paris. While in Europe, Wright involved herself in both the British and French suffrage movements. She organized a meeting in Paris at which English suffragist Emmeline Pankhurst spoke in 1910 and arranged for Pankhurst to make an appearance in Albany during her tour of the United States in 1911.</p> 
<p>During a suffrage demonstration, Wright was arrested and spent two months in London's Holloway Gaol. During this time she modeled a small bust of Emmeline Pankhurst, her prison-mate, with art supplies she had smuggled into the prison. When she returned to Paris she organized a petition drive demanding the release of jailed British suffragists. By 1913 Wright's art work had won several prizes, and had been exhibited in New York, Paris, and London. After returning home in 1914, she became the recording secretary of the New York State Women's Suffrage Party, and only returned full time to her sculpture after the passage of the Nineteenth Amendment.
</p>
<p>Wright's lifelong companion was Edith J. Goode, whom she met at Smith, and together they worked tirelessly for peace and justice. Wright's love of animals increasingly drew her to the cause of animal protection, and although she was heralded as one of the leading young American sculptors, art increasingly took a backseat to her reform activities. By 1945 she was devoting all her time to the cause, founding the National Humane Education Association, and working with various other animal protection organizations. Russell Sage College awarded her an honorary degree in 1947. Wright died in Albany at the age of 93, on April 8, 1975.</p>

</bioghist>
<scopecontent id="scope">
<head>Scope and Contents of the Collection</head>
<p>The Alice Morgan Wright Papers include biographical material, correspondence, writings, postcards, scrapbooks, artwork and photographs of her work as a sculptor; subject files, and memorabilia.   Wright's career as a sculptor and her activism are well-documented; personal material is more fragmentary.   Topics include art, women's suffrage, women's rights, women companions, birth control, world peace, animal welfare, the International Police Force and the United Nations, and Navajo Indians.  Her postcards provide a vivid and interesting account of Wright's travels, especially her years as an art student in Paris. Also included are reminiscences of the Pankhursts and of Wright's confinement in Holloway Gaol where she spent two months after her arrest at a suffrage demonstration in England.</p> 
<p> Notable correspondents include Florence E. Allen, Emily Greene Balch, Mary Ellen Chase, Helen Keller, Stella Newsome, Ada Comstock Notestein, Emmeline Pankhurst, Alice Paul, Emmeline Pethink-Lawrence, Adlai S. Stevenson, Elisabeth Telling, Mary E. Woolley, Edith J. Goode (Wright's lifelong partner), and her mother, Emma Morgan Wright.</p>
</scopecontent>
<arrangement encodinganalog="351$a" id="scope-org">
	<head>Organization of the Collection</head>
	<p>This collection is organized into six series:</p>
	<list>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser1">SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1873-1990)</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser2">SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE (1909-78)</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser3">SERIES III. SCRAPBOOKS (1903-75)</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser4">SERIES IV. ARTWORK (1907-78)</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser5">SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES (1912-94)</ref>
		</item>
		<item>
			<ref target="list-ser6">SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS (1893-1970s)</ref>
		</item>

		<item>
			<ref target="list-serOV">OVERSIZE MATERIALS</ref>
		</item>
	</list>
</arrangement>


<!-- End collection level metadata -->

<!-- Enter administrative information -->

<descgrp id="admin">
	<head>Information on Use</head>
	<descgrp>
		<head>Terms of Access and Use</head>
		<accessrestrict id="admin-access">
			<p>The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.  </p>
		</accessrestrict>
		<userestrict id="admin-use">
			<p>Copyright ownership of the Alice Morgan Wright papers is unknown.  Copyright to materials created by persons other than Wright may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.</p>
		</userestrict>
	</descgrp>
 	<prefercite id="admin-cite">
		<head>Preferred Citation</head>
		<p>Please use the following format when citing materials from this collection:</p>
		<p>The Papers should be cited as: Alice Morgan Wright Papers, Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, Northampton, Mass.</p>
	</prefercite>
	<descgrp>
		<head>History of the Collection</head>
		<acqinfo id="admin-acqinfo">
			<p>Most of Alice Morgan Wright's papers were given to the Sophia Smith Collection by her cousin Elinor Wright Fleming (Mrs. Clark M. Fleming) in 1980. Wright herself had sent small increments earlier.  Photographs of Smith College, originally passed on to Ruth Sharp from the estate of Alice Morgan Wright, were sent to President Thomas Mendenhall in 1965 by Ruth and Lauriston Sharp.  In 1998 Ann Lee O'Connell Anderson '55 and Albert G. Anderson donated a watercolor painting of an unidentified young woman, done by Wright in 1916.  Betsy Fahlman donated additional materials pertaining to Wright's artwork in 1998.  Dorcas MacClintock gave biographical materials, including Betsy Fahlman's definitive work on Wright's sculpture, in 2003.</p> 
		</acqinfo>
		<processinfo id="admin-process">
			<p>Processed by Indus Chadha, 2007.</p> 
		</processinfo>
	</descgrp>
</descgrp>




<!-- End administrative information -->

<!-- Enter controlled access terms -->

<controlaccess id="subj">
<head>Search Terms</head>
	
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Animal welfare--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Art--Study and teaching--History--Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Europe--Description and travel--Sources</geogname> 
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Female friendship--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Humane education--History--Sources</subject>
	<geogname encodinganalog="651" source="lcsh">Paris (France)--Description and travel--Sources</geogname>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Sculptors--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Smith College--Students--History--Sources</corpname>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Suffragists--Great Britain--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Suffragists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women artists--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women sculptors--United States--Biography--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Suffrage--Great Britain--History--Sources</subject>
	<subject encodinganalog="650" source="lcsh">Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources</subject>
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Art Students League (New York, N.Y.)</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">New York State Woman Suffrage Party</corpname> 
	<corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcsh">Women's Party (Great Britain)</corpname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Pankhurst, Emmeline, 1858-1928</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Pethick-Lawrence, Emmeline, 1867-</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Whitehouse, Vira Boarman, 1875-</persname> 
	<persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Wright, Alice Morgan, 1881-1975</persname> 

</controlaccess>

<!-- end controlled access terms -->

<!-- Enter additional information -->
<descgrp id="addinfo" type="add">
<head>Additional Information</head>
<relatedmaterial id="add-related">
<head>Related Material</head>
<p>
Additional papers pertaining to Alice Morgan Wright are housed at the Albany Institute of History and Art (125 Washington Avenue, Albany, New York).</p>
<p>Sketches Wright made of classmates at Smith are present in the student files in the
<extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/smitharchives/list">Smith College Archives</extref>. Artwork by Wright can be seen around the Smith College campus: sculpture in Alumnae Gym; Doleman plaque on College Hall; and Seelye plaque on John M. Greene porch. Materials regarding the National Humane Education Society can be found in the
<extref href="http://asteria.fivecolleges.edu/findaids/sophiasmith/mnsss180_main.html">Miscellaneous Organizations Collection</extref> of the Sophia Smith Collection. </p>

</relatedmaterial>
<bibliography id="add-biblio">
<head>Bibliography</head>
<p>Additional biographical information can be found in <title render="italic">Notable American women</title>, 1607-1950; a biographical dictionary. Edward T. James, editor. Janet Wilson James, associate editor. Paul S. Boyer, assistant editor.    
(Cambridge, Mass. : Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1971- )    
</p>
</bibliography>
</descgrp>

<!-- End additional information -->

<!-- Begin series descriptions type="analyticover" -->
<dsc type="analyticover">

 <c01 level="series">
   <did>
 	<unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS <unitdate>(1873-1990)</unitdate></unittitle>
   </did>
	<note>
           <p>
                  <ref target="list-wlg38tributes">[See also SERIES IV. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES - WLG 1838 and WLG 1874 commemorative verse and writings]</ref>
	  </p>
	</note>

	<scopecontent>
	<p>This series contains articles, clippings, and notes by and about Wright. It also contains her telephone and address books. Materials pertaining to her education at Smith College, such as notebooks, sketchbooks, correspondence and the Ivy Oration by Wright, are also included. Awards and citations, including the honorary degree she received from Russell Sage College in 1947, speeches, memorabilia, and miscellaneous family material are contained in this series. Also present are her obituaries, her will, and the instructions to its executors.</p>
</scopecontent>
 </c01>

 <c01 level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE <unitdate>(1909-78)</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
<scopecontent>
	<p>Correspondence includes letters from Florence E. Allen, Emily Greene Balch, Mary Ellen Chase, Helen Keller, Stella Newsome, Ada Comstock Notestein, Emmeline Pankhurst, Alice Paul, Emmeline Pethink-Lawrence, Adlai S. Stevenson, Elisabeth Telling, and Mary E. Woolley. Postcards provide a vivid and interesting account of Wright's travels, especially her years as an art student in Paris, and include correspondence between Edith J. Goode, Wright's lifelong partner, and her mother, Emma Morgan Wright.</p>
</scopecontent>
 </c01>

 <c01 level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. SCRAPBOOKS <unitdate>(1903-75)</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
<scopecontent>
	<p>Wright's scrapbooks contain clippings pertaining to subjects that were of great interest to her. The Whiteface Mountain scrapbook focuses on current affairs. She devoted one scrapbook entirely to art clippings (1903-75, n.d.) and another to theatre programs and pictures (1904, n.d.). This series also includes a scrapbook entitled "For Alice Morgan Wright - A Friend of Pussy-Cats" (n.d.) containing animal pictures and poems that was probably compiled by a friend and gifted to Wright. </p>
</scopecontent>

 </c01>

 <c01 level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES IV. ARTWORK <unitdate>(1907-78)</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
<scopecontent>
	<p>This series contains Wrights artwork and related materials. It also includes the Mary Augusta Jordan medal presented to Wright; two metal plates for the L. Clarke Seelye bas relief done by her; various sketches and drawings - including those done for greeting cards for the National Humane Education Society; and the bookplate done for the Anna Cutler Fund, Smith College Library. The series also contains verse by Wright, clippings and writings about her artwork, exhibit catalogues and materials, and original artwork by others, including works by Shirley Thomson.</p>
</scopecontent>
 </c01>

 <c01 level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES <unitdate>(1912-94)</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
<scopecontent>
	<p>The subject files, like Wright's scrapbooks, contain materials pertaining to subjects that were of interest to her and with which she was actively involved. This series includes materials regarding animal protection; birth control; women's rights; the International Police Force and the United Nations; Navajo Indians; and Suffrage, including memorabilia, such as a knife and a hunger strike medal, of the time Wright spent in confinement in Holloway Gaol after her arrest at a suffrage demonstration in England.</p>
</scopecontent>
 </c01>

 <c01 level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS <unitdate>(1893-1970s)</unitdate>
</unittitle>
 </did>
<scopecontent>
	<p>This series contains portraits of Wright; and photographs of her with friends, animals, and her artwork. There are photographs pertaining to Smith College, including photographs of John M. Greene, and of Wright's classmates.  The series also contains a sub series devoted entirely to photographs of Wright's artwork - contact prints of her artwork and studio, bas relief (including the one of L. Clarke Seelye), busts, and sculpture. Another sub series contains various negatives.</p>
</scopecontent>
 </c01>

 <c01 level="series">
    <did>
 	<unittitle>OVERSIZE MATERIALS</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c01>
</dsc>

<!-- End series descriptions -->

<!-- Insert container list here -->
<dsc id="list-contlist" type="in-depth">
 <c01 id="list-ser1" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Contents</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Articles, clippings, and notes by and about A.M.W</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>General,<unitdate> 1918-90, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>"Alice Morgan Wright <unitdate>(1881-1975),</unitdate>" by Marla Frances Wagshal, 1978</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Telephone and address books (5)</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">1</container>
 <unittitle>Index cards with addresses</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Education: Smith College</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Notebook, correspondence and ivy oration by AMW,<unitdate> 1903-63, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>"Verses," notebook with notes and sketches, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <unittitle>"A. Morg. Wright," sketchbook with notes, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Awards and citations</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous,<unitdate> 1948-71, n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
<note><p><ref target="list-serOV">[see also Oversize Materials]</ref></p></note>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Russell Sage College Honorary Degree,<unitdate> 1947</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Speeches,<unitdate> 1948, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Memorabilia,<unitdate> 1908-53, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Obituaries,<unitdate> 1967-75</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Will and instructions to executors,<unitdate> 1954-67</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">2</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous family material,<unitdate> 1873-1946, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser2" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous correspondence with and regarding family,<unitdate> 1941, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>A-Z (includes Florence E. Allen, Mary Ellen Chase, Helen Keller, Stella Newsome, Ada Comstock Notestein, Alice Paul, Adlai S. Stevenson, Elisabeth Telling, Mary E. Woolley),<unitdate> 1910-78, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Balch, Emily Greene,<unitdate> 1948, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Benoit, Maria<unitdate>. 1948, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Bispham, David,<unitdate> 1917</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Gobinot, B.,<unitdate> 1946, 1969</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Grierson, Margaret S. and Marine Leland (includes letters to Edith Goode),<unitdate> 1947-63, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Guilbert, Yvette,<unitdate> 1917, 1920</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Lefaucheux, Marie Helene,<unitdate> 1949-50</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Lutz, Bertha,<unitdate> 1947-52, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Mehta, Shrimati Hansa,<unitdate> 1948-53</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Menon (Pandit), Vijaya Lakshmi,<unitdate> 1949-62, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Pankhurst, Emmeline,<unitdate> 1911-13</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>Pethick-Lawrence, Emmeline,<unitdate> 1912, 1948-52</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Pethick-Lawrence, Frederick,<unitdate> 1948-57</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>Shepard, Edith,<unitdate> 1909-13, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">17</container>
 <unittitle>Undset, Sigrid,<unitdate> 1941</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">18</container>
 <unittitle>Whitehouse, Vira B.,<unitdate> 1918-20</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">19</container>
 <unittitle>Unidentified,<unitdate> 1912-57, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">3</container>
 <container type="folder">20</container>
 <unittitle>Business,<unitdate> 1910-51 </unitdate>(includes Ruth Benedict)</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Postcards</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>From AMW to the Wright family,<unitdate> 1908-27, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>From AMW to parents and others,<unitdate> 1909-31, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>To AMW, <unitdate>circa 1905-31, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">4</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous unidentified,<unitdate> 1910-30, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser3" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES III. SCRAPBOOKS </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Whiteface Mountain Amendment (1),<unitdate> 1941</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Whiteface Mountain Amendment (2),<unitdate> 1941</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Art clippings,<unitdate> 1903-75, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">5</container>
 <unittitle>Theatre programs and pictures,<unitdate> 1904, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">6</container>
 <unittitle>"For Alice Morgan Wright - A Friend of Pussy-Cats," <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser4" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES IV. ARTWORK </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>"Pastorale" bas relief; bronze medal for fifty years of service at the College of the City of New York,<unitdate> 1907</unitdate>; Mary Augusta Jordan medal; 2 metal plates for the L. Clarke Seelye bas relief</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Sketches and drawings</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>"Elizabeth Edmond," sketchbook with notes, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Betsy Fahlman</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence,<unitdate> 1974-75</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>"Catalogue of works of sculpture contained in the studio of Alice Morgan Wright <unitdate>(1881-1975),</unitdate>" 1975</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>"Sculpture and Suffrage: The Art and Life of Alice Morgan Wright,<unitdate> 1881-1975,</unitdate>" catalogue of exhibition at Albany Institute of Art, 1978</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>Drawings, mostly greeting cards, for National Humane Education Society, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <unittitle>Bookplate done for Anna Cutler Fund, Smith College Library, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Clippings,<unitdate> 1911-75, n.d.</unitdate>
</unittitle>
 <note><p><ref target="list-ser3">[see also SERIES III. SCRAPBOOKS]</ref></p></note></did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Exhibit catalogues and materials,<unitdate> 1915-78, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous,<unitdate> 1910-75, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>Original artwork by others, including works by Shirley Thomson,<unitdate> 1912-39, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">7</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Verse by Alice Morgan Wright, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser5" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES V. SUBJECT FILES </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Animal protection</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence,<unitdate> 1952-67, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Humane Society of the United States,<unitdate> 1954-79</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous,<unitdate> 1946-66, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>National Humane Education Society,<unitdate> 1949-94, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
<note><p>[see also Miscellaneous file above]</p></note></did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>UNESCO and UN,<unitdate> 1950-59, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Birth control: correspondence (letters from Margaret Sanger, others at Planned Parenthood, and A. H. Askanasy),<unitdate> 1948-61, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">7</container>
 <unittitle>Women's rights,<unitdate> 1948-50, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">8</container>
 <unittitle>International Police Force and UN,<unitdate> 1947</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">9</container>
 <unittitle>Navajo Indians, Toadlena, N.M.,<unitdate> 1932-34, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Suffrage</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Prison in England</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">10</container>
 <unittitle>Notes, writings, and memorabilia,<unitdate> 1912, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">11</container>
 <unittitle>Correspondence: letters from, and visiting cards of, French associates,<unitdate> 1912, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 <c04>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">12</container>
 <unittitle>Mementos: hunger strike medal and knife, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c04>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">13</container>
 <unittitle>Clippings,<unitdate> 1912-17, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">14</container>
 <unittitle>Miscellaneous,<unitdate> 1915-16, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">15</container>
 <unittitle>Parade New York, <unitdate>Oct 1917: </unitdate>clippings</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">8</container>
 <container type="folder">16</container>
 <unittitle>United Nations: reports and "Christmas Message" by AMW,<unitdate> 1948, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-ser6" level="series">
 <did>
 <unittitle>SERIES VI. PHOTOGRAPHS </unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Alice Morgan Wright,<unitdate> 1893- circa 1970s, n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>AMW and others: art classes, studio, and with animals, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Others: studio, miscellaneous, and unidentified, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">4</container>
 <unittitle>AMW and a friend: glass negatives, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Smith College</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>John M. Greene and others, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">9</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Classmates from scrapbook, n.d. <unitdate>(circa 1902-07)</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Artwork</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>Contact prints of artwork and studio, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">2</container>
 <unittitle>Bas reliefs, <unitdate>n.d. </unitdate>(Seelye circa 1914; Doleman circa 1922)</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">3</container>
 <unittitle>Busts, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">4-5</container>
 <unittitle>Sculpture, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">10</container>
 <container type="folder">6</container>
 <unittitle>Artwork by others, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
 <unittitle>Negatives</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">1</container>
 <unittitle>AMW in New York State Suffrage Party booth, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">2-4</container>
 <unittitle>Artwork and studio, n.d. <unitdate>(circa 1910-13)</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 <c03>
 <did>
 <container type="box">11</container>
 <container type="folder">5</container>
 <unittitle>Friends and animals, <unitdate>n.d.</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c03>
 </c02>
 </c01>
 <c01 id="list-serOV" level="series">
    <did>
 	<unittitle>OVERSIZE MATERIALS (Flat file)</unittitle>
 </did>
 <c02>
 <did>
<container type="box">12</container>
 <unittitle>Art folio of original drawings and sketches by Alice Morgan Wright</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
<container type="map-case">Flat file</container>
 <unittitle>Certificate from the Women's Social and Political Union, signed by Emmeline Pankhurst</unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
<container type="map-case">Flat file</container>
 <unittitle>"Clacton's Welcome to Released Suffragettes": clipping, <unitdate>4 May 1912</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
<container type="map-case">Flat file</container>
 <unittitle>Suffrage Parade: clipping, <unitdate>4 Nov 1917</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 <c02>
 <did>
<container type="map-case">Flat file</container>
 <unittitle>Art show for cause of suffrage: poster from <title render="italic">New York Tribune</title> <unitdate>10 Oct 1915</unitdate></unittitle>
 </did>
 </c02>
 </c01>
</dsc>



<!-- End container list -->

</archdesc>
</ead>
